<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-04T11:15:14+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">디멘의 블로그</title><subtitle>이데아를 여행하는 히치하이커</subtitle><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The Kripke-Wittgenstein Paradox</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/07/03/kripkenstein/en" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Kripke-Wittgenstein Paradox" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/07/03/kripkenstein/kripkenstein-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/07/03/kripkenstein/en"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>This post was machine translated and has not yet been proofread. It may contain minor errors or unnatural expressions. Proofreading will be done in the near future.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Please note that section “2.2. Dispositional Analysis” contains considerable additional commentary by the author that is independent from Kripke’s original paper.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="overview">Overview</h3>

<p>Kripke argues that the core of Wittgenstein’s <em>Philosophical Investigations</em> lies in what is known as <strong>scepticism about rule following</strong>.</p>

<p>According to Kripke’s reading, §1-137 of the <em>Investigations</em> is where Wittgenstein criticises and overcomes the linguistic view of the <em>Tractatus</em>. In §138-242, scepticism about rule following is presented. The sceptical argument, which questions whether there exists a state of affairs corresponding to propositions such as “Alice means addition by ‘+’”, not only confirms §1-137 by showing that the linguistic view of the <em>Tractatus</em> cannot be correct, but also seems to suggest the devastating conclusion that no theory whatsoever that elucidates the problem of meaning is possible.</p>

<p>According to Kripke, Wittgenstein provides a “sceptical solution” to this. That is, whilst accepting the sceptic’s conclusion—that there is no state of affairs corresponding to “Alice means addition by ‘+’“—he elucidates how it can be used meaningfully, unlike propositions such as “green thoughts sleep”. This solution emphasises the <strong>publicity of language</strong>—that the meaning of language is inseparable from its function within a community, and therefore discussions of meaning are vacuous at the level of individual language users but valid at the level of linguistic communities.</p>

<p>From §243 onwards applies the “sceptical solution” to other philosophical problems. One implication of the sceptical solution is the impossibility of private language. Nevertheless, there are two representative areas of language that appear to operate in a private manner: mathematical language and psychological language. <strong>However, Wittgenstein argues that the idea that mathematical and psychological languages constitute private languages is a misconception.</strong> In this section, we can glimpse Wittgenstein’s distinctive positions in the philosophy of mathematics and psychology.</p>

<h2 id="1-the-kripke-wittgenstein-paradox">1. The Kripke-Wittgenstein Paradox</h2>

<p>The conclusion of the Kripke-Wittgenstein paradox is as follows:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Propositions of the form “Speaker $A$ means meaning $m$ by symbol $s$”<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> have no corresponding state of affairs. That is, such propositions lack truth values.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Therefore, for instance, the proposition “Alice means addition by ‘+’” is as incomprehensible as the proposition “Alice’s thoughts are green”.</p>

<h3 id="11-the-appearance-of-the-sceptic">1.1. The Appearance of the Sceptic</h3>

<p>Why then do Kripke and Wittgenstein make such an extreme claim? The core of the argument lies in an easily overlooked but genuinely contradictory aspect hidden in the process by which language users grasp the meaning of words: from <em>finite</em> past learning experiences, one must be able to make correct inferences about the <em>infinite</em> cases in which that word could be used.</p>

<p>For example, suppose Alice has never performed addition of two numbers both exceeding 50. Even so, if someone asked Alice ‘68 + 57’, she would readily answer ‘125’. But at this point, a sceptic approaches Alice and claims that her answer ‘125’ is wrong, and that the answer Alice should have given was ‘5’. Specifically, the sceptic claims the following:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If the meaning Alice assigned to ‘+’ in the past matches the meaning she assigns to ‘+’ in the present, then Alice should have answered ‘5’.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Because—at least according to the sceptic—the meaning Alice assigned to ‘+’ in the past was actually not addition (+) but <strong>quaddition</strong> (⨁). The definition of quaddition is as follows:</p>

\[x \oplus y =
\begin{cases}
x + y &amp; x, y &lt; 50 \\
5 &amp; \text{otherwise}
\end{cases}\]

<p>Alice would immediately object that she has used ‘+’ to mean addition, not quaddition, since the past. But here begins the real problem. <strong>How can it be proved that the meaning Alice assigned to ‘+’ in the past was addition rather than quaddition?</strong> Due to the assumption of the problem, it is impossible to prove this from the records of ‘+’ calculations that Alice performed in the past.</p>

<p>The expression ‘proof’ that has just appeared might make this problem seem epistemological (“How can we know that Alice means addition by ‘+’?”). However, what Kripke asks is whether even an omniscient observer who could see into Alice’s mind could know whether Alice means addition by ‘+’, or whether she means some non-standard operation that agrees with addition in sufficiently many cases. <strong>In this respect, the scepticism Kripke presents is ontological.</strong> The point of the problem is whether there is a state of affairs corresponding to “Alice means addition rather than quaddition”. This is revealed by the fact that Kripke goes on to examine attempts to resolve scepticism through counterfactual conditionals or possible worlds—though he concludes that these attempts also fail.</p>

<h3 id="12-two-conditions">1.2. Two Conditions</h3>

<p>There are two noteworthy points about the sceptic’s claim. <strong>Firstly, the sceptic’s claim is conditional.</strong> The sceptic is not claiming that Alice should answer ‘5’ <em>in any case</em>. What he claims is that if the meaning Alice assigned to ‘+’ in the past <em>matches</em> the meaning she assigns to ‘+’ in the present, then she should answer ‘5’. <strong>Secondly, the sceptic’s claim is normative.</strong> The sceptic’s claim is not that—when the aforementioned condition is satisfied—Alice <em>will</em> answer ‘5’, but that she <em>should</em> answer ‘5’.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> In other words, the sceptic claims that if Alice had answered ‘5’ to ‘68 + 57’, that answer <em>would have been justified</em>.</p>

<p>Therefore, any refutation of the sceptic’s claim must also have two characteristics. <strong>Firstly, it must explain what fact about a speaker constitutes that speaker’s use of a particular symbol with a particular meaning.</strong> This explanation is necessary to elucidate what the antecedent means in the sceptic’s claim.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> <strong>Secondly, it must explain how that fact justifies the speaker’s use of language.</strong> This explanation is necessary because the sceptic’s conclusion is normative.</p>

<p>The significance of the second condition may not be immediately apparent, so let me elaborate. Suppose some mad scientist approached the sceptic and said:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Actually, I once scanned Alice at the atomic level in the past. So after hearing your claim, I asked Alice-2, whom I created by copying that scan, ‘68 + 57’, and Alice-2 answered ‘125’. Therefore, past Alice did not mean quaddition by ‘+’.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>However, the mad scientist’s experiment is insufficient to refute the sceptic’s claim. This is because the mad scientist’s experiment does not satisfy the second condition. The result of that experiment only guarantees that Alice <em>would have</em> always answered ‘125’, but does not guarantee that Alice <em>should have</em> always answered ‘125’.</p>

<p>This can be understood more clearly through <strong>cases of systematic computational error</strong>. For instance, children learning addition often forget to carry. Such a child would answer ‘115’ rather than ‘125’ to ‘68 + 57’. Now suppose there is someone called Johnson who, due to some problem, has failed to correct his carrying mistakes even as an adult. Johnson understands what addition is, and when asked about properties of addition rather than specific addition problems—such as “Does it satisfy the associative law?”—he answers correctly. However, in situations where Johnson has no instructor to correct his mistakes, he would <em>always</em> have answered ‘115’ to ‘68 + 57’, and will continue to do so in future. We would want to claim that Johnson assigns the meaning of addition to ‘+’, but fails to answer ‘68 + 57’ in a <em>justified manner</em> according to that meaning. It is precisely to make this claim possible that the second condition is needed. If we adopt a semantics that fails to satisfy the second condition, we would have to accept that Johnson assigns to ‘+’ the meaning of <strong>baddition</strong>—an operation that performs addition without carrying—or <strong>maddition</strong>—an operation that performs baddition when no instructor is present and performs addition with the instructor’s correction when one is present.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup></p>

<h2 id="2-examination-of-refutations-of-scepticism">2. Examination of Refutations of Scepticism</h2>

<h3 id="21-linguistic-elucidation">2.1. Linguistic Elucidation</h3>

<p>The first answer Alice might give upon hearing the sceptic’s claim would probably be this: “In the past, I have assigned to ‘x + y’ the meaning of the operation of counting x objects and y objects together. Therefore, I did not use ‘+’ to mean quaddition in the past.”</p>

<p>However, the sceptic can deploy scepticism once again against this. In short, he can claim that in the past Alice consistently understood the word ‘count’ not as count but as <em>quount</em>. To quount a collection is to count it when the collection’s size is less than 50 and to answer 5 when it exceeds 50.</p>

<p>The point is that <strong>attempts to prove what meaning was assigned to ‘+’ through other linguistic evidence fall into infinite regress, as such evidence cannot eliminate the possibility that non-standard meanings were assigned to it as well</strong>.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup></p>

<h3 id="22-dispositional-analysis">2.2. Dispositional Analysis</h3>

<p>In philosophy of mind, <strong>dispositional analysis</strong> is the way behaviourism explains psychological states, with the core as follows:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Dispositional analysis of psychological states.</strong> For subject $A$ to be in psychological state $\mathfrak{m}$ in the past, present, or future means that if stimulus $s$ had been given / is given / will be given to $A$, then $A$ would have shown / will show / will show response $b = f_\mathfrak{m}(s)$. That is, psychological state ($\mathfrak{m}$) is reduced to stimulus-response correspondence ($f_\mathfrak{m}$).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For example, suppose Alice, having just awakened from a light sleep, formed the belief “it is raining now” upon hearing the dim room and the sound of water drops from outside the window. According to dispositional analysis, the meaning of “Alice believes ‘it is raining now’” is nothing different from the following (countless) stimulus-response correspondences:</p>

<ul>
  <li>If a friend calls to go eat together, -&gt; she will bring an umbrella.</li>
  <li>If a neighbour contacts her saying her laundry is hanging outside, -&gt; she will rush to collect the laundry.</li>
  <li>If an outdoor schedule is planned for tomorrow, -&gt; she will check tomorrow’s weather, etc…</li>
</ul>

<p>If phenomena significantly deviating from these stimulus-response correspondences are observed, the dispositional analyst would revise their view of Alice’s belief. For instance, if Alice went out but brought sunglasses instead of an umbrella, they would judge that Alice has the belief “the sun is shining brightly” rather than the belief “it is raining”.</p>

<p>Two characteristics of dispositional analysis to note from the explanation so far:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>It uses counterfactual conditionals.</strong> Even if Alice does not go out in the past, present, or future, “if Alice <em>had gone out</em> / <em>goes out</em> / <em>will go out</em>, she would have brought / will bring / will bring an umbrella” forms part of the dispositional analysis of the belief she had / has / will have.</li>
  <li><strong>It is descriptive.</strong> Because dispositional analysis is based on behaviourism, it consists of descriptive propositions such as “if Alice goes out, she <em>will</em> bring an umbrella” rather than normative propositions such as “if Alice goes out, she <em>should</em> bring an umbrella”. According to dispositional analysis, if Alice goes out but brings sunglasses instead of an umbrella, she does not have the belief that it is raining but is <em>failing</em> to act <em>justifiably</em> according to it; rather, she simply does not have the belief that it is raining in the first place.</li>
</ol>

<p>Kripke reports that some philosophers who discussed the rule-following paradox with him in private attempted to resolve the paradox through dispositional analysis by relying on the first characteristic of dispositional analysis. This approach claims the following:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Dispositional analysis of meaning.</strong> For speaker $A$ to mean meaning $\mathfrak{m}$ by symbol $s$ in the past, present, or future means that if sentence $\phi$ containing $s$ had been given / is given / will be given to $A$, then $A$ would have answered / will answer / will answer with sentence $\psi = f_\mathfrak{m}(\phi)$. That is, meaning ($\mathfrak{m}$) is reduced to question-answer correspondence ($f_\mathfrak{m}$).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>According to this analysis, for Alice to mean addition by ‘+’ in the past, present, or future means that when x + y had been asked / is asked / will be asked of Alice, $A$ would have answered / will answer / will answer with the sum of x and y. The train of thought of a philosopher attempting to overcome scepticism through such counterfactual conditionals would roughly be as follows:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The sceptic points out that there has been no state of affairs, and will be none in future, that distinguishes whether past Alice meant addition by ‘+’ or meant some non-standard operation that agrees with addition in sufficiently many cases but is not addition.</li>
  <li>The reason 1 can be claimed is that the number of ‘+’ operations Alice has performed and will perform is finite.</li>
  <li>However, if we use counterfactual conditionals such as “if ‘x + y’ <em>had been asked</em> of past Alice, I <em>would have answered</em> the sum of x and y” or “if ‘x + y’ <em>is asked</em> of future Alice, I <em>will answer</em> the sum of x and y”, we can overcome the finiteness of 2.</li>
  <li>Accordingly, if we accept the fact that counterfactual conditionals have objective truth values—through possible world ontology, etc.—the dispositional analysis of meaning objectively determines the operation that Alice means by ‘+’.</li>
</ol>

<p>This argument satisfies the first condition that any refutation of the sceptic must have—it must explain <em>what fact</em> about a speaker constitutes that speaker’s use of a particular symbol with a particular meaning. That fact is the counterfactual conditional. <strong>However, Kripke points out that dispositional analysis is insufficient to resolve the paradox because it fails to satisfy the second condition—it must explain how that fact <em>justifies</em> the speaker’s use of language.</strong> This is because, as noted earlier, dispositional analysis is essentially descriptive. To quote Kripke:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Well and good, I know that ‘125’ is the response I am disposed to give (I am actually giving it!), and maybe it is helpful to be told — <strong>as a matter of brute fact</strong> — that I <em>would have given</em> the same response in the past. <strong>How does any of this indicate that — now <em>or</em> in the past — ‘125’ was an answer <em>justified</em> in terms of instructions I gave myself, rather than a mere jack-in-the-box unjustified and arbitrary response?</strong></p>

  <p>(Italics in original, emphasis mine)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What Kripke points out can be understood step by step as follows. Recalling, any claim against the sceptic must have the following form:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Claim 1.</strong> If the meaning Alice assigned to ‘+’ in the past matches the meaning she assigns to ‘+’ in the present, then</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Alice should not answer ‘5’, but rather</li>
    <li>Alice should answer ‘125’.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>According to dispositional analysis, the above claim is synonymous with the following:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Claim 1.1.</strong> If Alice’s past question-answer disposition regarding ‘+’ matches Alice’s present question-answer disposition regarding ‘+’, then</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Alice should not answer ‘5’, but rather</li>
    <li>Alice should answer ‘125’.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>“As a matter of brute fact”, suppose Alice’s past question-answer disposition regarding ‘+’ was to state the sum when given two numbers. Substituting this fact above:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Claim 1.2.</strong> If Alice’s present question-answer disposition regarding ‘+’ is to state the sum when given two numbers, then</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Alice should not answer ‘5’, but rather</li>
    <li>Alice should answer ‘125’.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>However, even though Claim 1 has been restated as Claim 1.2, there is still no basis for establishing this. If the predicates in 1 and 2 were “<em>will answer</em>”, the claim would hold, but what is required is “<em>should answer</em>”. This is not a fact that can be known from question-answer dispositions alone.</p>

<p>Then could we not set the predicates in 1 and 2 as “<em>will answer</em>” from the beginning? That is, claiming the following to the sceptic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Claim 2.</strong> If the meaning Alice assigned to ‘+’ in the past matches the meaning she assigns to ‘+’ in the present, then</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Alice will not answer ‘5’, but rather</li>
    <li>Alice will answer ‘125’.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>This cannot be done. As explained in detail earlier in the “case of systematic computational error”, the fact that Alice did not answer ‘125’ to ‘68 + 57’ does not immediately suggest that Alice did not mean addition by ‘+’. We sometimes make mistakes in performing addition, but such mistakes do not mean that we used ‘+’ to mean something other than addition each time we made them. Rather, the very fact that I can make <strong>mistakes</strong> in performing ‘+’ operations suggests that it is not the computational results I produce that determine the meaning I assign to ‘+’, but conversely, the meaning I assign to ‘+’ that precedes and determines the result I <em>should produce</em>.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, to explain the normativity of meaning through dispositional analysis, one would seemingly have to reinterpret the sceptic’s challenge as follows:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Claim 3.</strong> If Alice <em>wants to make</em> the meaning she assigned to ‘+’ in the past match the meaning she assigns to ‘+’ in the present,</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Alice should not answer ‘5’, but rather</li>
    <li>Alice should answer ‘125’.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>This leads to the following statement:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Claim 3.1.</strong> If Alice’s present question-answer disposition regarding ‘+’ <em>wants to be</em> to state the sum when given two numbers,</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Alice should not answer ‘5’, but rather</li>
    <li>Alice should answer ‘125’.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>Certainly, Claim 3.1 appears more plausible than Claims 1.1 and 1.2. However, in my view, Claim 3.1 still has problems.</p>

<p><strong>The first problem is that even if Claim 3 holds, it does not suggest Claim 1.</strong> Let $p$ and $q$ be as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>$p:$ The meaning Alice assigned to ‘+’ in the past matches the meaning she assigns to ‘+’ in the present.</li>
  <li>$q:$ Alice answers ‘125’.</li>
</ul>

<p>In this case, Claim 1 and Claim 3 are respectively as follows ($W$ means “wants to” and $\Box$ means “should”):</p>

<ul>
  <li>Claim 1. $p \rightarrow \Box q$</li>
  <li>Claim 3. $Wp \rightarrow \Box q$</li>
</ul>

<p>However, since $p$ does not suggest $Wp$ (something I do not want can happen to me) and $Wp$ does not suggest $p$ either (something I want may not happen to me), there is no logical relationship between Claim 1 and Claim 3. Specifically, for the former case, there is the situation where a rebellious student who resolved to use ‘+’ to mean multiplication answers ‘125’ to ‘68 + 57’ out of habit, making his resolution meaningless. For the latter case, there is the case of a student who wants to use the ‘+’ symbol to mean addition but has not yet fully mastered the concept of addition.</p>

<p><strong>The second problem is that Claim 3 falls into infinite regress in the first place.</strong> For convenience of explanation, let me return to the case of psychological states. Converting the current problem to one about psychological states would be as follows: Alice can go out carrying something other than an umbrella despite having the belief that it is raining outside. For instance, consider a situation where Alice hurriedly prepared to go out and grabbed something from the umbrella stand before leaving the house, but what she grabbed was not an umbrella but a walking stick. According to existing dispositional analysis, in this case Alice did not have the belief that it was raining in the first place, which is a counter-intuitive conclusion. In response, the dispositional analyst might instead put forward the following claims:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Claim 4.</strong> If Alice <em>wants to make</em> the belief she formed in the past regarding ‘a dim room and the sound of water drops falling outside the window’ match the belief she forms in the present regarding the same situation,</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Alice should not bring a walking stick, but rather</li>
    <li>Alice should bring an umbrella.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Claim 4.1.</strong> If Alice <em>wants to make</em> the stimulus-response correspondence Alice would have shown regarding ‘a dim room and the sound of water drops falling outside the window’ match Alice’s present stimulus-response correspondence regarding the same situation,</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Alice should not bring a walking stick, but rather</li>
    <li>Alice should bring an umbrella.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Claim 4.2.</strong> If Alice’s stimulus-response correspondence regarding ‘a dim room and the sound of water drops falling outside the window’ <em>wants to be</em> to bring an umbrella in situations of going out,</p>
  <ol>
    <li>Alice should not bring a walking stick, but rather</li>
    <li>Alice should bring an umbrella.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>As mentioned earlier, Claim 4 is of the form $Wp \rightarrow \Box q$, so it has no logical relationship with $p \rightarrow \Box q$ in the first place, but even setting aside that problem, the seemingly plausible Claim 4.2 has an essential problem. The reason we attempt dispositional analysis in the first place is to translate statements about psychological states into behaviourist expressions. However, Claim 4.2 has merely changed a statement about one specific psychological state—the belief that it is raining outside—into a statement about another psychological state—the <em>intention to show</em> the response of bringing an umbrella in situations of going out. Now we must explain what ‘being in a state of wanting to show the response of bringing an umbrella in situations of going out’ means through dispositional analysis, which ultimately falls into infinite regress.</p>

<p>For the same reason, Claim 3 also falls into infinite regress. Recalling the earlier discussion, one necessary condition that any refutation of the sceptic’s claim must satisfy is to “explain what fact about a speaker constitutes that speaker’s use of a particular symbol with a particular meaning”. However, Claim 3.1 provides the answer “the intention to make question-answer dispositions match in a particular way” to this problem. The sceptic can then ask in return, “What fact about a speaker constitutes that speaker’s having the intention to make question-answer dispositions regarding the ‘+’ symbol match in a particular way—for instance, the question-answer disposition corresponding to addition rather than quaddition?”</p>

<p>In conclusion, attempts to solve the problem of meaning through dispositional analysis fail to explain the normativity of meaning. Attempts to force dispositional analysis to fit so as to explain normativity not only deviate from what the problem requires but also fall into the fallacy of infinite regress.</p>

<h3 id="23-mechanistic-approach">2.3. Mechanistic Approach</h3>

<p>Then, instead of relying on abstract explanations like linguistic elucidation or dispositional analysis, could we not respond to the sceptic by designing and presenting a concrete machine corresponding to the operation that ‘+’ means? For instance, creating a mechanical calculator or designing a full adder with logic circuits. However, Kripke argues that this attempt is also inappropriate for three main reasons.</p>

<p><strong>Firstly, the method of using the machine remains a problem requiring elucidation.</strong> Taking Turing machines as an example, we would interpret the binary sequences output by the Turing machine in binary notation to read the results. However, the sceptic can claim that the correct way to interpret this machine is in <em>quinary notation</em>, and according to quinary notation, the Turing machine is outputting quaddition, not addition.</p>

<p><strong>Secondly, actual machines can only receive finite inputs.</strong> In that sense, actual machines do not become more ‘capable’ entities than Alice. If instead of implementing an actual machine we present the algorithm of the machine, this returns us to “2.1. Linguistic Elucidation”.</p>

<p><strong>Thirdly, machines can malfunction.</strong> Someone might drop the machine causing gears to fall out, or wires might melt from overuse. Therefore, we cannot transfer the responsibility of meaning elucidation entirely to the machine and claim “this machine <em>always</em> calculates the operation I mean”. Nor can we claim “this machine <em>always calculates the operation I mean unless it malfunctions</em>”. To make such a claim, we would need to provide criteria for judging whether the machine is operating normally or malfunctioning, and those criteria would ultimately depend on what <em>intention</em> we wish to use this machine for (could not some eccentric designer create a machine that calculates addition through the falling out of gears and the melting of wires?). Therefore, the moment we use the expression <em>unless it malfunctions</em>, the speaker’s intention, not the machine, takes precedence.</p>

<h3 id="24-occams-razor">2.4. Occam’s Razor</h3>

<p>Kripke also considers the following claim:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Occamist semantics.</strong> When two hypotheses “Speaker $A$ means meaning $\mathfrak{m}_1$ by symbol $s$” and “Speaker $A$ means meaning $\mathfrak{m}_2$ by symbol $s$” are in an underdetermined state, we should preferentially accept the hypothesis of the simpler of $\mathfrak{m}_1$ and $\mathfrak{m}_2$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For example, consider the following two hypotheses:</p>

<p>    H1. Past Alice meant addition by ‘+’.</p>

<p>    H2. Past Alice meant quaddition by ‘+’.</p>

<p>Since both terms in Alice’s past ‘+’ operation records are 50 or below, H1 and H2 are in an underdetermined state. What Occamist semantics claims is that in this case we should preferentially accept the H1 hypothesis. This is because addition is a simpler operation than quaddition.</p>

<p>However, Kripke only briefly mentions and passes over this claim, because it is self-evident that it is inappropriate for refuting scepticism. This is not only because the predicate ‘simple’ is subjective, difficult to define, or because quaddition might be simpler than addition for Martians—though these reasons are also very legitimate. The more essential reason is that the conclusion of the sceptical argument is not “it is undetermined which of H1 and H2 is true”, but “it is undetermined <em>what state of affairs</em> the truth of either H1 or H2 <em>corresponds to</em>”. According to the sceptical argument, we are in a situation where we are not even certain whether H1 and H2 represent different states of affairs. If the states of affairs that hypotheses represent are so unclear, we cannot even <em>apply</em> Occam’s razor before considering whether its application is justified.</p>

<h3 id="25-psychologism">2.5. Psychologism</h3>

<p>A more important objection that Kripke considers is psychologism.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Psychologistic semantics.</strong> For speaker $A$ to mean $\mathfrak{m}$ by symbol $s$ means that a distinctive<sub>queer</sub> psychological experience $p_\mathfrak{m}$ corresponding to $\mathfrak{m}$ has formed in the speaker’s mind.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here, “distinctive psychological experience” can be thought of as similar to qualia. In short, just as “seeing red” is a distinctive experience that cannot be reduced to other predicates or experiences, so too is “meaning addition by ‘+’” such a distinctive experience.</p>

<p>Kripke does not deny the possibility that such distinctive experiences exist.<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup> However, Kripke points out that psychologistic semantics also fails to resolve the sceptical argument. The problem once again lies in condition 2 of “1.2. Two Conditions”.</p>

<p>As a simple example, suppose Alice feels pain in her forehead every time she uses the ‘+’ symbol. This fact satisfies condition 1 of “1.2. Two Conditions”. That is, for the meaning Alice assigned to ‘+’ in the past to be the same as the meaning she assigns in the present means that the past pain Alice felt when using the ‘+’ symbol is qualitatively the same as the present pain. However, how could that pain possibly inform Alice that she should answer ‘125’ to ‘68 + 57’?</p>

<p>Kripke connects this discussion to a more general empiricist refutation. According to empiricism, for me to mean ‘triangle’ is for me to conjure up an impression of a triangle in my mind. But how does this impression of a triangle inform me of the rule for using the word ‘triangle’? For instance, even if the impression that comes to my mind is an acute triangle, I can legitimately point to an obtuse triangle and call it a triangle. Conversely, I cannot point to a triangular prism with a base exactly the same shape as the impression in my mind and call it a triangle. In short, even when some impression is presented in the mind, how that impression should be <em>interpreted</em> remains shrouded in mystery.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, Kripke emphasises that we should not swing to the opposite extreme and conclude that psychological experiences or feelings are completely irrelevant to problems of meaning. Kripke mentions the following cases derived from discussions in the <em>Philosophical Investigations</em>:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semantic_satiation">The phenomenon where saying the same word dozens of times makes it feel ‘strange’, as if the meaning has drained out of the word leaving only a shell</a></li>
  <li>The difference between saying ‘bat’ whilst thinking of the animal versus thinking of the sports equipment (compare this to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necker_cube">Necker cube</a> illusion)</li>
  <li><em>Semantic zombies</em>—similar to philosophical zombies in philosophy of mind—speakers who cannot be distinguished from ordinary language users by their utterance records alone but have no internal semantics whatsoever</li>
</ul>

<p>Kripke acknowledges that the above cases are problems that need to be elucidated, but unfortunately passes over them due to space constraints.</p>

<h3 id="26-platonism">2.6. Platonism</h3>

<p>Finally, the objection Kripke considers is Platonism.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Platonistic semantics.</strong> For speaker $A$ to mean $\mathfrak{m}$ by symbol $s$ means that the speaker is directed towards the Platonic object $\pi_\mathfrak{m}$ corresponding to meaning $\mathfrak{m}$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Therefore, for Alice to mean addition by ‘+’ is for Alice to establish some relationship with Platonic addition.</p>

<p>This would have been the answer Frege might have given to the sceptic. According to Frege, symbols appear to speakers as particular senses<sub>sense, <em>Sinn</em></sub>, and sense uniquely determines reference. Here, both sense and reference are Platonic objects.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Frege’s philosophy of language: Symbol -&gt; Speaker -&gt; Sense -&gt; Reference</p>
</blockquote>

<p>However, Kripke rejects Platonism with almost the same logic as before. Platonism not only fails to explain how finite humans can relate to infinite sets like addition, but consequently raises the problem of how to determine whether the Platonic object Alice is directed towards is the addition set or the quaddition set.</p>

<div style="margin: 2em 0">$$\cdot \quad \cdot \quad \cdot$$</div>

<p>We have thus examined the Kripke-Wittgenstein paradox and the main objections and counter-objections to it. Ultimately, Kripke concludes that direct refutation of the sceptical argument is impossible. Therefore, the discussion now moves to elucidating why, if indeed the conclusion of the sceptical argument is correct that “Alice means addition by ‘+’” lacks a corresponding state of affairs no less than “Alice’s thoughts are green”, the former can be used meaningfully in linguistic life unlike the latter. This is closely related to Kripke’s reading of Wittgenstein’s private language argument, which shall be examined in detail in the next article.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Following Fregean theory, propositions that lack corresponding states of affairs, i.e., propositions that lack truth values, are not propositions in the true sense, so the expression “arrangements of symbols that appear to be propositions but are not propositions” would be more accurate. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>If the sceptic’s claim had been the former, it would have been immediately refuted by the fact that Alice said ‘125’ rather than ‘5’, just as the claim “heavier balls fall faster” was immediately refuted by the Tower of Pisa experiment. (The fact that the Tower of Pisa experiment was never actually conducted is now well known, but it serves as a good example.) <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Returning to the Tower of Pisa example, this would be explaining what fact constitutes ‘a heavier ball’, which could be explained as “the side that tilts when hung on a balance”. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>Of course, in this case the ‘+’ he performs does not satisfy the associative law (for example, he would answer 21 to “(10 + 7) + (10 + 4)” but 31 to “(10 + (7 + 4)) + 10”), so we would have to claim that he is fundamentally unable to assign a consistent meaning to ‘+’. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>Readers who have studied mathematical logic will be able to connect this to the Löwenheim-Skolem theorem. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>Kripke does call the existence of experiences distinctive to meaning “dubious”. By contrast, in the <em>Philosophical Investigations</em>, he devotes considerable space to denying the existence of such experiences. Wittgenstein urges us to compare the case of pretending to read a foreign language one does not know with the case of reading that foreign language unconsciously after sufficient learning, emphasising that there is no special ‘feeling’ in either the former or the latter case. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><category term="Philosophy" /><category term="Philosophy of Language" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post was machine translated and has not yet been proofread. It may contain minor errors or unnatural expressions. Proofreading will be done in the near future.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">크립키-비트겐슈타인 역설</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/07/03/kripkenstein" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="크립키-비트겐슈타인 역설" /><published>2025-07-03T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-07-03T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/07/03/kripkenstein</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/07/03/kripkenstein"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>“2.2. 성향적 분석” 절에서 크립키의 원 논문과는 독자적인 필자의 보론이 많이 들어갔으니 유의 바랍니다.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="개요">개요</h3>

<p>크립키는 비트겐슈타인의 ⟪철학적 탐구⟫의 핵심이 소위 <strong>규칙 따르기에 대한 회의주의<sub>Skepticism about rule following</sub></strong>에 있다고 주장한다.</p>

<p>크립키의 독해에 따르면 ⟪탐구⟫의 §1-137은 비트겐슈타인이 ⟪논리철학논고⟫의 언어관을 비판하고 극복하는 대목이다. §138-242에서는 규칙 따르기에 대한 회의주의가 제시된다. “앨리스는 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미한다”와 같은 명제에 대응되는 사태가 있는지에 관해 의문을 제기하는 회의주의 논증은, ⟪논고⟫의 언어관이 올바를 수 없음을 보이는 최종적인 논증이라는 점에서 §1-137을 확정지을 뿐 아니라, 의미의 문제를 해명하는 이론은 어떠한 형태로든 가능하지 않다는 궤멸적인 결론을 시사하는 듯하다.</p>

<p>크립키에 따르면 비트겐슈타인은 이에 대해 “회의주의적 해답”을 제시한다. 즉, 회의주의자의 결론 — “앨리스는 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미한다’“에 대응하는 사태는 없다 — 을 받아들이되, 그것이 어떻게 “초록색 생각이 잠을 잔다”와 같은 명제와는 달리 유의미하게 사용될 수 있는지를 해명하는 것이다. 그 해답이란, 언어의 의미는 그것이 공동체에서 가지는 기능과 불가결하며, 따라서 의미에 대한 논의는 개별 언어 사용자 단위에서는 공허하지만 언어 공동체 단위에서는 유효하다는 <strong>언어의 공적성</strong>을 강조하는 것이다.</p>

<p>§243 이후는 “회의주의적 해답”을 기타 철학적 문제에 적용하는 대목이다. 회의주의적 해답의 함의 중 하나는 사적 언어<sub>private language</sub>의 불가능성이다. 그럼에도 사적인 방식으로 작동하는 듯한 영역의 언어가 대표적으로 두 가지 있는데, 바로 수학적 언어와 심리적 언어이다. <strong>그러나 비트겐슈타인은 수학적 언어와 심리적 언어가 사적 언어에 해당한다는 생각이 착각이라고 역설한다.</strong> 이 대목에서 우리는 비트겐슈타인 특유의 수학철학적 · 심리철학적 입장을 엿볼 수 있다.</p>

<h2 id="1-크립키-비트겐슈타인-역설">1. 크립키-비트겐슈타인 역설</h2>

<p>크립키-비트겐슈타인 역설의 결론은 다음과 같다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“화자 $A$는 기호 $s$로 의미 $m$을 의미한다” 꼴의 명제<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>에는 대응되는 사태가 없다. 즉, 해당 명제는 진릿값을 결여한다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>따라서 가령 “앨리스는 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미한다”라는 명제는 “앨리스의 생각은 초록색이다”라는 명제만큼이나 불가해한 명제이다.</p>

<h3 id="11-회의주의자의-등장">1.1. 회의주의자의 등장</h3>

<p>그렇다면 도대체 어째서 크립키-비트겐슈타인은 이토록 극단적인 주장을 하는 것일까? 논증의 핵심은, 언어 사용자가 단어의 의미를 파악하는 과정에 숨은, 간과하기 쉽지만 실로 모순적인 측면에 있다. 바로 과거의 <em>유한한</em> 학습 경험으로부터, 해당 단어가 사용될 수 있는 <em>무한한</em> 사례들에 대해 올바른 추론을 할 수 있어야 한다는 것이다.</p>

<p>예를 들어 앨리스는 지금까지 50이 넘는 두 수의 덧셈을 해본 적이 없다고 하자. 그렇다고 해도 누군가 앨리스에게 ’68 + 57’을 묻는다면 그는 어렵지 않게 ‘125’라고 답할 것이다. 그런데 이때 앨리스에게 한 회의주의자가 다가오더니, ‘125’라는 그의 답은 틀렸으며, 앨리스가 내놓았어야 하는 답은 ‘5’였다고 주장한다. 구체적으로, 회의주의자는 다음을 주장한다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>만약 앨리스가 과거에 ‘+’에 부여하던 의미와 현재 ‘+’에 부여하는 의미가 일치한다면, 앨리스는 ‘5’라고 답했어야 한다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>왜냐하면 — 적어도 회의주의자에 따르면 — 앨리스가 과거에 ‘+’에 부여했던 의미는 사실 덧셈(+)이 아니라 <strong>컷셈</strong>(⨁)이었기 때문이다. 컷셈의 정의는 다음과 같다.</p>

\[x \oplus y =
\begin{cases}
x + y &amp; x, y &lt; 50 \\\
5 &amp; \text{otherwise}
\end{cases}\]

<p>이에 앨리스는 과거부터 자신은 ‘+’를 컷셈이 아닌 덧셈의 의미를 사용했다고 즉각 반박할 것이다. 그런데 여기부터 본격적인 문제가 시작된다. <strong>과거에 앨리스가 ‘+’에 부여한 의미가 컷셈이 아닌 덧셈이었음을 어떻게 입증할 수 있는가?</strong> 문제의 가정으로 인해, 과거에 앨리스가 수행한 ‘+’의 계산 기록들로부터 이를 입증하는 것은 불가능하다.</p>

<p>방금 등장한 ‘입증’이라는 표현으로 인해 이 문제가 인식론에 속하는 것처럼 보일 수 있다 (“우리는 앨리스가 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미한다는 사실을 어떻게 알 수 있을까?”). 그러나 크립키가 묻는 것은, 앨리스의 머리 속까지 들여다 볼 수 있는 전지전능한 관찰자라고 할지라도 앨리스가 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미하는지, 혹은 덧셈과 충분히 많은 경우에 일치하는 비표준적인 연산을 의미하는지 알 수 있는가이다. <strong>이런 점에서 크립키가 제시하는 회의주의는 존재론적인 것이다.</strong> 문제의 요점은 “앨리스가 컷셈이 아닌 덧셈을 의미한다”에 대응하는 사태<sub>case</sub>가 있는가이다. 이는 후술하다시피 크립키가 반사실적 조건문 혹은 가능세계를 통해 회의주의를 해소하려는 시도까지 검토한다는 점에서 — 비록 그 시도 또한 실패한다고 결론 내리지만 — 드러난다.</p>

<h3 id="12-두-가지-조건">1.2. 두 가지 조건</h3>

<p>회의주의자의 주장에는 두 가지 주목할 점이 있다. <strong>첫째, 회의주의자의 주장은 가정문이다.</strong> 회의주의자는 앨리스가 <em>어떤 경우에서든</em> ’5’라고 답해야 함을 주장하는 것이 아니다. 그가 주장하는 바는, 만약 앨리스가 과거에 ‘+’에 부여하던 의미와 현재 ‘+’에 부여하는 의미가 <em>일치한다면</em> ’5’라고 답해야 한다는 것이다. <strong>둘째, 회의주의자의 주장은 규범적이다.</strong> 회의주의자의 주장은 — 앞서 말한 조건이 만족되었을 때 — 앨리스는 ‘5’라고 <em>답할 것</em>이라는 주장이 아니라 ‘5’라고 <em>답해야 한다</em>는 주장이다.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> 달리 말해, 회의주의자는 만약 앨리스가 ’68 + 57’에 대해 ‘5’라고 대답했더라면 그 대답은 <em>정당했을 것</em> 임을 주장한다.</p>

<p>따라서 회의주의자의 주장에 대한 반박 또한 두 가지 특징을 갖춰야 한다. <strong>첫째, 화자에 관한 어떠한 사실이, 해당 화자가 특정 기호를 특정 의미로 사용함을 구성하는지 설명해야 한다.</strong> 이 설명은 회의주의자의 주장에서 가정이 무엇을 의미하는지를 해명하기 위해 필요하다.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> <strong>둘째, 해당 사실이 어떠한 방식으로 화자의 언어 사용을 정당화하는지 설명해야 한다.</strong> 이 설명은 회의주의자의 결론이 규범적이기 때문에 필요하다.</p>

<p>두 번째 조건의 의의가 안 와닿을 수도 있기 때문에 조금 더 설명을 해 보겠다. 가령 어떤 매드사이언티스트가 오더니 회의주의자에게 이렇게 말했다고 하자.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>사실 나는 과거에 앨리스를 원자 단위로 스캔한 적이 있다. 그래서 나는 너의 말을 듣고 그 스캔본을 본따 만든 앨리스-2에게 ’68 + 57‘을 물어보았고, 앨리스-2는 ’125‘라고 대답했다. 따라서 과거의 앨리스는 ’+‘로 컷셈을 의미하지 않았다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>그러나 매드사이언티스트의 실험은 회의주의자의 주장을 반박하는 데 역부족이다. 매드사이언티스트의 실험은 두 번째 조건을 만족하지 않기 때문이다. 해당 실험의 결과는 앨리스가 언제나 ‘125’라고 <em>답했을 것</em>임을 보증할 뿐, 앨리스가 언제나 ‘125’라고 <em>답해야만 했음</em>은 보증하지 않는다.</p>

<p>이는 <strong>체계적 계산 오류의 사례</strong>를 통해 더 명확히 이해할 수 있다. 가령 덧셈을 처음 배우는 아이는 종종 받아올림을 까먹곤 한다. 그런 아이는 ’68 + 57’에 대해 ‘125’가 아니라 ‘115’라고 대답할 것이다. 그런데 모종의 문제로 인해 어른이 될 때까지 받아올림 실수를 교정하지 못한 존슨이라는 사람이 있다고 하자. 존슨은 덧셈이 무엇인지 이해하며, 구체적인 덧셈 문제가 아니라 덧셈에 대한 성질을 질문 받으면 — 가령, “결합법칙을 만족하는가?” — 올바르게 대답한다. 다만, 존슨은 그의 실수를 교정해 줄 지도자가 없는 상황에서 ’68 + 57’을 질문 받으면 <em>언제나</em> ‘115’라고 대답했을 것이며, 앞으로도 그럴 것이다. 이를 두고 우리는 존슨이 ‘+’에 덧셈의 의미를 부여하고 있으나, 그 의미에 <em>정당한 방식대로</em> ’68 + 57’에 대답하지 못하는 것이라 주장하고 싶다. 바로 이 주장을 성립시키기 위해 두 번째 조건이 필요한 것이다. 두 번째 조건을 만족하지 못하는 의미론을 채택한다면, 우리는 존슨이 ‘+’에 <strong>텃셈</strong> — 두 수의 덧셈을 받아올림을 제하고 수행하는 연산 — 혹은 <strong>펏셈</strong> — 곁에 지도자가 없는 상황에서는 텃셈을 수행하고, 있는 상황에서는 지도자의 교정을 받아 덧셈을 수행하는 연산 — 의 의미를 부여하고 있다고 수긍해야 하기 때문이다.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup></p>

<h2 id="2-회의주의에-대한-반박-검토">2. 회의주의에 대한 반박 검토</h2>

<h3 id="21-언어적-해명">2.1. 언어적 해명</h3>

<p>회의주의자의 주장을 들은 앨리스가 내놓을 첫 번째 대답은 아마 이러할 것이다. “과거의 나는 ‘x + y’에 x개의 대상과 y개의 대상을 한데 모아 세는 연산의 의미를 부여해 왔다. 따라서 과거의 나는 ‘+’를 컷셈의 의미로 사용하지 않았다.”</p>

<p>그러나 회의주의자는 이에 대해 또 한번 회의주의를 펼칠 수 있다. 요컨대 그는 과거에 앨리스는 ‘모아 세다’라는 단어를 줄곧 셈<sub>count</sub>이 아닌 <em>켐<sub>quont</sub></em>으로 이해하고 있었다고 주장할 수 있다. 묶음을 켄다는 것은 묶음의 크기가 50 미만일 때는 세는 것이고 50을 초과할 때는 5라고 대답하는 것이다.</p>

<p>요지는, <strong>‘+’에 부여한 의미가 무엇인지를 다른 언어적 증거를 통해 입증하려는 시도는 해당 증거 또한 비표준적인 의미가 부여되었을 가능성을 제거하지 못하므로 무한 퇴행에 빠진다</strong>는 것이다.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup></p>

<h3 id="22-성향적-분석dispositional-analysis">2.2. 성향적 분석<sub>dispositional analysis</sub></h3>

<p>심리철학에서 <strong>성향적 분석</strong>은 행동주의<sub>behaviourism</sub>가 심리 상태를 설명하는 방식으로, 핵심은 다음과 같다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>심리 상태의 성향적 분석.</strong> 주체 $A$가 과거, 현재, 또는 미래에 심리 상태 $\mathfrak{m}$에 있다는 것은, $A$에게 특정 자극 $s$이 주어졌더라면 / 주어진다면 / 주어지게 된다면, $A$는 반응 $b = f_\mathfrak{m}(s)$를 보였을 / 보일 / 보이게 될 것이라는 말이다. 즉, 심리 상태($\mathfrak{m}$)은 자극-반응 대응($f_\mathfrak{m}$)으로 환원된다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>예를 들어 금방 선잠에서 깬 앨리스가, 어둑어둑한 방과 창밖으로 들리는 물방울 소리를 듣고, “지금 비가 오고 있다”라는 믿음을 형성했다고 해보자. 성향적 분석에 따르면 “앨리스는 ‘지금 비가 오고 있다’고 믿는다”의 의미는 다음의 (무수히 많은) 자극-반응 대응과 다름이 없다.</p>

<ul>
  <li>친구에게서 같이 밥 먹으러 가자는 전화가 온다면, -&gt; 우산을 챙길 것이다.</li>
  <li>이웃에게서 밖에 당신의 빨래가 걸려 있다는 연락이 온다면, -&gt; 빨래를 급히 거두러 갈 것이다.</li>
  <li>내일 야외 일정이 잡힌다면, -&gt; 내일의 날씨를 확인할 것이다, 등등…</li>
</ul>

<p>만약 이러한 자극-반응 대응에서 크게 어긋나는 현상이 관측된다면 성향적 분석주의자는 앨리스의 믿음에 대한 견해를 수정할 것이다. 예를 들어 앨리스가 외출을 나서는데 우산을 챙기는 대신 선글라스를 챙긴다면, 그는 앨리스가 “비가 오고 있다”는 믿음이 아닌 “햇살이 쨍쨍하다”는 믿음을 가지고 있다고 판단할 것이다.</p>

<p>지금까지의 설명에서 주목할 성향적 분석의 특징은 두 가지이다.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>반사실적 조건문을 사용한다.</strong> 앨리스가 과거, 현재, 또는 미래에 외출을 나가지 않는다고 하더라도, “앨리스가 외출을 <em>나갔더라면</em> / <em>나간다면</em> / <em>나가게 된다면</em> 그는 우산을 챙겼을 / 챙길 / 챙기게 될 것이다”는 그가 가졌던 / 가지고 있는 / 가지게 될 믿음에 대한 성향적 분석의 일부를 이룬다.</li>
  <li><strong>기술적이다.</strong> 성향적 분석은 행동주의를 기반으로 하기 때문에 “앨리스가 외출을 나간다면 그는 우산을 <em>챙겨야 한다</em>” 와 같은 규범적 명제가 아닌, “앨리스가 외출을 나간다면 그는 우산을 <em>챙길 것이다</em>” 와 같은 기술적 명제로 이루어진다. 성향적 분석에 따르면, 만약 앨리스가 외출을 나서는데 우산을 챙기는 대신 선글라스를 챙긴다면, 앨리스는 비가 오고 있다는 믿음을 가지고 <em>있음에도</em> 그에 <em>정당하게</em> 행동하지 않는 것이 아니라, 애초에 비가 오고 있다는 믿음을 가지고 있지 않은 것이다.</li>
</ol>

<p>크립키는 자신과 사적인 자리에서 규칙 따르기 역설을 논의했던 일부 철학자들이, 성향적 분석의 1번 특징에 의존함으로써 성향적 분석을 통한 역설의 해결을 시도했다고 전한다. 이 접근법은 다음을 주장한다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>의미에 대한 성향적 분석.</strong> 화자 $A$가 과거, 현재, 또는 미래에 기호 $s$로 의미 $\mathfrak{m}$을 의미한다는 것은, $s$가 포함된 문장 $\phi$가 $A$에게 주어졌더라면 / 주어진다면 / 주어지게 된다면, $A$는 문장 $\psi = f_\mathfrak{m}(\phi)$로 대답했을 / 대답할 / 대답하게 될 것이라는 말이다. 즉, 의미($\mathfrak{m}$)는 문답 대응($f_\mathfrak{m}$)으로 환원된다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>이 분석에 따르면, 앨리스가 과거, 현재, 또는 미래에 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미한다는 것은, 앨리스에게 x + y를 물어보았더라면 / 물어본다면 / 물어보게 될 때, $A$는 x와 y의 합으로 대답했을 / 대답할 / 대답하게 될 것이라는 말이다. 이러한 반사실적 조건문을 통해 회의주의를 극복하려는 철학자의 사고 흐름은 대략 다음과 같을 것이다.</p>

<ol>
  <li>회의주의자는 과거의 앨리스가 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미했는지, 덧셈이 아니지만 충분히 많은 경우에 덧셈과 일치하는 비표준적 연산을 의미했는지 구별하는 사태가 지금까지 없었고, 앞으로도 없을 것임을 지적한다.</li>
  <li>1이 주장 가능한 이유는, 앨리스가 지금까지 수행했고, 앞으로 수행할 ‘+’의 연산 횟수가 유한하기 때문이다.</li>
  <li>그러나 “과거의 앨리스에게 ’x + y’을 <em>물어보았더라면</em> 나는 x와 y의 합을 <em>대답했을 것이다</em>”, 또는 “미래의 앨리스에게 ‘x + y’를 <em>물어본다면</em> 나는 x와 y의 합을 <em>대답할 것이다</em>”라는 반사실적 조건문을 사용하면, 우리는 2의 유한성을 극복할 수 있다.</li>
  <li>이에 따라, 반사실적 조건문은 객관적인 진릿값을 가진다는 사실을 — 가능세계 존재론 등을 통해 — 인정한다면, ”앨리스가 ’+‘로 덧셈을 의미한다“에 대응되는 의미에 대한 성향적 분석은 앨리스가 ‘+’로서 의미하는 연산을 객관적으로 결정한다.</li>
</ol>

<p>이 논증은 회의주의자에 대한 반박이 갖춰야 할 첫째 조건 — 화자에 관한 <em>어떠한 사실이</em> 해당 화자가 특정 기호를 특정 의미로 사용함을 구성하는지 설명해야 한다 — 을 만족한다. 그 사실이라 함은 반사실적 조건문인 것이다. <strong>그러나 크립키는 둘째 조건 — 해당 사실이 어떠한 방식으로 화자의 언어 사용을 <em>정당화하는지</em> 설명해야 한다 — 을 갖추지 못하므로 성향적 분석은 역설을 해소하는 데 불충분하다고 지적한다.</strong> 이는 앞서 지적했듯이 성향적 분석이 본질적으로 기술적이기 때문이다. 크립키의 말을 인용하자면,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>좋다. 나는 ‘125’가 내가 주어진 수식에 대해 내놓을 대답임을 알며, (실제로 그렇게 대답하고 있지 않은가!) 어쩌면 — <strong>그저 하나의 주어진 사실로서</strong> — 과거의 나에게 같은 수식이 주어졌다고 <em>하더라도</em> 똑같이 대답했으리라는 사실 또한 안다고 하자. <strong>이 모든 사실들이 도대체 어떻게 — 현재 <em>또는</em> 과거에서 — ‘125’가, 내 내면의 어떤 규칙에 의거하여 도출된 <em>정당화된</em> 답이지, 그저 눈 가리고 아웅하며 내놓은 아무 근거 없는 답이 아니라는 사실을 보여주는가?</strong></p>

  <p><small>Well and good, I know that ‘125’ is the response I am disposed to give (I am actually giving it!), and maybe it is helpful to be told — <strong>as a matter of brute fact</strong> — that I <em>would have given</em> the same response in the past. <strong>How does any of this indicate that — now <em>or</em> in the past — ‘125’ was an answer <em>justified</em> in terms of instructions I gave myself, rather than a mere jack-in-the-box unjustified and arbitrary response?</strong></small></p>

  <p>(이탤릭체는 원문, 강조는 필자)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>크립키가 지적하는 바는 다음과 같이 차근차근 이해할 수 있다. 기억을 되살려 보면, 회의주의자에게 대항하는 주장은 다음의 형식을 갖춰야 한다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>주장 1.</strong> 만약 앨리스가 과거에 ‘+’에 부여하던 의미와 현재 ‘+’에 부여하는 의미가 일치한다면,</p>

  <ol>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘5’라고 답해야 하는 것이 아니라,</li>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘125’라고 답해야 한다.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>성향적 분석에 의하면 위 주장은 다음과 동의적이다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>주장 1.1.</strong> 만약 ‘+’에 대한 과거 앨리스의 문답 성향이 ‘+’에 대한 현재 앨리스의 문답 성향과 일치한다면,</p>

  <ol>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘5’라고 답해야 하는 것이 아니라,</li>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘125’라고 답해야 한다.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>“그저 하나의 주어진 사실로서”, ‘+’에 대한 과거 앨리스의 문답 성향이 두 수가 주어졌을 때 그 합을 말하는 것이었다고 하자. 이 사실을 위에 대입하면,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>주장 1.2.</strong> 만약 ‘+’에 대한 현재 앨리스의 문답 성향이 두 수가 주어졌을 때 그 합을 말하는 것이라면,</p>

  <ol>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘5’라고 답해야 하는 것이 아니라,</li>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘125’라고 답해야 한다.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>그러나 주장 1을 주장 1.2.로 재진술하였다고 한들, 이를 성립시킬 근거는 여전히 전무하다. 만약 1, 2의 술어부가 “<em>답할 것이다</em>”였다면 주장이 성립하겠지만, 요구된 것은 “<em>답해야 한다</em>”이다. 이것은 문답 성향만 가지고서 알 수 있는 사실이 아니다.</p>

<p>그렇다면 처음부터 1, 2의 술어부를 ”<em>답할 것이다</em>“라고 둘 수는 없을까? 요컨대 회의주의자에게 다음을 주장하는 것이다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>주장 2.</strong> 만약 앨리스가 과거에 ‘+’에 부여하던 의미와 현재 ‘+’에 부여하는 의미가 일치한다면,</p>

  <ol>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘5’라고 답할 것이 아니라,</li>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘125’라고 답할 것이다.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>그럴 수는 없다. 앞서 “체계적 계산 오류의 사례”에서 자세히 설명했듯이, 앨리스가 ‘68 + 57’에 대해 ‘125’라고 대답하지 않았다고 해서 그 사실이 즉시 앨리스가 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미하지 않았음을 시사하지는 않기 때문이다. 우리는 덧셈을 수행함에 있어 때때로 실수를 하곤 하지만, 그런 실수가 저지를 때마다 ’+‘를 덧셈이 아닌 다른 의미로 사용했음을 뜻하지는 않는다. 오히려 내가 ‘+’ 연산을 수행함에 있어 <strong>실수</strong>를 저지를 수 있다는 사실 자체가, 내가 내놓는 계산 결과가 내가 ‘+’에 부여하는 의미를 결정하는 것이 아니라, 역으로 내가 ‘+’에 부여하는 의미가 선행하여 내가 <em>내놓아야 할</em> 결과를 결정함을 시사한다.</p>

<p>그럼에도 성향적 분석으로 의미의 규범성을 설명하기 위해서는 다음과 같이 회의주의자의 도전을 재해석해야만 할 듯하다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>주장 3.</strong> 만약 앨리스가 과거에 ‘+’에 부여하던 의미와 현재 ‘+’에 부여하는 의미를 <em>일치시키고자 한다면,</em></p>

  <ol>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘5’라고 답해야 하는 것이 아니라,</li>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘125’라고 답해야 한다.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>이는 다음 진술로 이어진다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>주장 3.1.</strong> 만약 ‘+’에 대한 현재 앨리스의 문답 성향이 두 수가 주어졌을 때 그 합을 말하는 것이 <em>되고자 한다면,</em></p>

  <ol>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘5’라고 답해야 하는 것이 아니라,</li>
    <li>앨리스는 ‘125’라고 답해야 한다.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>확실히 주장 3.1은 주장 1.1, 1.2보다는 그럴듯해 보인다. 그러나 필자가 보기에 주장 3.1에도 여전히 문제가 있다.</p>

<p><strong>첫째 문제는, 설령 주장 3이 성립한다고 하더라도 그것이 주장 1을 시사하지는 않는다는 문제이다.</strong> $p, q$를 다음과 같이 두자.</p>

<ul>
  <li>$p:$ 앨리스가 과거에 ‘+‘에 부여하던 의미와 현재 ’+‘에 부여하는 의미가 일치한다.</li>
  <li>$q:$ 앨리스는 ‘125’라고 답한다.</li>
</ul>

<p>이 경우 주장 1과 주장 3은 각각 다음과 같다. ($W$는 ”하고자 한다“를, $\Box$는 “해야 한다”를 의미)</p>

<ul>
  <li>주장 1. $p \rightarrow \Box q$</li>
  <li>주장 3. $Wp \rightarrow \Box q$</li>
</ul>

<p>그러나 $p$는 $Wp$를 시사하지 않고 (내가 원하지 않는 일이 나에게 일어날 수 있다) $Wp$ 또한 $p$를 시사하지 않기 때문에 (내가 원하는 일이 나에게 일어나지 않을 수 있다) 주장 1과 주장 3에는 어떠한 논리적 관계도 없다. 구체적으로 전자의 경우로는, ‘+’를 곱셈의 의미로 사용하겠다고 다짐한 반항아 학생이 자신의 다짐이 무색하게 습관적으로 ‘68 + 57‘에 ’125‘라고 대답해버리는 상황이 있다. 후자의 경우로는 ‘+’ 기호를 덧셈의 의미로 사용하고자 하지만 아직 덧셈의 개념을 완전히 숙지하지 못한 학생의 경우가 있다.</p>

<p><strong>둘째 문제는, 애초에 주장 3은 무한 회귀에 빠진다는 것이다.</strong> 잠시 설명의 편의를 위해 심리 상태의 사례로 돌아가 보자. 현재의 문제를 심리 상태에 관한 것으로 전환하면 다음과 같을 것이다. 앨리스는 지금 밖에 비가 오고 있다는 믿음을 가지고 있음에도 불구하고 우산이 아닌 다른 물건을 챙긴 채 밖으로 나갈 수 있다. 가령 앨리스가 허겁지겁 외출 준비를 하고는 우산꽂이에서 아무거나 뽑은 채 집을 나섰는데, 손에 잡힌 게 우산이 아니라 지팡이였던 상황을 고려해 보자. 기존의 성향적 분석에 따르면 이 경우 앨리스는 애초부터 비가 오고 있다는 믿음을 가지고 있지 않던 것인데 이는 반직관적인 결론이다. 이에 대해 성향적 분석주의자는 다음의 주장들을 대신 내세울지 모른다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>주장 4.</strong> 만약 앨리스가 과거에 ‘어두컴컴한 방과 창밖으로 떨어지는 물방울 소리’에 형성하던 믿음과 현재 동 상황에 형성하는 믿음을 <em>일치시키고자 한다면,</em></p>

  <ol>
    <li>앨리스는 지팡이를 챙겨야 하는 것이 아니라,</li>
    <li>앨리스는 우산을 챙겨야 한다.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>주장 4.1.</strong> 만약 ‘어두컴컴한 방과 창밖으로 떨어지는 물방울 소리’에 대해 앨리스가 보였을 자극-반응 대응과, 동 상황에 대한 현재 앨리스의 자극-반응 대응을 <em>일치시키고자 한다면,</em></p>

  <ol>
    <li>앨리스는 지팡이를 챙기는 것이 아니라,</li>
    <li>앨리스는 우산을 챙겨야 한다.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>주장 4.2.</strong> 만약 ‘어두컴컴한 방과 창밖으로 떨어지는 물방울 소리’에 대한 앨리스의 자극-반응 대응이 외출을 나가는 상황에 대하여 우산을 챙기는 것이 <em>되고자 한다면</em>,</p>

  <ol>
    <li>앨리스는 지팡이를 챙기는 것이 아니라,</li>
    <li>앨리스는 우산을 챙겨야 한다.</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>이미 앞서 말했듯이 주장 4는 $Wp \rightarrow \Box q$의 형태이므로 애초에 $p \rightarrow \Box q$와 논리적 관계가 없지만, 그 문제를 차치하더라도 일면 타당해 보이는 주장 4.2에는 본질적인 문제가 있다. 애당초 우리가 성향적 분석을 시도하는 이유는 심리 상태에 관한 진술을 행동주의적인 표현으로 옮기기 위해서이다. 그런데 주장 4.2는 한 특정 심리 상태 — 밖에 비가 오고 있다는 믿음 — 에 관한 진술을, 다른 심리 상태 — 외출을 나가는 상황에 대하여 우산을 챙기는 반응을 <em>보이고자 하는 의도</em> — 에 관한 진술로 바꾼 것에 지나지 않는다. 이제 우리는 누군가가 ‘외출을 나가는 상황에 대하여 우산을 챙기는 반응을 보이고자 하는 상태’가 무엇인지를 성향적 분석으로 설명해야 하는데, 이는 결국 무한 회귀에 빠지는 것이다.</p>

<p>동일한 이유로 주장 3 또한 무한회귀에 빠진다. 앞선 논의를 되새겨 보면, 회의주의자의 주장에 대한 반박이 갖춰야 할 필요조건 중 하나는 “화자에 관한 어떠한 사실이, 해당 화자가 특정 기호를 특정 의미로 사용함을 구성하는지 설명할 것“이다. 그런데 주장 3.1은 이 문제에 대해 “문답 성향을 특정한 방식에 일치시키고자 하는 의도”라는 답을 제시한다. 그렇다면 회의주의자는 이에 대해, ”화자에 관한 어떠한 사실이, 해당 화자가 ‘+’ 기호에 대한 문답 성향을 특정한 방식 — 이를테면, 컷셈이 아닌 덧셈에 대응되는 문답 성향 — 에 일치시키고자 하는 의도를 가지고 있음을 구성하는가?“ 라고 반문할 수 있다.</p>

<p>결론적으로, 성향적 분석으로 의미의 문제를 해결하려는 시도는 의미의 규범성을 설명하지 못한다. 규범성을 설명할 수 있도록 성향적 분석을 억지로 끼워맞추려는 시도는 문제가 요구하는 바를 벗어날 뿐 아니라, 무한 회귀의 오류에까지 빠지게 된다.</p>

<h3 id="23-기계주의">2.3. 기계주의</h3>

<p>그렇다면 언어적 해명이나 성향적 분석과 같은 추상적인 설명에 급급하는 대신, 아예 ‘+’가 의미하는 연산에 대응되는 구체적인 기계를 설계해 제시해 줌으로써 회의주의자에게 대응할 수는 없을까? 가령 기계식 계산기를 제작하거나, 논리 회로로 전가산기를 설계해 보이는 것이다. 그러나 크립키는 이 시도 또한 크게 세 가지 이유에서 부적절한다고 주장한다.</p>

<p><strong>첫째, 기계의 사용법이 여전히 해명을 요하는 문제로 남는다.</strong> 튜링 기계로 예를 들면, 우리는 튜링 기계가 출력하는 이진 나열을 이진법으로 해석하여 결과를 읽을 것이다. 그러나 회의주의자는 이 기계를 해석하는 올바른 방식이 <em>퀴진법</em> 이며, 퀴진법에 따르면 튜링 기계는 덧셈이 아니라 컷셈을 출력하고 있다고 주장할 수 있다.</p>

<p><strong>둘째, 실제 기계는 오직 유한한 입력만을 받을 수 있다.</strong> 그런 의미에서 실제 기계는 앨리스보다 더 ‘유능한’ 존재가 되지 못한다. 그렇다고 실제 기계를 구현하는 대신 기계의 알고리즘을 제시한다면, 이는 다시 “2.1. 언어적 해명”으로 돌아가는 것이다.</p>

<p><strong>셋째, 기계는 오작동할 수 있다.</strong> 누군가 기계를 떨어뜨려서 기어가 빠지거나, 너무 오래 쓰다 보니 전선이 녹을 수도 있다. 따라서 우리는 기계에게 의미 해명의 책임을 전임하여 “이 기계는 <em>언제나</em> 내가 의미하는 연산을 계신한다”라고 주장할 수 없다. 그렇다고 우리는 “이 기계는 <em>오작동하지 않는 한 언제나</em> 내가 의미하는 연산을 계산한다”라고 주장할 수도 없다. 그렇게 주장하기 위해서는 기계가 정상적으로 작동하고 있는지 오작동하는지 판단하는 기준을 제시해야 하는데, 그 기준은 결국 우리가 이 기계를 어떤 <em>의도로</em> 사용하고자 하는지에 달려 있을 것이다 (어떤 괴이한 설계자는 기어의 빠짐과 전선의 녹아내림을 통해 덧셈을 계산하는 기계를 만들 수도 있지 않은가?). 따라서 <em>오작동하지 않는 한</em> 이라는 표현을 사용하는 순간 기계가 아닌 화자의 의도가 선행하게 된다.</p>

<h3 id="24-오컴의-면도날">2.4. 오컴의 면도날</h3>

<p>크립키는 다음의 주장도 고려한다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>오캄 의미론.</strong> 두 가설 “화자 $A$는 기호 $s$로 의미 $\mathfrak{m}_1$을 의미한다”와 “화자 $A$는 기호 $s$로 의미 $\mathfrak{m}_2$를 의미한다”가 비결정 상태에 있을 때, $\mathfrak{m}_1$과 $\mathfrak{m}_2$ 중 더 단순한 쪽의 가설을 우선적으로 받아들여야 한다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>예를 들어 다음 두 가설을 보자.</p>

<p>    H1. 과거에 앨리스는 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미했다.</p>

<p>    H2. 과거에 앨리스는 ‘+’로 컷셈을 의미했다.</p>

<p>과거에 앨리스가 수행한 ‘+’ 연산 기록의 양항은 모두 50 이하이므로, H1과 H2는 비결정 상태에 있다. 오캄 의미론이 주장하는 바는 이 경우 우리는 H1설을 우선적으로 받아들여야 한다는 것이다. 덧셈이 컷셈보다 더 단순한 연산이기 때문이다.</p>

<p>그러나 크립키는 이 주장을 짧게만 언급하고 넘어가는데, 회의주의를 논박하는 데 있어 부적절하다는 사실이 자명하기 때문이다. 이는 ‘단순하다’라는 술어가 주관적이라든가, 정의하기 어렵다든가, 화성인에게는 컷셈이 덧셈보다 더 단순할지도 모른다 등의 이유 — 물론 이 이유들도 매우 정당하다 — 때문만이 아니다. 더 본질적인 이유는, 회의주의 논증의 결론이 “H1과 H2 중 어느 하나가 참인지 미정이다”가 아니라, “H1과 H2 중 어느 하나가 참이라는 사실이 <em>어떤 사태에 해당하는지가</em> 미정이다”라는 것이다. 회의주의 논증에 따르면 우리는 H1과 H2가 서로 다른 사태를 나타내는지도 확실하지 않은 상황이다. 이토록 가설이 나타내는 사태가 명확하지 않다면 우리는 오컴의 면도날의 적용이 정당한지를 따지기도 전에 애초에 적용할 <em>수</em> 없다.</p>

<h3 id="25-심리주의">2.5. 심리주의</h3>

<p>크립키가 더 중요하게 고려하는 반론은 심리주의이다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>심리주의 의미론.</strong> 화자 $A$가 기호 $s$로 $\mathfrak{m}$을 의미한다는 것은, 화자의 내면에 $\mathfrak{m}$에 대응되는 특유한<sub>queer</sub> 심리적 경험 $p_\mathfrak{m}$이 형성되었다는 말이다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>여기서 “특유한 심리적 경험”은 퀄리아와 비슷한 것으로 생각할 수 있다. 요컨대 “빨간색을 보는 것”이 다른 술어나 경험으로 환원될 수 없는 특유 경험이듯이, “‘+’로 덧셈을 의미하는 것” 또한 그러한 특유 경험이라는 것이다.</p>

<p>크립키는 그러한 특유 경험이 존재할 가능성을 부정하지 않는다.<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup> 그러나 크립키는 심리주의 의미론 또한 회의주의 논증을 해결하지 못함을 지적한다. 문제는 어김없이 “1.2. 두 가지 조건” 중 2번 조건에 있다.</p>

<p>단적인 예시로, 앨리스는 ‘+’ 기호를 사용할 때마다 이마에서 통증을 느낀다고 해보자. 이 사실은 “1.2. 두 가지 조건” 중 1번 조건을 만족한다. 즉, 앨리스가 과거에 ‘+’에 부여한 의미와 현재 부여하는 의미가 같다는 것은 앨리스가 ‘+’ 기호를 사용할 때 느낀 과거의 통증과 현재의 통증이 질적으로 같다는 것이다. 그러나 그렇다고 해서, 그 통증이 도대체 어떤 방식으로 앨리스에게 ’68 + 57’에 대해 ‘125’라고 대답해야 한다는 사실을 알려줄 수 있다는 말인가?</p>

<p>크립키는 이 논의를 보다 일반적인 경험주의 반박과 연관짓는다. 경험주의에 따르면 내가 ‘삼각형’을 의미한다는 것은 내가 내면에서 삼각형의 인상을 떠올린다는 것이다. 그런데 이 삼각형의 인상이 어떻게 내가 ‘삼각형’이라는 단어를 사용하는 규칙을 알려준다는 말인가? 가령 나의 머리에 떠오른 인상이 예각삼각형이라고 하더라도 나는 둔각삼각형을 가리키며 정당하게 삼각형이라고 말할 수 있다. 반면 나의 머리에 떠오른 인상과 정확히 같은 모양의 밑변을 가지는 삼각뿔을 가리키며 삼각형이라고 말할 수는 없다. 요컨대 머리 속에서 어떤 인상이 제시된다고 한들, 그 인상을 어떻게 <em>해석해 내야</em> 할지는 미궁에 쌓여있다.</p>

<p>그럼에도 크립키는 우리가 반대 극단으로 치우쳐, 심리적 경험 내지 느낌이 의미의 문제와 완전히 무관하다고 결론내려서는 안 됨을 강조한다. 크립키는 ⟪철학적 탐구⟫의 논의에서 파생되는 다음의 사례들을 거론한다.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semantic_satiation">같은 단어를 수십 번 말하다 보면 마치 단어에서 의미가 빠져나가고 껍질만 남은 것처럼 ‘낯설게’ 느껴지는 현상</a></li>
  <li>’배’를 운송수단을 떠올리며 말할 때와 과일을 떠올리며 말할 때의 차이 (이것을 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necker_cube">네커 큐브</a> 착시와 비교해 보라)</li>
  <li>심리철학의 철학적 좀비와 유사한, <em>의미론적 좀비</em> — 발화 기록만으로는 일반적인 언어 사용자와 구별되지 않으나 내면에 어떠한 의미론도 가지고 있지 않은 화자</li>
</ul>

<p>크립키는 위 사례들이 해명되어야 할 문제임을 인정하지만, 안타깝게도 지면의 문제로 인해 넘어간다.</p>

<h3 id="26-플라톤주의">2.6. 플라톤주의</h3>

<p>마지막으로 크립키가 고려하는 반론은 플라톤주의다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>플라톤주의 의미론.</strong> 화자 $A$가 기호 $s$로 $\mathfrak{m}$을 의미한다는 것은, 화자가 의미 $\mathfrak{m}$에 대응되는 플라톤적 대상 $\pi_\mathfrak{m}$을 지향한다는 것이다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>따라서 앨리스가 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미한다는 것은, 앨리스가 플라톤적 덧셈과 모종의 관계를 맺는 것이다.</p>

<p>이것은 프레게가 회의주의자에게 제시했을 대답이었을 걸로 짐작할 수 있다. 프레게에 따르면 기호는 화제에게 특정한 뜻<sub>sense, <em>Sinn</em></sub>으로서 나타나는데, 뜻은 지시체를 유일하게 결정한다. 여기서 뜻과 지시체는 플라톤적 대상이다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>프레게의 언어철학: 기호 -&gt; 화자 -&gt; 뜻 -&gt; 지시체</p>
</blockquote>

<p>그러나 크립키는 플라톤주의 또한 이전과 거의 같은 논리로 기각한다. 플라톤주의는 유한한 인간이 어떻게 덧셈과 같은 무한집합과 관계 맺을 수 있는지를 설명하지 못할 뿐더러, 이에 따라 앨리스가 지향하는 플라톤적 대상이 덧셈 집합인지 컷셈 집합인지를 어떻게 결정하냐는 문제를 낳는다.</p>

<div style="margin: 2em 0">$$\cdot \quad \cdot \quad \cdot$$</div>

<p>이상으로 크립키-비트겐슈타인 역설과, 이에 대한 주요 반박 및 재반박을 살펴 보았다. 최종적으로 크립키는 회의주의 논증에 대한 직설적인 반박은 불가능하다고 결론 내린다. 따라서 이제 논의는, 정말로 회의주의 논증의 결론대로 “앨리스는 ‘+’로 덧셈을 의미한다”가 “앨리스의 생각은 초록색이다”와 다를 바 없이 대응되는 사태를 결여하는 명제라면, 어째서 전자는 후자와 달리 언어 생활에서 유의미하게 사용될 수 있는가를 해명하는 것으로 넘어간다. 이것은 비트겐슈타인의 사적 언어 논증에 대한 크립키의 독해와 밀접한 관련이 있으며, 다음 글에서 자세히 살펴보도록 한다.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>프레게식 이론을 따른다면, 대응되는 사태가 없는 명제, 즉 진릿값을 결여한 명제는 진정한 의미에서의 명제가 아니므로 ”명제처럼 보이지만 명제가 아닌 기호들의 나열“이라는 표현이 더 적확할 것이다. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>만약 회의주의자의 주장이 전자에 해당했다면, 이는 “더 무거운 공이 더 빨리 떨어진다”라는 주장이 피사의 사탑 실험으로서 즉시 반박되었듯이, 앨리스가 ‘5’가 아니라 ‘125’라고 말했다는 사실로서 즉시 반박되었을 것이다. (피사의 사탑 실험이 실제로 진행된 바 없다는 것은 이제 잘 알려진 사실이지만 좋은 예시라서 사용했다.) <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>다시 피사의 사탑 예시를 들자면, 이는 ‘더 무거운 공’이 어떤 사실로서 구성되는지를 설명하는 것으로 “양팔저울에 매달았을 때 기울어지는 쪽”과 같이 설명할 수 있다. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>물론 이 경우 그가 수행하는 ‘+’는 결합법칙을 만족하지 않으므로 (예를 들어 “(10 + 7) + (10 + 4)”에 대해서 그는 21이라고 대답하지만 ”(10 + (7 + 4)) + 10“에 대해서는 31이라고 대답한다) 우리는 그가 애초에 ‘+’에 일관된 의미를 부여하지 못하고 있다고 주장해야 할 것이다. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>수리논리학을 배워본 적 있는 독자라면 이를 뢰벤하임-스콜렘 정리와 연결지을 수 있을 것이다. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>크립키는 의미에 특유한 경험의 존재가 “미심쩍다<sub>dubious</sub>”고 하기는 한다. 반면 ⟪철학적 논고⟫에서 긴 지면을 할애하며 그러한 경험의 존재를 부정한다. 비트슈타인은 외국어를 알지 못하지만 읽는 척을 하는 경우와, 충분한 학습 이후 해당 외국어를 무의식적으로 읽는 경우를 비교해 볼 것을 중용하며, 전자의 경우나 후자의 경우나 어떤 특별한 ‘느낌’이 있지는 않음을 강조한다. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><category term="철학" /><category term="언어철학" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“2.2. 성향적 분석” 절에서 크립키의 원 논문과는 독자적인 필자의 보론이 많이 들어갔으니 유의 바랍니다.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">프란츠 카프카, 「여덟 권의 청색 팔절판 노트」 중 제1권</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/17/kafka-blue-octavos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="프란츠 카프카, 「여덟 권의 청색 팔절판 노트」 중 제1권" /><published>2025-06-17T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-06-17T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/17/kafka-blue-octavos</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/17/kafka-blue-octavos"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>「여덟 권의 청색 팔절판 노트<sub>Acht blaue Oktavhefte</sub>」는 1917년 말부터 1919년 중순까지 카프카가 작성한 일련의 노트이다. 「팔절판 노트」라는 이름은 카프카의 출판 담당자인 막스 브로트가 그의 사절판 일기장과 구분하기 위해 붙인 것이다. 이후 브로트가 카프카의 일기를 출판했을 때 「팔절판 노트」는 생략되었는데, 카프카의 다른 일기보다 철학적이고 문학적이라는 점에서 성격을 달리한다는 이유에서였다. 이로 인해 「팔절판 노트」는 카프카 특유의 사색적이고 몽환적인 성격에도 불구하고 세간에 잘 알려져 있지 않으며, 특히 국내에서는 전문이 번역된 바가 없다. 이에 필자가 직접 번역을 시도했다. 비전공자의 번역인 점을 감안하여 독일어 원문을 같이 수록했다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="/public/the-blue-notebooks.png" style="max-width: 350px; width: 100%; margin: 7em auto 5em auto;" /></p>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">i.</h4>

<p>모든 사람은 자신의 내면에 하나의 방을 가지고 다닌다. 이 사실은 심지어 청각의 감각을 통해 증명할 수 있다. 주위가 고요한 밤중에, 서둘러 걸음을 재촉하는 자가 귀를 기울일 때면, 그는 예컨대 벽에 충분히 고정되지 못한 거울이 부딪치는 소리를 듣는 것이다.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Jeder Mensch trägt ein Zimmer in sich. Diese Tatsache kann man sogar durch das Gehör nachprüfen. Wenn einer schnell geht und man hinhorcht, etwa in der Nacht, wenn alles ringsherum still ist, 
so hört man zum Beispiel das Scheppern eines nicht genug befestigten Wandspiegels.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">ii.</h4>

<p>남자는 움츠린 가슴, 튀어나온 어깨, 축 늘어진 팔, 거의 들 수조차 없는 다리, 그리고 한 지점을 응시하는 눈빛으로 서 있다. 그는 화부<sub>火夫</sub>다. 그는 삽에 석탄을 담아 화염이 치솟는 용광로에 던져 넣는다. 한 아이가 공장의 스무 안뜰을 살금살금 건너와 그의 거적때기에 안긴다. “아버지” — 아이가 말한다 — “제가 수프를 가지고 왔어요.”</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Er steht mit eingedrückter Brust, vorragenden Schultern, hängenden Armen, kaum zu erhebenden Beinen, 
auf eine Stelle starrendem Blick. 
Ein Heizer. 
Er nimmt Kohle auf die Schaufel und stößt sie in das Ofenloch voll Flammen. 
Ein Kind hat sich durchgestohlen durch die zwanzig Fabrikshöfe und zupft ihn am Schurz. 
»Vater«, sagt es, 
»ich bringe dir die Suppe.«
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">iii.</h4>

<p>이곳이 저 아래 겨울의 대지보다 따뜻한가? 백색은 온 주위에 쌓여가 오직 나의 들통만이 검다. 이전에 높은 곳에 있었던 나는 이제 깊은 곳에 있으며, 산을 올려다보려는 시도는 나의 목을 골절시킨다. 얼어붙은 백색은 사라진 스케이터들의 궤도를 따라 사방으로 금이 달렸다. 깊고 한 치도 꺼지지 않는 눈 위로, 나는 작은 북극견들의 발자국을 좇는다. 말을 타는 일은 의미를 잃었다. 나는 내려서 들통을 어깨에 메고 걷는다.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Ist hier wärmer als unten auf der winterlichen Erde? Weiß ragt es rings, mein Kübel das einzig Dunkle. War ich früher hoch, bin ich jetzt tief, der Blick zu den Bergen renkt mir den Hals aus. Weißgefrorene Eisfläche, strichweise durchschnitten von den Bahnen verschwundener Schlittschuhläufer. Auf dem hohen, keinen Zoll breit einsinkenden Schnee, folge ich der Fußspur der kleinen arktischen Hunde. Mein Reiten hat den Sinn verloren, ich bin abgestiegen und trage den Kübel auf der Achsel.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">iv.</h4>

<p>V. W.<br />
베토벤 책에 대해 진심 어린 감사를 보냅니다. 쇼펜하우어는 오늘 시작합니다. 이 책들은 정말 대단한 업적입니다. 당신이 당신의 섬세한 손길과, 참된 진실을 향하는 강렬한 시선과, 절제되었으면서도 위엄한 대지의 불 같은 시적 본성과, 환상적일 정도로 방대한 지식을 통해 앞으로도 이러한 위업을 이룩하여 저에게 형언할 수 없는 기쁨을 주시기를 기원합니다.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
V. W.<br />
Meinen innigsten Dank für das Beethovenbuch. Den Schopenhauer beginne ich heute. Was für eine Leistung, dieses Buch. Möchten Sie doch mit Ihrer allerzartesten Hand, mit Ihrem allerstärksten Blick für die wahrhafte Realität, mit dem gezügelten und mächtigen Grundfeuer Ihres dichterischen Wesens, mit Ihrem phantastisch weiten Wissen noch weiter solche Denkmäler aufrichten — zu meiner unaussprechlichen Freude.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">v.</h4>

<p>늙고 비대한 육신 속에서, 나는 가벼운 심장 질환을 앓으며, 점심 식사 이후 한 발은 바닥에 떨군 채 소파에 누워 역사책을 읽고 있었다. 하녀가 오더니 삐죽 튀어나온 입술 위로 두 손가락을 얹고는 방문객이 왔다고 일렀다.</p>

<p>“누구인가?” 나는 오후의 커피를 마셔야 할 때에 방문객을 상대해야 한다는 사실에 짜증이 난 목소리로 물었다. “중국인 남자입니다.” 하녀가 말하더니, 경련적으로 몸을 돌리고는 문 앞의 방문객이 들어서는 안 될 웃음을 삼켰다.</p>

<p>“중국인? 나를 보기 위해? 중국 의상을 입고 있나?” 하녀는 여전히 웃음을 억누르며 고개를 끄덕였다. “그에게 나의 이름을 말해주고, 그가 정말로 나를 방문하려는지 물어보거라. 나는 옆집 사람에게도 낯선 이인즉 중국에서는 오죽하겠나.”</p>

<p>하녀는 나에게 몸을 기울이더니 속삭였다. “그는 한 장의 쪽지만을 가지고 있는데, 쪽지에는 그를 들여보내달라는 부탁만 쓰여 있었습니다. 그는 독일어를 할 줄 모르며 알아들을 수 없는 언어로만 말합니다. 저는 쪽지를 그에게서 가져가는 것이 두려울 지경이었습니다.”</p>

<p>“그를 들여보내거라!” 나는 심장 문제가 종종 일으키곤 하는 숨가쁨 속에서 외치며, 책을 바닥 위로 던지고는 하녀의 어색한 접대를 저주했다. 나는 일어나 이처럼 천장이 낮은 방으로 들어오는 방문객이라면 누구든지 경악할 수밖에 없을 거구를 뻗으며 문에 다가섰다. 과연 그 중국인은 나와 눈이 마주치자마자 즉시 들어왔던 길로 미끄러지듯이 돌아갔다. 나는 사뿐히 복도로 손을 뻗어 남자의 비단 저고리를 움켜잡아 내게로 조심히 끌어당겼다. 그는 한눈에 보기에도 학자였으며, 작고, 연약했고, 뿔테 안경을 썼고, 얇고 희끗희끗하고 푸석한 염소 수염을 달고 있었다. 호감상의 난쟁이 — 머리는 한쪽으로 기울인 채 반쯤 감은 눈으로 미소 짓는구나.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Alt, in großer Leibesfülle, unter leichten Herzbeschwerden, lag ich nach dem Mittagessen, einen Fuß am Boden, auf dem Ruhebett und las ein geschichtliches Werk. Die Magd kam und meldete, zwei Finger an den zugespitzten Lippen, einen Gast.<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
»Wer ist es?« fragte ich, ärgerlich darüber, zu einer Zeit, da ich den Nachmittagskaffee erwartete, einen Gast empfangen zu sollen. »Ein Chineser«, sagte die Magd und unterdrückte, krampfhaft sich drehend, ein Lachen, das der Gast vor der Türe nicht hören sollte.<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
»Ein Chinese? Zu mir? Ist er in Chinesenkleidung?« Die Magd nickte, noch immer mit dem Lachreiz kämpfend. »Nenn ihm meinen Namen, frag, ob er wirklich mich besuchen will, der ich unbekannt im Nachbarhaus, wie sehr erst unbekannt in China bin.«<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Die Magd schlich zu mir und flüsterte: »Er hat nur eine Visitkarte, darauf steht, daß er vorgelassen zu werden bittet. Deutsch kann er nicht, er redet eine unverständliche Sprache, die Karte ihm wegzunehmen fürchtete ich mich.«<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
»Er soll kommen!« rief ich, warf in der Erregtheit, in die ich durch mein Herzleiden oft geriet, das Buch zu Boden und verfluchte die Ungeschicklichkeit der Magd. Aufstehend und meine Riesengestalt reckend, mit der ich in dem niedrigen Zimmer jeden Besucher erschrecken mußte, ging ich zur Tür. Tatsächlich hatte mich der Chinese kaum erblickt, als er gleich wieder hinaushuschte. Ich langte nur in den Gang und zog den Mann vorsichtig an seinem Seidengürtel zu mir herein. Es war offenbar ein Gelehrter, klein, schwach, mit Hornbrille, schütterem grauschwarzem steifem Ziegenbart. Ein freundliches Männchen, hielt den Kopf geneigt und lächelte mit halbgeschlossenen Augen.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">vi.</h4>

<p>어느 날 아침, 변호사 부케팔루스 박사는 그의 가정부에게 침대로 오게 하고는 그녀에게 말했다. “오늘 내 동생 부케팔루스 대 트롤해타 사<sub>社</sub> 소송의 큰 재판이 있소. 나는 원고의 편에서 법정에 서지요. 재판이 적어도 수일은 걸릴 테다가, 정말이지 휴식 시간이 없을 것이니, 다음 며칠 동안 나는 집에 전혀 오지 않을 거요. 소송이 끝나거나, 끝날 조짐이 보이는 대로 전화를 주겠소. 지금으로서는 더이상 말할 수도 없고, 어떠한 질문에도 답할 수 없소. 당연히 내 목소리를 최대의 역량으로 보존하는 데 집중해야 하니 말이오. 그런 연유로, 나에게 아침 식사로 두 개의 날달걀과 꿀을 섞은 차를 가져다주겠소?” 그리고, 천천히 등을 베개 속에 묻히며, 눈 위를 손으로 덮은 채, 그는 침묵에 빠졌다.</p>

<p>수다스러울지언정 집주인 앞에 설 때면 두려워 죽을 지경이던 가정부는 이에 실로 당황했다. 그토록 놀라운 소식은 그리 갑작스럽게도 찾아오는 것이었다. 바로 전날 저녁만 하더라도 집주인은 그녀와 말 몇 마디를 나누었건만 곧 다가올 일에 관해서는 아무런 내색도 비치지 않았다. 하지만 재판 일정이 밤중에 정해졌을 수는 없지 않은가? 그리고 날밤을 새우면서 쉼 없이 진행되는 재판이 있던가? 그리고 왜 집주인은 이전에는 일절 알려준 적 없는 피고와 원고의 이름을 언급한 것인가? 그리고 작은 청과물 상점을 운영하는 집주인의 동생 아돌프 부케팔루스가 — 그나저나 그는 집주인과 지난 오랜 기간 좋은 관계로 보이지는 않았다 — 도대체 어떠한 거대한 소송에 연루되었다는 것인가? 그리고 집주인 앞으로 형언하기 힘들 정도의 시련이 닥쳤다는 사실이, 지금 그가 — 이른 새벽빛이 착시를 일으키는 것이 아니라면 — 초췌해진 자신의 얼굴을 손으로 가리는 모습과 어울린다고 정녕 말할 수 있는가? 그리고 그가 늘 원하던, 기력을 완전히 충전시켜 줄 약간의 와인과 햄은 막론하고 오직 차와 달걀만 받고자 한 것은? 그런 생각을 하며 가정부는 부엌으로 물러가, 그녀가 가장 좋아하는, 꽃과 카나리아가 있는 창가의 자리에 잠깐 앉아, 빗장으로 잠긴 창문 너머로 반쯤 벌거벗은 채 함께 뛰놀며 씨름하는 두 아이가 보이는 안뜰 너머를 바라보더니, 이내 일어나 한숨을 쉬고는, 차를 내고, 선반에서 달걀 두 개를 꺼내, 식사를 쟁반에 정돈하고, 차마 어쩔 수 없어 와인 한 병도 준비한 채, 모든 것을 침실로 가져갔다.</p>

<p>방은 비어 있었다. 어떻게, 집주인이 벌써 떠났을 리는 없을 텐데? 단 일 분 만에 옷을 입을 수는 없지 않은가? 하지만 그의 속옷과 양복은 어디에도 보이지 않았다. 도대체 집주인은 뭐 하자는 것인지 환장할 노릇이다. 서둘러 복도로! 코트, 모자, 그리고 지팡이조차 없다. 그렇다면 창문으로! 맙소사, 저기 대문을 나서는 집주인이 있다 — 머리 뒤로 모자를 걸치고, 코트 앞섶은 풀린 채, 손은 서류가방을 꽉 쥐었고, 주머니에 꿴 갈고리 위로 지팡이는 대롱거린다.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Der Advokat Dr. Bucephalus ließ eines Morgens seine Wirtschafterin zu seinem Bett kommen und sagte ihr: »Heute beginnt die große Verhandlung im Prozeß meines Bruders Bucephalus gegen die Firma Trollhätta. Ich führe die Klage, und da die Verhandlung zumindest einige Tage dauern wird, und zwar ohne eigentliche Unterbrechung, werde ich in den nächsten Tagen überhaupt nicht nach Hause kommen. Sobald die Verhandlung beendet sein oder Aussicht auf Beendigung vorhanden sein wird, werde ich Ihnen telephonieren. Mehr kann ich jetzt nicht sagen, auch nicht die geringste Frage beantworten, da ich natürlich auf Erhaltung meiner vollen Stimmkraft bedacht sein muß. Deshalb bringen Sie mir auch zum Frühstück zwei rohe Eier und Tee mit Honig.« Und sich langsam in die Polster zurücklehnend, die Hand über den Augen, verstummte er.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Die plappermäulige, aber vor ihrem Herrn in Furcht ersterbende Wirtschafterin war sehr betroffen. So plötzlich kam eine so außerordentliche Anordnung. Noch abends hatte der Herr mit ihr gesprochen, aber keine Andeutung darüber gemacht, was bevorstand. Die Verhandlung konnte doch nicht in der Nacht angesetzt worden sein. Und gibt es Verhandlungen, die tagelang ununterbrochen dauern? Und warum nannte der Herr die Prozeßparteien, was er doch ihr gegenüber sonst niemals tat? Und was für einen ungeheuern Prozeß konnte der Bruder des Herrn, der kleine Gemüsehändler Adolf Bucephalus haben, mit dem übrigens der Herr schon seit langem auf keinem guten Fuß zu stehen schien? Und wie paßte es zu den unausdenkbaren Anstrengungen, die dem Herrn bevorstanden, daß er jetzt so müde in seinem Bette lag und sein, wenn das Frühlicht nicht täuschte, irgendwie verfallenes Gesicht mit der Hand bedeckte? Und nur Tee und Eier sollten gebracht werden, nicht auch wie sonst ein wenig Wein und Schinken, um die Lebensgeister völlig aufzuwecken? Mit solchen Gedanken kehrte die Wirtschafterin in die Küche zurück, setzte sich nur für ein Weilchen auf ihren Lieblingsplatz beim Fenster, zu den Blumen und dem Kanarienvogel, blickte auf die gegenüberliegende Hofseite, wo hinter einem Fenstergitter zwei Kinder halbnackt im Spiel miteinander kämpften, wandte sich dann seufzend ab, goß den Tee ein, holte zwei Eier aus der Speisekammer, ordnete alles auf einem Tablett, konnte es sich nicht versagen, die Weinflasche als wohltätige Verlockung auch mitzunehmen und ging mit dem allem ins Schlafzimmer.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Es war leer. Wie, der Herr war doch nicht schon weg? In einer Minute konnte er sich doch nicht angezogen haben? Aber die Wäsche und die Kleider waren auch nicht mehr zu sehn. Was hat denn der Herr um Himmels willen? Ins Vorzimmer! Auch Mantel, Hut und Stock sind fort. Zum Fenster! Beim Leibhaftigen, da tritt der Herr aus dem Tor, den Hut im Nacken, den Mantel offen, die Aktenmappe an sich gedrückt, den Stock in eine Manteltasche gehängt.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">vii.</h4>

<p>당신은 파리의 트로카데로를 아십니까? 사진만 봐서는 전혀 짐작하지 못할 크기를 자랑하는 이 건물에서, 아주 대단한 재판의 핵심 심리가 지금 이 순간 진행되고 있습니다. 어쩌면 당신은 그토록 큰 건물을 어떻게 이처럼 지독한 겨울에 난방하는 것이 가능한지 궁금할지도 모르겠습니다. 건물은 난방되지 않습니다. 이와 같은 경우에 난방부터 생각하기란, 당신이 인생을 보낸 곳과 같은 안락한 소도시에 사는 사람들에게나 가능한 일이죠. 트로카데로는 난방이 없지만 이것이 심리의 진행을 방해하지는 않습니다. 오히려 모든 방향에서 뿜어져 나오는 한기 속에서, 심리는 그에 정확히 부응하는 빠르기로 진행됩니다. 가로와 세로를 종횡무진 가르며.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Sie kennen das Trocadéro in Paris? In diesem Gebäude, von dessen Ausdehnung Sie sich nach bloßen Abbildungen keine auch nur annähernde Vorstellung machen können, findet soeben die Hauptverhandlung in einem großen Prozeß statt. Sie denken vielleicht nach, wie es möglich ist, ein solches Gebäude in diesem fürchterlichen Winter genügend zu heizen. Es wird nicht geheizt. In einem solchen Fall gleich an die Heizung denken, das kann man nur in dem niedlichen Landstädtchen, in dem Sie Ihr Leben verbringen. Das Trocadéro wird nicht geheizt, aber dadurch wird der Fortgang des Prozesses nicht gehindert, im Gegenteil, mitten in dieser von allen Seiten herauf und herab strahlenden Kälte wird in ganz ebenbürtigem Tempo kreuz und quer, der Länge und der Breite nach, prozessiert.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">viii.</h4>

<p>어제 실신<sub>失神</sub>이 나를 찾아왔다. 그녀는 이웃집에 산다. 나는 예전부터 저녁 무렵이면 종종 그녀가 몸을 굽히며 대문을 지나 사라지는 것을 보았다. 길게 흘러내리는 옷과 깃털이 꽂힌 넓은 모자를 쓴 거구의 여인. 그녀는 마치 죽어가는 환자에게 너무 늦게 도착한 것은 아닌지 두려워하는 의사처럼 급히 문을 열고는 소란스레 들어왔다. “안톤” — 그녀는 공허하면서도 자부하는 듯한 목소리로 외쳤다 — “제가 왔어요, 제가 여기 있어요!” 내가 가리킨 소파에 그녀는 기꺼이 털썩 주저앉았다.</p>

<p>“높이도 사는군요, 높이도 살아요.” 그녀는 신음하듯이 말했다.</p>

<p>나는 내 안락의자에 파묻힌 채 고개를 끄덕였다. 눈앞으로는 내 방으로 이어지는 수많은 계단이 끝없이 일렁이는 물결처럼 앞다투어 튀어 올랐다.</p>

<p>“어찌 이리도 춥나요?” 그녀는 묻더니, 헌 펜싱 장갑처럼 생긴 그녀의 기다란 장갑을 벗어 탁자 위로 던지고는 갸우뚱한 고개로 나를 바라보며 눈을 찡긋했다. 나로서는 한 마리의 참새가 된 듯한 기분이었으니, 계단 위에서 폴짝이며 날갯짓을 연습하는데 그녀가 나의 부드럽고 솜털 같은 회색 깃털을 헝클어뜨리는 것이었다.</p>

<p>“당신이 저에 대한 그리움으로 괴로워한다니 진심으로 유감이에요.” 그녀가 말했다. “이따금 당신이 안뜰에 서서 제 창문을 올려다볼 때면 당신의 피폐한 얼굴에서 깊은 슬픔을 읽곤 했지요. 그래요, 제가 당신에게 적의를 품은 것은 아니랍니다. 비록 당신이 제 마음을 아직 얻지 못했어도, 그것을 쟁취하는 것 또한 불가능하진 않으니까요.”</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Gestern kam eine Ohnmacht zu mir. Sie wohnt im Nachbarhaus, ich habe sie dort schon öfters abends im niedrigen Tor gebückt verschwinden sehn. Eine große Dame mit lang fließendem Kleid und breitem, mit Federn geschmücktem Hut. Eiligst kam sie rauschend durch meine Tür, wie ein Arzt, der fürchtet, zu spät zum auslöschenden Kranken gekommen zu sein. »Anton«, rief sie mit hohler und doch sich rühmender Stimme, »ich komme, ich bin da!«
In den Sessel, auf den ich zeigte, ließ sie sich fallen.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
»Hoch wohnst du, hoch wohnst du«, sagte sie stöhnend.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Tief in meinem Lehnstuhl nickte ich. Zahllos hüpften vor meinen Augen die Treppenstufen auf, die zu meinen Zimmern führten, eine hinter der andern, unermüdliche kleine Wellen.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
»Warum so kalt?« fragte sie, zog ihre langen alten Fechterhandschuhe aus, warf sie auf den Tisch und sah mich, den Kopf geneigt, augenzwinkernd an.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Mir war, als sei ich ein Spatz, übe auf der Treppe meine Sprünge und sie zerzause mein weiches flockiges graues Gefieder.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
»Es tut mir von Herzen leid, daß du dich nach mir verzehrst. Oft schon sah ich aufrichtig traurig in dein abgehärmtes Gesicht, wenn du im Hof standst und zu meinem Fenster aufblicktest. Nun, ich bin dir nicht ungünstig gesinnt und hast du auch mein Herz noch nicht, so kannst du es doch erobern.«
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">ix.</h4>

<p>사람은 이토록 무관심에 빠질 수 있는가 — 그가 영원히 올바른 길을 잃어버렸다는 그토록 깊은 신념에.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
In was für Gleichgültigkeit Menschen kommen können, in wie tiefe Überzeugung, für immer die rechte Spur verloren zu haben.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">x.</h4>

<p><strong>착오.</strong> 내가 연 것은 긴 복도 끝 위쪽에 있는 내 방의 문이 아니었다. “착오였습니다,” 라는 말과 함께 나는 다시 나가려고 했다. 그 순간, 나는 방 안쪽으로 수척하고 수염이 없는 사내를 보았다. 입을 굳게 다문 채, 그가 앉은 작은 탁자에는 단 하나의 석유 램프만이 있었다.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
<i>Ein Irrtum.</i> Es war nicht meine Türe oben auf dem langen Gang, die ich geöffnet hatte. »Ein Irrtum«, sagte ich und wollte wieder hinausgehen. Da sah ich den Inwohner, einen mageren bartlosen Mann, mit festgeschlossenem Munde an einem Tischchen sitzen, auf dem nur eine Petroleumlampe stand.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">xi.</h4>

<p>우리의 집 — 변두리에 위치한 이 거대한 건물, 지울 수 없는 중세의 폐허가 스며든 다세대 주택에서, 얼음 같은 안개가 낀 금일의 겨울 아침 이런 공문이 게시되었다.</p>

<p>모든 세입자께 알립니다.</p>

<p>나는 다섯 자루의 장난감 총을 가지고 있습니다. 총은 저마다 고리에 걸린 채 내 장롱에 보관되어 있습니다. 첫 번째 총은 나의 것이지만 나머지는 원하는 사람이 가져가도 좋습니다. 네 명보다 많은 희망자가 있을 시 자신이 소유한 총을 가져 와 장롱에 두어야 합니다. 통일성은 반드시 지켜져야만 하기 때문입니다. 통일성 없이는 우리는 앞으로 나아갈 수 없습니다. 그나저나 내가 가지고 있는 총들이란 죄다 어떤 용도로도 쓸모가 없습니다. 기계 장치는 망가졌고, 노리쇠는 떨어져 나갔으며, 오직 방아쇠만이 여전히 딸깍거릴 뿐입니다. 그러니 필요하다면, 이런 총을 더 많이 구하기란 어려운 일이 아닐 것입니다. 하지만 근본적으로 보면, 첫 시도에는 총이 없는 사람들도 괜찮을 듯합니다. 우리 총을 가진 사람들이 결정적인 순간에 무장하지 않은 자들을 가운데로 몰아넣을 것입니다. 이 전투 방식은 최초의 미국 농부들이 인디언들과 맞설 때 증명된 방법인 만큼, 상황의 유사성을 고려할 때 여기서도 통하지 않을 리 있겠습니까? 생각해 보면 우리는 심지어 오래도록 총을 포기할 수도 있고, 이 다섯 자루조차 꼭 필요한 것은 아닙니다만, 단지 이미 존재하기 때문에 쓰자는 것뿐입니다. 하지만 다른 네 사람이 총을 들기를 원하지 않는다면, 그렇게 하지 않아도 됩니다. 그러면 나 혼자서만 지도자로서 총을 들겠습니다. 그러나 우리는 지도자를 가져서는 안 됩니다. 그래서 나 또한 내 총을 부수거나 내려놓을 것입니다.</p>

<p>이것이 첫 번째 공문이었다. 우리의 집에 사는 사람들은 시간도 없고 공문을 읽거나 숙고할 의욕도 없다. 얼마 안 있어 그 종이쪼가리는 다락방에서 시작해 복도로 터져 나온 더러운 물줄기에 흠뻑 젖은 채로 계단을 따라 쓸려 나가더니 그곳 밑에서 역류하는 물줄기와 싸우는 신세가 되었다. 그러나 일주일 뒤 두 번째 공문이 붙었다.</p>

<p>세입자들이여!</p>

<p>지금까지 아무도 나에게 연락하지 않았습니다. 나는 내 생계에 필수적인 일을 하지 않는 시간에는 항상 집에 머물러 있었습니다. 집을 비울 때는 방문을 열어두어, 원하는 사람은 누구든 이름을 적을 수 있도록 책상 위에 종이를 놓아두었습니다. 아무도 이름을 적지 않았습니다.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
In unserem Haus, diesem ungeheuren Vorstadthaus, einer von unzerstörbaren mittelalterlichen Ruinen durchwachsenen Mietskaserne, wurde heute am nebligen eisigen Wintermorgen folgender Aufruf verbreitet:
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
An alle meine Hausgenossen:
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Ich besitze fünf Kindergewehre. Sie hängen in meinem Kasten, an jedem Haken eines. Das erste gehört mir, zu den andern kann sich melden, wer will. Melden sich mehr als vier, so müssen die überzähligen ihre eigenen Gewehre mitbringen und in meinem Kasten deponieren. Denn Einheitlichkeit muß sein, ohne Einheitlichkeit kommen wir nicht vorwärts. Übrigens habe ich nur Gewehre, die zu sonstiger Verwendung ganz unbrauchbar sind, der Mechanismus ist verdorben, der Pfropfen abgerissen, nur die Hähne knacken noch. Es wird also nicht schwer sein, nötigenfalls noch weitere solche Gewehre zu beschaffen. Aber im Grunde sind mir für die erste Zeit auch Leute ohne Gewehre recht. Wir, die wir Gewehre haben, werden im entscheidenden Augenblick die Unbewaffneten in die Mitte nehmen. Eine Kampfesweise, die sich bei den ersten amerikanischen Farmern gegenüber den Indianern bewährt hat, warum sollte sie sich nicht auch hier bewähren, da doch die Verhältnisse ähnlich sind. Man kann also sogar für die Dauer auf die Gewehre verzichten und selbst die fünf Gewehre sind nicht unbedingt nötig, und nur weil sie schon einmal vorhanden sind, sollen sie auch verwendet werden. Wollen sie aber die vier andern nicht tragen, so sollen sie es bleiben lassen. Dann werde also ich allein als Führer eines tragen. Aber wir sollen keinen Führer haben und so werde auch ich mein Gewehr zerbrechen oder weglegen.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Das war der erste Aufruf. In unserem Haus hat man keine Zeit und keine Lust, Aufrufe zu lesen oder gar zu überdenken. Bald schwammen die kleinen Papiere in dem Schmutzstrom, der, vom Dachboden ausgehend, von allen Korridoren genährt, die Treppe hinabspült und dort mit dem Gegenstrom kämpft, der von unten hinaufschwillt. Aber nach einer Woche kam ein zweiter Aufruf:
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Hausgenossen!
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Es hat sich bisher niemand bei mir gemeldet. Ich war, soweit ich nicht meinen Lebensunterhalt verdienen muß, fortwährend zu Hause und für die Zeit meiner Abwesenheit, während welcher meine Zimmertür stets offen war, lag auf meinem Tisch ein Blatt, auf dem sich jeder, der wollte, einschreiben konnte. Niemand hats getan.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">xii.</h4>

<p>가끔씩 나는, 내가 기계공장에서의 교대근무를 마치고 밤늦게 또는 이른 아침에 집으로 돌아올 때, 내가 저지른, 그리고 저지를, 과거와 미래의 모든 죄가 뼈마디의 통증으로 속죄되는 것은 아닌지 생각한다. 나는 내가 이 일을 견딜 수 있을 정도로 강하지 않다는 사실을 이미 오래전부터 알고 있다. 그러나 나는 아무것도 바꾸지 않는다.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Manchmal glaube ich, alle meine vergangenen und künftigen Sünden durch die Schmerzen meiner Knochen abzubüßen, wenn ich abends oder gar morgens nach einer Nachtschicht aus der Maschinenfabrik nach Hause komme. Ich bin nicht kräftig genug zu dieser Arbeit, das weiß ich schon seit langem und doch ändere ich nichts.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">xiii.</h4>

<p>우리의 집 — 변두리에 위치한 이 거대한 건물, 중세의 폐허가 스며든 다세대 주택에는, 나와 같은 복도에서 한 노동자 가족과 같이 사는 서기가 있다. 사람들은 그를 공무원이라고 부르지만 실상은 하찮은 서기에 불과하며, 낯선 부부와 그들의 여섯 자식 틈에 끼인 채 바닥에 깔린 밀짚 둥지에서 밤을 보내는 자이다. 그리고 그가 그토록 하찮은 서기라면, 내가 그에게 무슨 신경을 쓰겠는가. 이 집 — 도시가 끓여낸 불행이란 불행은 다 모인 이 집에도, 적어도 백 명은 넘는 사람들이 살거늘…</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
In unserm Hause, diesem ungeheuren Vorstadthause, einer von mittelalterlichen Ruinen durchwachsenen Mietskaserne, wohnt auf dem gleichen Gang wie ich, bei einer Arbeiterfamilie, ein Amtsschreiber. Sie nennen ihn zwar Beamter, aber er kann doch nur ein kleiner Schreiber sein, der mitten in dem Nest des fremden Ehepaars und seiner sechs Kinder auf einem Strohsack am Boden die Nächte verbringt. Und wenn es also ein kleiner Schreiber ist, was kümmert er mich. Selbst in diesem Haus, in dem sich doch das Elend versammelt, das die Stadt auskocht, gibt es gewiß über hundert Leute...
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">xiv.</h4>

<p>나와 같은 복도에는 한 수선재봉사가 산다.
아무리 조심해도 내 옷은 너무 빨리 닳아서, 최근에도 나는 그에게 다시 외투 하나를 들고 가야만 했다.
그날은 참으로 아름답고 따뜻한 여름 저녁이었다.
재봉사는 자신과 아내, 그리고 여섯 아이까지 모두 단 한 칸의 방 — 그 방은 부엌이기도 하다 — 에서 살고 있다.
그런데도 그는 심지어 한 세무청의 서기를 세입자로 들였다.
이 정도로 들어찬 방은 이미 열악하기 짝이 없는 우리 주택의 기준으로 봐도 지나친 수준이다.
그렇다고는 해도 사람은 각자의 사정이 있고, 재봉사에게 또한 그의 절약에 달아날 수 없는 이유가 분명히 있겠거니,
외부인이 그 이유에 대해 굳이 이야기하려는 일은 없다.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Auf dem gleichen Gang wie ich wohnt ein Flickschneider. Trotz aller Vorsicht verbrauche ich die Kleider zu bald, letzthin mußte ich wieder einen Rock zum Schneider tragen. Es war ein schöner, warmer Sommerabend. Der Schneider hat für sich, die Frau und sechs Kinder nur ein Zimmer, das gleichzeitig Küche ist. Überdies aber hat er noch einen Mieter bei sich, einen Schreiber von der Steuerbehörde. Dieser Zimmerbelag geht doch ein wenig über das Übliche hinaus, das ja in unserem Hause schon arg genug ist. Immerhin, man läßt jedem das Seine, der Schneider hat gewiß für seine Sparsamkeit unwiderlegliche Gründe und keinem Fremden fällt es ein, eine Besprechung dieser Gründe einzuleiten.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">xv.</h4>

<p>1917년 2월 19일.</p>

<p>오늘은 헤르만과 도로테아, 그리고 리히터 회고록 약간을 읽었으며, 그의 사진들을 봤고, 마지막으로 하웁트만의 그리젤다에서 나오는 장면을 읽었다. 한 시간이라는 순간 안에 나는 다른 사람이 되어 있었다. 모든 풍경은 여전히 안개처럼 뿌옇지만, 이제는 안개 그림으로 변했다. 오늘 처음 신어 보는 질긴 장화 속에는 — 그 장화는 원래 군사용으로 만들어진 것이었다 — 또다른 사람이 서 있었다.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
19. Februar 1917.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Heute gelesen Hermann und Dorothea, einiges aus Richters Lebenserinnerungen, Bilder von ihm gesehn und schließlich eine Szene aus Hauptmanns Griselda gelesen. Bin für den Augenblick der nächsten Stunde ein anderer Mensch. Alle Aussichten zwar nebelhaft wie immer, aber veränderte Nebelbilder. In den schweren Stiefeln, die ich heute zum erstenmal angezogen habe (sie waren ursprünglich für den Militärdienst bestimmt), steckt ein anderer Mensch.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">xvi.</h4>

<p>저는 크룸홀츠 씨 댁에 삽니다. 방은 세무청의 한 서기와 나눠 쓰지요. 그 방에서는 크룸홀츠 씨의 두 딸 — 여섯 살, 일곱 살 소녀입니다 — 또한 같은 침대에서 잡니다. 서기가 이사를 해온 첫날부터 — 저로 말하자면 이미 수년 동안 크룸홀츠 씨 댁에 살고 있었습니다 — 저는 그의 첫인상에서 석연찮은 수상함을 느꼈습니다. 평균 신장 이하의 남성. 허약한 체격과, 건강하다고는 할 수 없는 폐. 후줄근한 회색 옷가지. 나이를 가늠할 수 없는 주름진 얼굴. 귀를 덮도록 넘겨진 회갈색의 긴 머리카락. 코끝까지 내려온 안경. 그리고 작고 — 역시나 — 회색인 염소 수염.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Ich wohne bei Herrn Krummholz, das Zimmer teile ich mit einem Schreiber von der Steuerbehörde. Außerdem schlafen in dem Zimmer in gemeinsamem Bett zwei Töchter des Krummholz, ein sechs- und ein siebenjähriges Mädchen. Seit dem ersten Tage, an welchem der Schreiber einzog — ich selbst wohne schon jahrelang bei Krummholz — hatte ich einen zunächst ganz unbestimmten Verdacht gegen ihn. Ein Mann unter Mittelgröße, schwach, wohl mit nicht ganz fester Lunge, grauen, ihn umschlotternden Kleidern, faltigem Gesicht unbestimmbaren Alters, graublonden, länglichen, über die Ohren gekämmten Haaren, einer weit auf der Nase vorgerückten Brille, und einem kleinen, gleichfalls ergrauenden Ziegenbart.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">xvii.</h4>

<p>내가 중부 콩고에서 철도 공사에 종사하며 보냈던 삶은 즐거운 것이 아니었다.</p>

<p>나는 내 오두막집의 차창이 쳐진 베란다에 앉아 있었다. 한쪽으로는 긴 벽 대신 극도로 촘촘한 모기장이 쳐져 있었는데, 그것은 현장 감독관 중 한 명이자 우리의 철도가 지나가는 지역의 족장에게서 얻은 것이었다. 삼베로 만든 그 그물은 튼튼하면서도 섬세하여, 유럽에서는 결코 만들 수 없을 정도였다. 그것은 내 자랑거리였고 많은 이들의 부러움을 샀다. 그 그물이 없었더라면 이렇게 저녁에 베란다에 평화롭게 앉아, 지금처럼 불을 켜고, 오래된 유럽 신문을 샅샅이 펼쳐 읽으며, 파이프를 힘차게 피우는 일은 결코 불가능했을 것이다.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Es war kein heiteres Leben, das ich damals beim Bahnbau am mittlern Kongo führte.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Ich saß in meiner Holzhütte auf der überdeckten Veranda. Anstatt einer Längswand war ein außerordentlich feinmaschiges Moskitonetz ausgespannt, das ich von einem der Arbeiterführer, dem Häuptling eines Stammes, durch dessen Gebiet unsere Bahn gehn sollte, erstanden hatte. Ein Hanfnetz, so fest und zart zugleich, wie man es in Europa gar nicht herstellen könnte. Es war mein Stolz und ich wurde viel darum beneidet. Ohne dieses Netz wäre es gar nicht möglich gewesen, friedlich am Abend auf der Veranda zu sitzen, das Licht aufzudrehn, wie ich es jetzt tat, eine alte europäische Zeitung zum Studium vorzunehmen und mächtig dazu die Pfeife zu rauchen.
</small></div>

<h4 style="font-family: 'Libre Baskerville';">xviii.</h4>

<p>나는 — 누가 자신의 능력을 이토록 자부하며 말할 수 있겠는가 — 행복하며 지칠 줄 모르는 늙은 낚시꾼의 손목을 가지고 있다.</p>

<p>나는 예컨대 집에 앉아, 낚시하러 나가기 전에, 고개를 휙 돌려 오른손을 응시하고는, 한 번은 멀리, 한 번은 가까이 손을 거둔다. 그것만으로도 나는 다가올 낚시의 결과를, 때로는 세세한 부분까지도, 내 시각과 촉각 속에서 예지할 수 있다. 평상시에는 힘을 비축하도록 금팔찌 속에 가둬 두는 이 날렵한 손목의 육감. 나는 내 낚시터의 강물을 구체적인 시각의, 구체적인 물살 속에서 본다. 강의 단면이 내 앞으로 드러난다. 분명한 수와 종류로 열 군데, 스무 군데 — 백 군데 지점에서 물고기들이 단면을 향해 밀려오는 모습이 보인다.
이제 나는 어떻게 낚아야 할지를 안다. 어떤 녀석들은 머리로 그 단면을 파고들어 가거늘, 나는 그들 앞에서 낚싯대를 흔들어댈 뿐인데 그들은 낚시고리에 걸려버린다. 내가 집의 책상에 앉아 있을 때도 황홀감을 안겨주는 운명의 순간. 다른 물고기들은 배<sub>腹</sub>까지 단면에 닿으니 그때가 절정의 기회이다. 나는 몇몇은 여전히 낚아내지만, 다른 물고기들은 꼬리까지 미끄러뜨리며 위험천만한 단면을 지나 내게서 빠져나가고 만다. 하지만 오직 이번뿐이다 — 진정한 낚시꾼은 어떤 물고기도 놓치지 않거늘.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 4em 0;"><small>
Ich habe — wer kann noch so frei von seinen Fähigkeiten sprechen — das Handgelenk eines alten glücklichen unermüdlichen Anglers.
<div style="margin: 1em 0;"></div>
Ich sitze zum Beispiel zu Hause, ehe ich angeln gehe, und drehe scharf zusehend die rechte Hand, einmal hin und einmal her. Das genügt, um mir in Anblick und Gefühl das Ergebnis des künftigen Angelns oft bis in Einzelheiten zu offenbaren. Ein Ahnungsvermögen dieses gelenkigen Gelenkes, das ich in Ruhezeiten, um es Kraft sammeln zu lassen, in ein Goldarmband einschließe. Ich sehe das Wasser meines Fischplatzes in der besonderen Strömung der besonderen Stunde, ein Querschnitt des Flusses zeigt sich mir, eindeutig an Zahl und Art dringen an zehn, zwanzig, ja hundert verschiedenen Stellen Fische gegen diese Schnittfläche vor, nun weiß ich, wie die Angel zu führen ist, manche durchstoßen ungefährdet mit dem Kopf die Fläche, da lasse ich die Angel vor ihnen schwanken und schon hängen sie, die Kürze dieses Schicksalsaugenblicks entzückt mich selbst am häuslichen Tisch, andere Fische dringen bis an den Bauch vor, nun ist hohe Zeit, manche ereile ich noch, andere aber entwischen der gefährlichen Fläche selbst mit dem Schwanz und sind für diesmal mir verloren, nur für diesmal, einem wahren Angler entgeht kein Fisch.
</small></div>

<hr />

<p>서두의 이미지는 막스 리히터, <em>The Blue Notebooks</em> 의 앨범 커버이다.</p>]]></content><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><category term="인문학" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[「여덟 권의 청색 팔절판 노트Acht blaue Oktavhefte」는 1917년 말부터 1919년 중순까지 카프카가 작성한 일련의 노트이다. 「팔절판 노트」라는 이름은 카프카의 출판 담당자인 막스 브로트가 그의 사절판 일기장과 구분하기 위해 붙인 것이다. 이후 브로트가 카프카의 일기를 출판했을 때 「팔절판 노트」는 생략되었는데, 카프카의 다른 일기보다 철학적이고 문학적이라는 점에서 성격을 달리한다는 이유에서였다. 이로 인해 「팔절판 노트」는 카프카 특유의 사색적이고 몽환적인 성격에도 불구하고 세간에 잘 알려져 있지 않으며, 특히 국내에서는 전문이 번역된 바가 없다. 이에 필자가 직접 번역을 시도했다. 비전공자의 번역인 점을 감안하여 독일어 원문을 같이 수록했다.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Franz Kafka, The Blue Octavo Notebooks, Volume 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/17/kafka-blue-octavos/en" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Franz Kafka, The Blue Octavo Notebooks, Volume 1" /><published>2025-06-17T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-06-17T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/17/kafka-blue-octavos/kafka-blue-octavos-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/17/kafka-blue-octavos/en"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/public/the-blue-notebooks.png" style="max-width: 350px; width: 100%; margin: 7em auto 5em auto;" /></p>

<p>This post is originally a Korean translation of Kafka’s <em>The Blue Octavo Notebooks</em>. Given that there already exists an English translation of the work, I won’t go through the hassle of translating into English again. However, I present the following passage, which I particularly admire.</p>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 2em 0 2em 1em;"><small>
Everyone carries a room about inside him. This fact can even be proved by means of the sense of hearing. If someone walks fast and one pricks up one's ears and listens, say in the night, when everything round about is quiet, one hears, for instance, the rattling of a mirror not quite firmly fastened to the wall.</small>
</div>

<div style="font-family: Libre Baskerville; margin: 1.5em 0 0 1em;"><small>
Jeder Mensch trägt ein Zimmer in sich. Diese Tatsache kann man sogar durch das Gehör nachprüfen. Wenn einer schnell geht und man hinhorcht, etwa in der Nacht, wenn alles ringsherum still ist, 
so hört man zum Beispiel das Scheppern eines nicht genug befestigten Wandspiegels.
</small></div>]]></content><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><category term="Humanities" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">슬라보예 지젝, ｢소프트 파시즘, 인공지능, 그리고 수치심의 몰락｣</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/06/zizek-soft-facism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="슬라보예 지젝, ｢소프트 파시즘, 인공지능, 그리고 수치심의 몰락｣" /><published>2025-06-06T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-06-06T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/06/zizek-soft-facism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/06/zizek-soft-facism"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>본 글은 2024년 11월 26일에 이루어진 <a href="https://youtu.be/OSYjmH_WPQQ?si=9Rb5ToZSwf0qg7gx">슬라보예 지젝의 옥스포드 강연</a>을 번역한 것이다. 주석은 역자 주이다. 또한 섹션의 구분도 역자가 독자의 편의를 위해 넣은 것이다. 매끄러운 흐름을 위해 내용을 덧대거나 빼는 수준의 의역과 문장 재배치를 한 부분이 있다.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="1-운명론적-역사관-비판">1. 운명론적 역사관 비판</h2>

<p>저는 “우리가 지금 어디에 있는가”라는 질문에 대한 몇 가지 개괄적인 이야기를 하고자 합니다. — 우리는 지금 어디에 있을까요?</p>

<p>저는 양자역학의 개념을 빌려와서 이 사회적 · 역사적 질문에 접근하고 싶습니다. 우선 저의 기본적인 생각은, 자유주의나 마르크스주의에서 피력하는 낙관적인 역사관을 포기해야 한다는 것입니다. 이러한 역사관들은 운명론적인 특징을 가지고 있습니다. 일례로 후쿠야마<sub>Francis Fukuyama</sub>는 “역사의 종말<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>”을 주장했습니다. 한편 정통 마르크스주의자들은, 여러 굴곡이 있더라도 궁극적으로는 공산주의 사회가 도래할 것이라고 주장합니다. “미래는 사회주의거나 야만주의다”라고 말한 로자 룩셈부르크<sub>Rosa Luxemburg</sub>처럼 운명론에서 아주 살짝 비껴난 입장도 있기는 했지요. 여담이지만, 안타깝게도 룩셈부르크는 이 점에 있어 틀렸습니다. 스탈린주의에는 둘 다 있었으니까요.</p>

<p>이런 운명론에 매달리기보다, 저는 다음과 같이 생각합니다. 양자역학에 따르면, 점 A에서 점 B로 이동하는 입자는 A와 B를 잇는 모든 경로를 양자 중첩 상태로 거칩니다. 우리가 관측하는 것은 그러한 중첩 상태에서 붕괴된 하나의 경로이지요. <strong>저는 우리의 현 사회가 붕괴 전의 중첩 상태라고 생각합니다.</strong> 과연 누가 앞으로의 인류가 어디로 향할지 알겠습니까? 우리가 아는 것은 우리의 미래에 치명적인 위협들이 있다는 것뿐입니다. 환경, 전쟁, 인구 문제 등이 떠오르네요. 우리는 이러한 위협들이 어떻게 상호작용할지도 오리무중입니다. 어떤 사람들은 환경 위기가 심각해지면 전쟁은 줄어들 것이라고 생각합니다. 저는 이 점에 관해 회의적입니다.</p>

<h2 id="2-소프트-파시즘과-불량-국가">2. 소프트 파시즘과 불량 국가</h2>

<p>이러한 위협들에 대응하는 과정에서 어쩌면 미래에는 새로운 사회주의가 도래할지도 모릅니다. 일부 문명만이 섬처럼 고립된 형태의 세계적인 야만주의가 도래할지도 모르지요. 그러나 제가 예상하건대 — 그리고 이 예상은 저를 정말 슬프게 만듭니다 — 가장 도래할 가능성이 높은 미래는 제가 <strong>소프트 파시즘<sub>Soft Fascism</sub></strong>이라고 부르는 것입니다. 여기서 “소프트”라는 표현은 이것이 나치주의와 같은 노골적인 파시즘이 아님을 의미합니다. 제가 생각하기에 파시즘의 가장 괜찮은 정의는 “보수적인 혁명”입니다. 영리한 파시스트들은 자본주의의 활력과 빠른 발전력을 탐내면서도, 방임된 자본주의는 사회 분열을 초래한다는 사실을 알았습니다. <strong>이 문제를 극복하기 위한 파시즘의 발상은, 강력한 국가 권력이 전통 · 종교 · 민족 등의 이데올로기를 통해 자본주의적 경제 구조를 억지로 유지해 내는 사회입니다.</strong></p>

<p>제가 소프트 파시즘의 교과서적인 사례로 생각하는 국가가 있습니다. 바로 중국입니다. 두 달 전, 중국 지도자의 연설이 있었습니다. 그는 우리 세대의 젊은이들이 충분히 교육되지 않았으며 그들을 사상적으로 훈련시켜야 한다고 말했습니다. 저는 그래서 그가 늘 하던 말 — 마르크스를 읽으라는 둥, 마오를 읽으라는 둥 — 을 할 줄 알았습니다. 하지만 아니었습니다. 그가 언급한 것은 유교 전통이었습니다. 통합을 위해서는 유교 정신이 필요하다는 것이었습니다. 같은 일이 인도에서는 모디<sub>Narendra Modi</sub>에 의해 행해지고 있습니다.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> 극도로 야만적인 자본주의 체제가 비자본주의적인 이데올로기를 통해 유지됩니다. 저에게 물어본다면, 이것이 대다수의 국가가 봉착하게 될 미래입니다. 역사는 우리의 편에 서 있지 않습니다.</p>

<p>저를 염려시키는 또다른 사실은, 소위 <strong>불량 국가<sub>rogue state</sub></strong>들이 점점 많아지고 있다는 것입니다. 당황하지 마세요. 제가 말하는 “불량 국가”는 서구의 제국주의적 언어에 해당하지 않습니다.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> 제가 정의하는 “불량 국가”란, <strong>현존하는 질서가 자기 자신의 이데올로기적 조건 속에서 스스로를 법적으로 유지할 수 없기 때문에 야만적이고 불법적인 폭력에 의존해야 하는 국가</strong>입니다.</p>

<p>아무래도 아이티가 가장 먼저 따오르는 사례군요. 그곳은 국가가 붕괴하여 국토의 80% 이상이 갱단에 의해 경영되고 있습니다. 하지만 굳이 아이티 같은 이례적인 사례에 집착할 필요는 없습니다. 러시아는 어떻습니까? 바그너 그룹은 전형적인 반법<sub>半法</sub>, 불법 군사 조직으로서, 이제는 러시아 정부의 전폭적인 지지를 받아왔음이 만천하에 드러났습니다. 그럼에도 불구하고 바그너 그룹은 중앙 정부와 언제나 일정한 거리를 두었죠. 그런가 하면 이스라엘은요? 솔직해집시다. 서안 지구<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>에 정착한 이스라엘인들은 다름아닌 이스라엘의 법에 따라 범법자들입니다. 이스라엘의 비극을 잘 보여주는 사례가 있습니다. 이타마르 벤그리브는 20여년 전에 인종 범죄로 이스라엘 법정에 기소된 바 있습니다. 지금 그는 이스라엘 안보부 장관입니다. 미국도 크게 다르지 않습니다. 현재 미국에는 반이슬람주의자, 반유대주의자, 프라우드 보이즈<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>와 같은 단체들이 공존하고 있습니다. 그리고 트럼프는 그들과 거리를 두면서도 그들을 통해 사회를 조종합니다. 이들이야말로 실패한 국가들입니다. 이들은 그 자신의 이데올리기와 법적 근거만을 통해서는 질서를 지탱할 수 없는 국가들입니다.</p>

<p><strong>따라서 우리는 현재의 극단적인 혼돈과 비결정성을 인지해야만 합니다.</strong> 현재의 상황이 언제까지나 이어질 수 없다는 사실은 명백합니다. 그러나 그 종착지가 어디일지는 그 어떤 의미에서도 결정된 것이 아닙니다. 다시 양자역학의 용어를 빌리자면, 우리의 중첩 상태가 어떠한 하나의 상태로 붕괴할지 전혀 알 수 없습니다. 미래가 가장 바람직한 특정 정치 형태로 나아가리라는 생각은 일종의 착시입니다.</p>

<h2 id="3-사후성">3. 사후성</h2>

<p>자세히 말할 시간은 없지만 저는 헤겔이 이것을 내다보았다고 생각합니다. 사후성<sub>retroactivity</sub>에 관한 헤겔의 논의를 봅시다. 특정한 현실이 자리를 잡으면, 그 현실이 과거를 실질적으로 변화시키지는 않지만 <em>사후적으로는</em> 변화시킵니다. <strong>다시 말해, 현재는 우리가 과거를 인지하는 방식과 과거에 부여하는 서사를 변화시킵니다.</strong> 그런 의미에서 우리는 늘 과거를 변화시키고 있습니다. 같은 주장을 마르크스에서도 발견할 수 있습니다. 마르크스는 순진한 진보주의자로 폄하되곤 하지만 — 물론 그에게 이러한 면모가 실제로 있었음은 부정할 수 없습니다 — 그에게는 다른 면모도 있습니다. 예를 들어 그의 ⟪정치경제학 비판 요강⟫에는 이런 대목이 있습니다. “인간의 해부학이 유인원의 해부학을 이해하는 열쇠인 것처럼 자본주의는 역사의 모든 단계를 해석하는 능력을 제공한다.” 마르크스의 이 대목은 놀랍도록 반-운명론적인 것입니다. 여기서 그가 말하려는 것은 “자본주의의 도래는 예정된 것이었다”와 같은 말이 아닙니다. 마르크스의 요점은 훨씬 더 정교합니다. 자본주의가 승리하고 나면, 우리는 <em>사후적으로</em> 역사를 해석하여 과거의 모든 사건들이 마치 자본주의를 향해 왔던 것처럼 재서술한다는 것입니다.</p>

<p>이러한 이유로 저는 데이비드 그레이버<sub>David Graeber</sub>와 윈그로<sub>David Wengrow</sub>의 연구를 — 비록 그들의 주장에 완전히 동의하지는 않지만 — 아주 높이 평가합니다. 그들은 고대 잉카 문명에서, 현대의 우리가 처한 것과 같은 중첩 상태를 포착하고자 했습니다. 잘 아시겠지만, 잉카 문명이 언제나 아이들을 희생시키는 식의 공포로 점철된 것은 아니었습니다. 잉카에서는 놀라운 수준의 지역 민주주의 체계가 작동하고 있었습니다. 어느 순간 붕괴했을 뿐이었지요. 이로부터 제가 내리는 교훈은 이것입니다. <strong>일어나는 일들을 이해하기 위해서는, 일어날 수 있었지만 일어나지 않은 일들에 주목해야 합니다.</strong> 일어날 <em>수</em> 있었지만 일어나지 않은 일들은 그저 소멸하지 않습니다. 그것은 어쩌면 반동적인, 어쩌면 진보적인, 일종의 염원으로서 사회에 잔존합니다.</p>

<h2 id="4-인공지능과-인간다움">4. 인공지능과 인간다움</h2>

<p>이러한 이유로 저는 우리가 “진보”를 정의하는 데 있어 매우 조심해야 한다고 생각합니다. 예를 들어 오늘날의 중요한 주제인 인공지능의 사례를 봅시다. 저는 우리가 “인공지능도 사고할 수 있게 될까?”와 같은 질문만 던져서는 인공지능의 문제에 올바르게 접근할 수 없다고 생각합니다. 물론 여기서 말하는 “사고”란 우리 인간과 같은 방식의 사고를 말합니다. 우선 이것은 우리가 답을 알지 못하는 추상적인 질문입니다. 우리는 우리와 같은 방식의 사고 가능성에 집착하지만, 완전히 새로운 형태의 정신이라든가 영혼이 생길 수도 있는 것 아니겠습니까?</p>

<p>대신 제가 여러분을 자극할 만한 정신분석학적 접근을 제시해 보겠습니다. “인공지능이 무엇을 할 수 있는가” — 흔히 있는 멍청한 토론 주제죠 — 라는 질문을 생각해 보면, 당연히 인공지능은 우리보다 훨씬 빠르게 계산할 수 있고, 스스로 학습할 수 있고, 자기 복제할 수 있습니다. 그러나 제 생각에는 인간에게 고유한, 그리고 인간다움의 핵심을 이루는 두 가지 특징이 있습니다.</p>

<p><strong>첫째는 일상에서의 의식, 달리 말하자면 미신적 습관입니다.</strong> 개인적인 사례를 들자면 저는 손을 씻고 수도꼭지를 잠굴 때 꼭지에서 물방울이 떨어지고 있지 않다는 것을 똑똑히 보고서도 꼭지에 손을 대서 확인하곤 합니다. 정신분석학자라면 이것을 피임에 대한 무의식적 강박으로 해석할지 모르겠지만 그런 말도 안 되는 소리는 사양하겠습니다. 이것은 단적인 습관일 뿐입니다. 하지만 우리는 모두 이같은 습관을 가지고 있습니다. 제가 아가타 크리스티의 전기에서 읽은 사실인데요, 그는 목욕을 하고 나올 때마다 사과 한 알을 먹었다고 합니다. 도대체 이런 행동에 어떤 의미가 있겠습니까? 이 행동들이 가지는 의미가 있다면 그것은 외양에 불과합니다.<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup> 혹은 의미를 가지지 않는 의미라고 말할 수 있겠습니다. “이 행동의 이면에는 이러한 트라우마가 있다”라든가 “이 행동의 이면에는 이러한 무의식적 동기가 있다”라고 말하는 것은 잘못되었습니다. 아가타 크리스티나가 무의식적으로 본인이 에덴 동산의 이브라고 생각했다는 말입니까? 아니죠. <strong>이러한 텅빈 의미의 외양은 우리 인간이 노골적일 정도로 혼란스러운 삶의 무의미에 대응하는 한 가지 방식에 다름 아닙니다.</strong></p>

<p><strong>둘째로, 저는 인공지능이 결코 진정한 의미에서 욕을 할 수 없다고 생각합니다.</strong> 저에게 있어 욕은 매우 흥미로운 현상입니다. 욕은 단순히 저급한 언어가 아닙니다. <strong>욕은 인간이 언어 안에 존재하기를 원한다는 증거입니다.</strong> 우리의 사고는 언어의 형태로 이루어지지만, 그럼에도 우리는 결코 진정한 의미에서 언어에 거주하지 않습니다. 우리가 욕을 할 때는 단순히 객관적 사건에 대한 불만족을 표출하는 것이 아닙니다. 욕은 그것을 언어로 형성할 수 없는 데에서 오는 분노의 표출입니다. 일례로 십자가에 매달린 예수를 떠올려 보세요. 저는 아무리 예수라고 해도 죽어가면서 욕을 했을 것이라고 생각합니다. 다소 어이없는 생각이긴 하지만, “와 시발…”이라고 중얼거렸을 수도 있지 않을까요? 제 요점은, <strong>언어 안에 완전히 존재할 수 없을 때 느끼는 수치심이야말로 인간다움을 구성하는 본질 중 하나라는 것입니다.</strong></p>

<h2 id="5-수치심의-몰락">5. 수치심의 몰락</h2>

<p>이제 또다른, 어쩌면 놀랍게 들릴 수도 있는 이야기로 마무리를 짓겠습니다. 오늘날 저를 정말로 슬프게 만드는 것은 <strong>뻔뻔함<sub>shamelessness</sub></strong>의 폭증입니다. 10년 전까지만 해도 공적인 장소에서 말하는 것이 불가능했던 말들이 이제는 공공연하게 이루어집니다. 단순히 도널드 트럼프나 보리스 존슨과 같은 뻔한 사례들을 말하려는 것이 아닙니다. 저는 단연코 반유대주의자가 아니지만 — 저는 이스라엘의 입장도 고려하려 합니다 —  최근에 이스라엘에서 일어난 두 가지 일은 저를 충격에 빠뜨렸습니다. 8월에 이스라엘 의회 케네셋에서 논쟁이 있었습니다. 먼저 배경을 말씀드리겠습니다. 예루살렘의 남쪽에 있는 하마스 수용소에서는 간수들이 수감자들을 매우 잔혹하게 다루고 있었습니다. 영상 자료도 유출되었기 때문에 부정할 수 없는 사실이지요. 바늘로 뒤덮인 커다란 철제 막대기를 항문에 쑤셔 넣는 등의 고문으로 인해 많은 수감자가 과다출혈로 사망했습니다. 물론 저는 중립을 지키고 싶기 때문에 하마스 측에서는 무슨 고문을 하고 있을지 누가 아냐는 단서를 남겨두겠습니다. 하지만 저를 정말 슬프게 만드는 것은, 케네셋의 논쟁에서 지배적이었던 의견이 간수들의 잘못을 따지는 것이 아닌, 가혹행위를 한 간수들이 기소되었다는 사실을 치욕으로 여기는 의견이었다는 것입니다. 하마스는 인간도 아니기에 그들에게는 무슨 짓을 해도 괜찮다는 것이었죠. <strong>저는 이런 솔직함보다는 위선이 낫다고 생각합니다.</strong></p>

<p>이제 두 번째 사건을 말해 보겠습니다. 엘리란 미즈라히라는 한 정직하고 올바른 이스라엘 병사가 있었습니다. 가자에서 복무할 당시 그는 끔찍한 명령을 받았습니다. 생사 여부를 따지지 말고 수백 명의 팔레스타인을 트랙터로 깔아뭉개라는 명령이었습니다. 그는 명령을 이행했지만 이후 극심한 혼란에 살다가 이내 자살했습니다. 미즈라히는 윤리적 고결함을 가지고 있었던 것이지요. 그러나 이를 본 이스라엘 방위군의 심리전문가들은 어떻게 병사들을 훈련시켜야 그들이 윤리적 딜레마를 느끼지 않도록 할 수 있을지를 연구하기 시작했습니다. 이것이 제가 말하는 “뻔뻔함”입니다.</p>

<p>그렇다면 이제 정말로 결론을 내리겠습니다. 저에게 무척이나 흥미로운 것은, 저의 스승이라고 부를 수 있을 자크 라캉의 견해입니다. 그는 69-70년에 정신분석학의 다른 측면에 대한 세미나를 진행했었는데요, 그 세미나는 68혁명에 대한 그의 반응이기도 했습니다. 세미나에서 라캉은 학생 저항을 지지하는 대신 이렇게 말했습니다. “당신들에게 결여되어 있는 것은 수치심이다.” 라캉에 따르면, 자유방임적인 오늘날의 사회에서 정신분석학의 궁극적인 목표는 아버지의 억압을 몰아내거나 성적 환상을 실현하는 것이 아닙니다. 오히려 수치의 결여, 그리고 그것이 야기하는 보편적인 도착증<sub>perversion</sub>이 주제입니다.</p>

<p><strong>도착증은 히스테리아에 비해 훨씬 덜 전복적입니다.</strong> 정신분석학에 대해 조금 들은 바가 있다면 아시겠지만, 이 두 증세는 성별과 결부되곤 합니다. 남성 쇼비니즘의 일환입니다만, 요지는 여성은 히스테리적이라 불평을 하면서도 은밀하게 새로운 주인에게 지배받기를 원하고, 남성은 도착적이라서 자신의 꿈을 시행에 옮기기에 급급하다는 것입니다. 하지만 일찍이 프로이트는 알고 있었습니다. 도착증보다 무의식이 더 억압받는 곳은 없으며, 모든 위대한 일은 히스테리아를 통해 발생한다는 사실을 말입니다. <strong>저는 이것이 오늘날의 우리를 위한 교훈이라고 생각합니다.</strong><sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup></p>

<p>제가 젊었을 때 저와 친구들은 촌스러운 좌파였습니다. 우리는 권력자들이 위엄을 지니고 있다고 생각했고, 우리 자신은 온갖 상스러운 손짓과 더러운 말을 주고받았지요. 하지만 이제는 압니다. 권력을 가진 저들이야말로 우리가 상상했던 것 이상으로 상스러운 자들입니다. 지난 선거 때 우리는 완전히 틀렸었습니다. 민주당은 아무것도 배우지 못한 것이죠. 트럼프가 거짓말을 했음이 밝혀졌을 때 민주당은 그의 약점을 잡았다고 생각했어요. 하지만 아니었지요! 오히려 그에게 도움이 됐습니다. 트럼프의 천박함과 거짓말은 그의 정체성을 이룹니다. 사람들은 바로 그 이유에서 그를 사랑했던 것이지요. 따라서 자유방임적인 오늘날의 시대에서 우리가 물어야 하는 질문은 이것입니다. <strong>어떻게 가장 기본적인 수치심의 감각을 되살릴 것인가?</strong></p>

<p>감사합니다.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>동명의 저술에서 후쿠야마는 자유민주주의와 시장자본주의의 혼합 체계가 사회문화적 진화의 궁극적 단계라는 이론을 주장했다. 이후 후쿠야마는 트럼프를 비롯한 미국 내 극단주의 세력의 부흥을 목격하고 자신의 이론을 폐기했다. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>모디 정권은 힌두교의 극단주의화를 촉진시키고 인도의 민주주의를 후퇴시켰다는 비판을 받는다. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>2002년에 부시 미국 대통령이 이라크, 이란, 북한을 “악의 축”으로 부른 것과, 최근에 미국 상원 원내대표가 중국, 러시아, 이란을 “새로운 악의 축”으로 부른 것을 비꼰 것이다. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>팔레스타인 지역의 일부. 팔레스타인 지역은 크게 이스라엘, 가자 지구, 그리고 서안 지구로 구성되어 있다. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>미국의 대안우파 단체. 좌익 단체에 대한 폭력적인 반대 활동으로 알려져 있으며, 2021년에 해당 단체의 회원들이 미국 국회의사당 습격 혐의로 기소되었다. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>더미 텍스트와 같이 통상적으로 어떤 의미를 가지고 있을 것으로 기대되나 — 텍스트, 신호, 행동 등 — 실제로는 의미를 완전히 결여하고 있음을 뜻한다. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:7">
      <p>도착증은 무의식적 긍정성의 발현으로서 자유, 방임, 행동, 능동성 등을 아우르는 개념인 한편, 히스테리아는 무의식적 부정성의 발현으로서 억압, 제약, 금지, 수동성 등을 아우르는 개념이다. 지젝은 본 강연에서 이데올리기와 자본주의가 기형적으로 융합된 “소프트 파시즘”, 인공지능, 그리고 “뻔뻔함의 폭증”을 긍정성의 맹목적인 발현, 즉 도착증이라는 범주 아래에 포섭시키는 것으로 보인다. <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><category term="철학" /><category term="인문학" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[본 글은 2024년 11월 26일에 이루어진 슬라보예 지젝의 옥스포드 강연을 번역한 것이다. 주석은 역자 주이다. 또한 섹션의 구분도 역자가 독자의 편의를 위해 넣은 것이다. 매끄러운 흐름을 위해 내용을 덧대거나 빼는 수준의 의역과 문장 재배치를 한 부분이 있다.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Slavoj Žižek, “Soft Fascism, Artificial Intelligence, and Shamelessness”</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/06/zizek-soft-facism/en" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Slavoj Žižek, “Soft Fascism, Artificial Intelligence, and Shamelessness”" /><published>2025-06-06T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-06-06T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/06/zizek-soft-facism/zizek-soft-facism-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/06/zizek-soft-facism/en"><![CDATA[<p>This post is originally a Korean translation of <a href="https://youtu.be/OSYjmH_WPQQ?si=9Rb5ToZSwf0qg7gx">Slavoj Žižek’s Oxford lecture</a>, so there is no separate English version. However, the following personal observation from the original post is reproduced here.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Psychoanalytically, <strong>Perversion</strong> is a manifestation of subconscious positivity whilst <strong>hysteria</strong> is a manifestation of subconscious negativity. <strong>Positivity</strong> encompasses concepts such as freedom, laissez-faire, liveliness, and activity, while <strong>negativity</strong> encompasses concepts such as repression, constraint, prohibition, and passivity. In this lecture, Žižek appears to subsume “soft fascism” — the pathological fusion of ideology and capitalism, — artificial intelligence, and the rise of Shamelessness under the category of perversion, namely the uncontrolled manifestation of positivity.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><category term="Philosophy" /><category term="Humanities" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is originally a Korean translation of Slavoj Žižek’s Oxford lecture, so there is no separate English version. However, the following personal observation from the original post is reproduced here.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">왜 연속함수의 위상적 정의는 “반대”인가?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/notes-on-continuity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="왜 연속함수의 위상적 정의는 “반대”인가?" /><published>2025-06-02T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-06-02T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/notes-on-continuity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/notes-on-continuity"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p><strong>정의.</strong> 두 위상공간 $X, Y$에 대해 사상 $f: X \to Y$가 <strong>연속</strong>이라는 것은, $V \subseteq Y$가 열린 집합이라면 $f^{-1}[V] \subseteq X$ 또한 열린 집합이라는 것이다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>위상수학을 처음 수강하는 학생들은 위 정의에서 혼란을 겪는다. 직관적으로는 “$U \subseteq X$가 열린 집합이라면 $f[U] \subseteq V$ 또한 열린 집합인 사상”이라는 정의가 자연스러운데, 실제 정의는 이와 반대이기 때문이다. 이러한 직관의 “근거”는 대충 다음과 같을 것이다.</p>

<h3 id="1-엡실론-델타-논법">1. 엡실론-델타 논법</h3>

<p>엡실론-델타 논법에 따르면 $f: X \to Y$가 연속이라는 것은 다음과 같다.</p>

\[\forall \epsilon &gt; 0 \; \exists \delta &gt; 0 : |x - y| &lt; \delta \rightarrow |f(x) - f(y)| &lt; \epsilon\]

<p>위 논리식을 보면 조건부에 $x, y \in X$가 있고 결론부에 $f(x), f(y) \in Y$가 있다. 따라서 연속함수의 위상적 정의 또한 조건부에 $U \subseteq X$가 있고 결론부에 $f[U] \subseteq Y$가 있는 것이 자연스러워 보인다.</p>

<h3 id="2-열린-집합에-대한-직관">2. 열린 집합에 대한 직관</h3>

<p>처음 위상수학을 배울 때, 열린 집합을 “서로 가까운 점들의 모임”으로 생각하곤 한다. 즉, $U$가 열린 집합이라는 것은 $x, y \in U$라면 $x, y$가 “가깝다”는 것이다. 그렇다면 연속함수는 “가까운 점들을 가까운 점들로 사상시키는 함수”이므로, 열린 집합을 열린 집합으로 사상시키는 함수로 정의하는 것이 자연스러워 보인다.</p>

<div style="margin: 2.5em 0;">
</div>

<p><strong>그러나 위 두 “근거”는 매우 잘못되었다.</strong></p>

<div style="margin: 2.5em 0;">
</div>

<h3 id="3-엡실론-델타-논법-근거가-잘못된-이유">3. “엡실론-델타 논법” 근거가 잘못된 이유</h3>

<p>$\rightarrow$만을 기준으로 왼쪽이 조건부, 오른쪽이 결론부로 판단하는 것은 오해를 낳기 딱 좋다. 왜냐하면 여기서는 양화사 또한 고려해야 하기 때문이다. 엡실론-델타 논법의 양화사 부분을 언어적으로 읽으면 “임의의 양수 $\epsilon$에 대해, 어떤 양수 $\delta$가 존재한다” 이다. 다른 말로 하자면, U$\epsilon$이 양수<em>라면</em>, 어떤 양수 $\delta$가 존재한다” 이다.</p>

<p>그리고 $\epsilon$과 유관한 공간은 $X$가 아닌 $Y$이다. <u>즉, $\epsilon$에 대한 서술, 그리고 그에 부수되는 $Y$에 대한 서술이 해당 논리식에서 가장 일차적인 조건부인 것이다.</u> 따라서 위상적 정의에서 $V \subseteq Y$가 조건부에 있는 것은 이상한 일이 아니다.</p>

<h3 id="4-열린-집합에-대한-직관-근거가-잘못된-이유">4. “열린 집합에 대한 직관” 근거가 잘못된 이유</h3>

<p>편의를 위해 $x$와 $y$가 “가깝다”는 것을 $x \sim y$로 표기하자. “열린 집합에 대한 직관” 근거는 다음의 잘못된 직관에 기반한다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>열린 집합에 대한 잘못된 직관.</strong> $x \in U$에 대해, $y \in U$라면 $x \sim y$이다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>이는 다음과 같이 수정해야 한다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>열린 집합에 대한 올바른 직관.</strong> $x \in U$에 대해, $x \sim y$라면 $y \in U$이다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>조금만 생각해 보면 이는 당연하다. 일례로 실수 전체의 집합 $\mathbb{R}$은 열린 집합이다. 그렇다면 임의의 두 실수는 언제나 “가까운” 것인가? 그건 말도 안 된다. 반대 경우를 보면, $\lbrace  0 \rbrace $은 열린 집합이 아니지만 $x, y \in \lbrace  0 \rbrace $일 때 $x = y$이므로 $x$와 $y$는 최대한으로 “가깝다”. 따라서 “잘못된 직관”에 따르면 $\lbrace  0 \rbrace $은 열린 집합이다.</p>

<p>반면 “올바른 직관”으로 보면 $\mathbb{R}$은 열린 집합이고 $\lbrace  0 \rbrace $은 열린 집합이 아닌 것이 분명하게 드러난다. $x \in \mathbb{R}$일 때, $x$와 “가까운” 실수 $y$는 자명하게 $\mathbb{R}$에 포함된다. 한편 $\lbrace  0 \rbrace $은 $0$의 “바로 곁”에 있는 실수들을 포함하고 있지 않으므로 열린 집합이 아니다.</p>

<p>또한 “올바른 직관”으로 보면 연속함수의 위상적 정의가 “뒤집혀야” 하는 이유 또한 분명하다. 먼저 연속함수는 다음과 같이 직관적으로 이해할 수 있다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>연속함수에 대한 올바른 직관.</strong> $x \sim y$라면 $f(x) \sim f(y)$이다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>이제 위의 “직관”과 연속함수의 위상적 정의가 동치임을 보이자.</p>

<h4 id="직관적-정의--위상적-정의">직관적 정의 =&gt; 위상적 정의</h4>

<p>$f$가 “직관적으로 연속”일 때, 열린 집합 $V$에 대해 $U = f^{-1}[V]$가 열린 집합임을 보이자. $x \in U$, $x \sim y$라고 하자. $f$가 연속이므로 $f(x) \sim f(y)$이다. 그리고 $V$가 열린 집합이며 $f(x) \in V$이므로 $f(y) \in V$이다. 따라서 $y \in U$이다. □</p>

<h4 id="위상적-정의--직관적-정의">위상적 정의 =&gt; 직관적 정의</h4>

<p>$f$가 “위상적으로 연속”일 때, $x \sim y$라면 $f(x) \sim f(y)$임을 보이자. $V$가 $f(x)$와 “가까운” 점들만을 포함하는 집합이라고 하자. $V$는 열린 집합이다. 왜냐하면 $z \in V$이고 $z \sim w$일 때, $V$의 정의에 의해 $f(x) \sim z$이므로 ~추이성에 의해~ $f(x) \sim w$, 즉 $w \in V$이기 때문이다. 그리고 $U = f^{-1}[V]$가 $x$를 포함하는 열린 집합이므로 $y \in U$이다. 따라서 $f(y) \in V$, 즉 $f(x) \sim f(y)$이다. ■</p>

<p>물론 위의 논의는 엄밀하게 정의되지 않은 관계 $\sim$을 사용하기 때문에 조금 석연찮기는 하다. 그러나 필자는 $\sim$을 사용하여 열린 집합과 연속성을 이해하는 것이 위상수학을 처음 공부하는 데 있어 유용한 길잡이가 되어준다고 생각한다. 덧붙이자면, 비표준 해석학을 사용하면 $x \sim y$를 $|x - y| = \epsilon$으로 엄밀하게 정의할 수 있다. 이에 관해서는 나중에 기회가 되면 이야기해 보겠다.</p>]]></content><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><category term="논리학" /><category term="위상수학" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[정의. 두 위상공간 $X, Y$에 대해 사상 $f: X \to Y$가 연속이라는 것은, $V \subseteq Y$가 열린 집합이라면 $f^{-1}[V] \subseteq X$ 또한 열린 집합이라는 것이다.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">논리적 외계인은 가능한가? 데카르트, 칸트, 프레게, 그리고 《논리철학논고》</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/wittgenstein-conant" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="논리적 외계인은 가능한가? 데카르트, 칸트, 프레게, 그리고 《논리철학논고》" /><published>2025-06-02T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-06-02T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/wittgenstein-conant</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/wittgenstein-conant"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>이 글은 <a href="/public/Search for Logically Alien Thought.pdf">James Conant, <em>The Search for Logically Alien Thought: Descartes, Kant, Frege, and the</em> Tractatus (1991)</a>를 정리한 것이다. 괄호 안의 내용은 필자가 보충한 것이다 (다시 말해 뇌피셜이다).</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="초록">초록</h2>

<p>서양 철학사의 주요 논의 중 하나는 논리 법칙의 필연성에 관한 것이다. 논리 법칙은 <em>필연적으로</em> 필연적인가, 혹은 <em>우연적으로</em> 필연적인가? 즉, 우리의 논리와는 상이한 논리 법칙을 가지는 세계, 또는 상이한 논리 법칙으로 사고하는 외계인이 가능한가?</p>

<p>이에 대한 철학자들의 답변을 개괄하자면 이렇다.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>아퀴나스는 신 또한 논리 법칙에 의거한다는 점에서 논리 법칙은 필연적으로 필연적이라고 주장했다.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>그러나 데카르트는 신이 진정으로 권능하다면 신은 논리 법칙 또한 바꿀 수 있어야 하며, 이에 따라 논리 법칙은 우연적으로 필연적이라고 주장했다.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>칸트는 논리 법칙을 이성적 사고의 초월적<a href="#sub1" id="sup1"><sup>1</sup></a> 조건으로서 제시함으로써 데카르트의 입장을 극복했다.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>그러나 데카르트의 입장은, 논리 또한 인간 사고의 일부이므로 논리학은 심리학으로 환원된다는 심리학주의<sub>Psychologism</sub>로 살아남었다.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>프레게는 칸트의 입장을 빌려 심리학주의를 신랄하게 공격했으나, 논리 법칙을 초월적 조건으로 보는 동시에 ‘자연의 가장 보편적인 법칙’으로 보는 그의 입장은 내적 긴장을 일으켰다.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>비트겐슈타인은 논리 법칙이 무의미<sub>Sinnlos</sub>하다고 주장했다. 나아가, 프레게의 내적 긴장의 원인은 “논리 법칙은 필연적으로 필연적인가?”라는 질문이 의미를 결여<sub>Unsinn</sub>하기 때문이라고 진단했다.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>이러한 철학사적 흐름을 통해 저자는 비트겐슈타인의 《논고》가 형언할 수 없는 진리에 대한 저술이라는 기존의 해석에 대항하여, 《논고》에는 <em>아무런</em> 철학적 주장도 담겨 있지 않으며 이 사실을 깨닫게 하는 것이 《논고》의 최종 목표라는 “새로운 비트겐슈타인<sub>New Wittgenstein</sub>” 진영의 해석을 옹호한다.</p>

<h2 id="1-아퀴나스와-데카르트-신은-논리에-종속되는가">1. 아퀴나스와 데카르트: 신은 논리에 종속되는가?</h2>

<p>스콜라 철학자들에게 논리 법칙의 필연성 논의는 심각한 문제였다. 신의 권능과 논리 법칙의 필연성은 양립할 수 없는 것으로 여겨졌기 때문이다. 아퀴나스는 이 딜레마를 극복하기 위해 절대적 가능<sub>possible absolutely</sub>과 절대적 불가능<sub>impossible absolutely</sub>이라고 부를 수 있는 구별을 제시했다. 절대적 가능은 지성체가 이해할 수 있는 사태를 의미하고, 절대적 불가능은 이해조차 불가능한 사태를 의미한다. 신의 권능이 뜻하는 바는 절대적으로 가능한 모든 일 — 이를테면 지구를 평평하게 만드는 일 — 은 신에게 가능하다는 것이며, 절대적으로 불가능한 일 — 이를테면 배중률을 위배하는 일 — 은 신의 권능을 논하는 데 무관하다는 것이 아퀴나스의 주장이다.</p>

<p>그러나 데카르트는 아퀴나스의 주장이 신성 모독적이라고 반박한다. 아퀴나스가 절대적 가능과 절대적 불가능을 구별할 때 근거로 삼은 “지성체”는 인간의 지성임이 암시적으로 전제되어 있다. 즉, 아퀴나스는 인간 지성의 한계 — <em>우리는</em> 빨간색인 동시에 빨간색이 아닌 사과를 상상할 수 없다 — 와 신의 권능의 한계 — 따라서 <em>신은</em> 빨간색인 동시에 빨간색이 아닌 사과를 창조할 수 없다 — 를 동일시했다. 데카르트는 이것이 인간 지성의 월권이라고 비판한다. 신은 인간이 이해할 수 없는 방식으로도 행할 수 있다. 그러한 신에게 논리 법칙은 자신의 의지대로 변경이 가능한 우연적 산물이라는 것이 데카르트의 주장이다.</p>

<p>그렇다면 어째서 인간은 논리 법칙을 필연적인 것으로 인식하는가? 데카르트의 답변은, 신이 인간에게 내려 준 이성이 논리 법칙을 필연적인 것으로 이해하도록 설계되었기 때문이라는 것이다. 신이 이 세계를 특정 논리 법칙에 따라 창조했다면, 자애로운 신은 이 세계에 거주할 피조물인 인간에게 해당 논리 법칙을 필연적인 것으로 인식하는 지성을 내려 줄 것이다 (이 대목을 데카르트의 유명한 악마 논변과 대조해 보라). 즉, 데카르트에 따르면 논리 법칙의 표면적 필연성은 (신이 내려 준) 이성의 설계에서 기원한다.<a href="#sub2" id="sup2"><sup>2</sup></a> 데카르트의 주장에서 신학적인 표현들을 신경생리학적 표현들로 대체하기만 하면, 논리 법칙의 표면적 필연성은 뇌의 작동에서 기원한다는 심리학주의의 주장을 얻는다.</p>

<p>그러나 데카르트주의에는 내적 모순이 있어 보인다. 데카르트는 다음의 세 명제를 동시에 주장하고자 한다.</p>

<p>① 인간은 논리적으로 불가능한 사태를 이해할 수 없다.</p>

<p>② 신은 논리적으로 불가능한 사태를 창조할 수 있다.</p>

<p>③ 인간은 ②의 진술을 이해할 수 있으며 나아가 참인 것으로 판단할 수 있다.</p>

<p>여기서 ①과 ③은 상충하는 것으로 보인다. <strong>’논리적으로 불가능한 사태’가 인간에게 이해 불가능한 개념이라면, 신이 그것을 행할 수 있다는 진술 또한 마찬가지로 이해 불가능하지 않겠는가?</strong> 마치 연속체 가설을 이해하지 못하는 사람에게는 ‘연속체 가설이 참인 수학 체계가 가능하다’라는 진술 또한 마찬가지로 이해 불가능하듯이 말이다. 이 문제에 답할 필요를 느낀 데카르트는 이해<sub>comprehend</sub>와 직관<sub>apprehend</sub>의 미묘한 구별을 제시했다. 이해가 무언가를 이성 속에서 완전히 파악하는 일이라면, 직관은 이성이 무언가에 <em>닿는</em> 일이다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>나는 신이 만물의 창조주이며, 불변하는 진리가 있으며, 신이 그것의 창조주임을 안다. 나는 내가 이것을 안다고 말하지, 내가 그것을 인식한다든가, 파악한다고 말하지 않는다. 왜냐하면 비록 우리의 정신은 유한하기에 신을 인식하거나 파악할 수 없지만, 신이 무한하며 전능하다는 사실은 알 수 있기 때문이다. 이것은 우리의 손이 산에 닿을 수는 있지만 우리가 두 팔로 산을 감쌀 수는 없는 것과 마찬가지이다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>따라서 데카르트는 ③을 다음과 같이 수정할 것이다.</p>

<p>③ 인간은 ②의 진술을 <em>직관할</em> 수 있으며 나아가 참인 것으로 판단할 수 있다.</p>

<p>나중에 우리는 이와 같이, 엄밀히 따지자면 무의미하지만 그럼에도 유효한 진리로 통하는 명제가 있음을 단어의 미묘한 구별 — 감히 말하자면 말장난 — 을 통해 정당화하려는 시도를 비트겐슈타인의 ⟪논고⟫에 대한 전통적 해석에서 다시 마주할 것이다.</p>

<h2 id="2-라이프니츠와-칸트-자유-이성-논리">2. 라이프니츠와 칸트: 자유, 이성, 논리</h2>

<p>라이프니츠는 신이 논리 법칙을 임의로 창조했다는 데카르트의 주장에 반대했다. 데카르트를 반박하기 위해 라이프니츠는 “신이 행하기 때문에 선한 일인가, 선한 일이기 때문이 신이 행하는 것인가?” 라는 스콜라 철학의 논쟁을 재등장시킨다. 라이프니츠는 후자를 주장한다. 신은 선한 일이기 <em>때문에</em> 그것을 행한다. 그러나 라이프니츠에 따르면 이는 신이 ‘선’의 개념에 얽매여 있음을 시사하지 않는다. 오히려 이 사실은, 그것이 선하다는 것을 신이 <em>이해한다는</em> 것을 보여준다. 즉 ‘선’의 개념은 신의 의지를 선행하지만, 신의 이성에는 포섭된다.</p>

<p><strong>라이프니츠는 신의 의지에 선행되는 ‘선’의 개념이 신의 자유에 반하기는커녕, 신의 자유가 성립하기 위한 조건임을 강조한다.</strong> 만약 신의 의지에 선행되는 원리가 전무하다면, 신은 특정 행동을 행할 어떠한 근거도 없을 것이다. (그럼에도 신이 무언가를 행한다면, 그것은 무작위적인 선택에 의한 것이라고밖에 볼 수 없다. 그러나 우리는 무작위적인 행동을 두고 자유의지에 의한 선택이라고 말하지 않는다. 이중 슬릿을 통과하는 전자들이 자유의지에 의해 통과할 슬릿을 선택한다고 말하지 않는 것과 같다. 따라서 자유의지는 무작위랑 구별되기 위한 원리를 요구한다.)</p>

<p>마찬가지로 라이프니츠는 논리 법칙이 신의 이성에 포섭되어 있되 신의 의지에 선행하는 원리이자, 신의 자유가 성립하기 위한 조건이라고 주장한다. 이러한 라이프니츠의 철학은 칸트로 계승된다. 데카르트가 논리 법칙을 이성의 산출물로서 보았다면, 칸트는 데카르트의 주장을 이른바 ‘코페르니쿠스적 전회’를 통해 뒤집는다. 칸트에 따르면 논리 법칙은 이성의 산출물이 아니라 이성의 구성 조건이다. 그리고 라이프니츠적인 의미에서, 자유로운 이성이란 논리 법칙을 따르는 이성이다. <strong>논리 법칙을 따르지 않는 이성은 엄격한 의미에서 이성이라 불릴 수 없다.</strong> (이는 마치 체스의 규칙을 따르지 않는 체스는 엄격한 의미에서 체스라 불릴 수 없는 것과 같다.) 이러한 칸트의 논리철학에 대해 퍼트넘은 다음과 같이 적는다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>칸트의 ⟪논리학 강의⟫는 오늘날의 우리가 ‘심리학주의’라고 부르는 입장과 극단적으로 대립하는 입장을 제시하는 선구적인 — 어쩌면 최초의 — 저술이다. […] 나의 관심을 끄는 것은, 비논리적인 생각은 엄격히 말해 애초에 생각이 아니라는 [칸트의] 반복적인 주장이다.</p>

  <p>확실히 논리학에는 아무런 형이상학적 가정이 없다. 규범적 의미에서의 생각, 즉 <em>참 [또는 거짓]으로 판명될 수 있는 판단</em>이 논리를 따른다는 것은 형이상학이 <em>설명해야 할</em> 무언가가 아니기 때문이다. 무언가를 설명한다는 것은 논리를 <em>전제한다</em>. 칸트에게 있어 논리는 모든 이성적 활동에 선행한다.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>특히 칸트는 논리가 심리학과 엄격히 구별되어야 함을 강조한다. 경험적 사실들에 대한 학문으로서 심리학은 이성의 판단 활동을 통해 도달하는 이론인 반면, 논리학은 그러한 이성의 활동이 가능하기 위해 전제되어야 하는 조건이기 때문이다. 따라서 논리학을 심리학으로 환원하려는 시도는 범주론적 오류이다. 여기서 칸트가 논하는 대상은 ‘인간 이성’이 아닌 이성 일반임에 주목하라.</p>

<p>그러나 칸트는 라이프니츠보다 더 엄격한 논리의 경계를 긋는다. 칸트에 따르면 논리학은 오직 문장의 순수 형식에 관한 것이다. (따라서 배중률, 전건 긍정<sub>modus ponens</sub>, 대우법 등은 논리의 범주에 속하지만, 오늘날의 우리가 집합론, 모델론, 양상 논리라고 부르는 것은 속하지 않는다.) <strong>이것이 함의하는 바는, 논리학은 세계에 관해 <em>아무것도</em> 진술하는 바가 없다는 것이다.</strong> (무한 공리 — 적어도 하나의 무한집합이 존재한다는 공리 — 나 공집합 공리 — 공집합이 존재한다는 공리 — 와 같은 존재론적 진술을 포함하는 집합론과 달리, 칸트적인 의미의 논리학은 어떠한 존재론적 진술도 주장하지 않는다.)</p>

<p>이처럼 논리학은 세계의 사태로부터 유리되어 있으므로, <strong>논리학의 필연성을 정당화하려는 시도나, 논리학으로부터 형이상학적 통찰을 얻으려는 시도는 초험적 비판의 대상이 된다.</strong> 그것은 영원의 불멸성에 관한 질문이나 신의 존재에 관한 질문만큼이나 이성의 한계를 벗어난 것이다. 나중에 우리는 비트겐슈타인이 칸트의 주장을 수용하면서도, 그의 주장을 더 원초적인 층위로 옮기는 것을 볼 것이다. 요컨대 칸트가 논리학에 관한 철학적 혼란의 원인을 이성이 그 한계를 넘어섰기 때문으로 진단했다면, 비트겐슈타인은 혼란의 원인이 이성이 부딪히고야 마는 <em>한계가 있다는 환상</em> 때문으로 진단한다.</p>

<h2 id="3-프레게-논리적-외계인-사고실험">3. 프레게: 논리적 외계인 사고실험</h2>

<p>프레게는 칸트와 마찬가지로 논리학이 이성의 산출물이 아니라 이성 — 인간 이성이 아닌 이성 일반 — 의 구성 조건임을 강조한다. 특히 프레게는 판단의 성립 요건으로서 그것이 참과 거짓의 여부를 따질 수 있는 명제일 것을 주장한다. <strong>판단의 성립 요건을 만족하지 않는 생각은 가짜 생각<sub>Scheingedanke</sub>이다.</strong> 이는 프레게가 논리 법칙으로 내세우는 — 칸트의 경우 <em>유일한</em> 논리 법칙으로 내세우는 — 배중률의 요구이다.</p>

<p>이러한 입장을 바탕으로 프레게는 당대에 유행하던 심리학주의를 강하게 비판했다. <strong>프레게는 심리학주의가 원인의 질문과 정당화의 질문을 혼동한다고 비판한다.</strong> 인간의 뇌에 대한 심리적, 생리학적 연구는 우리가 어째서 논리 법칙을 절대적 참으로 <em>받아들이는지에</em> 대한 설명을 제공할 수는 있다. 그러나 그 설명이 어째서 논리 법칙이 <em>절대적으로 참인지를</em> 정당화하는 것은 아니다. 논리 법칙의 정당성은 심리학을 선행한다.</p>

<p>프레게의 논변은 우리가 <em>약한 심리학주의</em> — 논리 법칙의 절대적 지위를 인정하는 한편 논리학을 심리학으로 환원하려는 입장 — 라고 부를 수 있을 입장을 성공적으로 반박한다. 그러나 <em>강한 심리학주의</em> — 논리 법칙의 절대적 지위를 인정하지 않고 오로지 심리학만으로 논리학을 환원하려는 입장 — 를 반박하는 데는 아직 부족하다. 강한 심리학주의자는 논리 법칙의 절대성에 관한 질문을 무의미한 질문, 마치 신의 존재에 관한 질문으로 치부할 수 있다.</p>

<p>프레게의 논리적 외계인 사고실험은 강한 심리학주의의 생각에 근본적인 오류가 있음을 지적한다. 강한 심리학주의에 따르면 우리와 다른 뇌 구조를 가지고 있어, 우리의 논리 법칙과 모순되는 논리 법칙을 절대적인 참으로 생각하는 외계인이 가능하다. 실제로 그러한 외계인이 우리 앞에 나타났다고 생각해 보자. 이 상황에서 프레게는 다음 질문을 던진다. <strong>외계인의 논리 법칙과 우리의 논리 법칙 중 무엇이 올바른가?</strong></p>

<p>이 기점에서 사고실험은 두 가지 갈림길로 나눠진다. 첫째 갈림길은 심리학주의자가 프레게의 질문을 유의미한 질문으로 인정하는 경우이다. 이 경우, 심리학주의자는 외계인의 논리 법칙과 우리의 논리 법칙 <em>둘 다를</em> 선행하여, 둘 중 어떤 법칙이 올바른지를 따질 수 있는 논리 체계가 있음을 인정하게 된다. “외계인과 우리 중 누가 올바른가?”라는 질문은 외계인-심리학에도, 인간-심리학에도 속하는 질문이 아니다. 그것은 심리학을 초월해 있으며, 이 질문의 유의미성에 대한 인정 자체가 심리학을 초월해 있는 논리를 인정하는 것이다. 이 상위 논리에 견주었을 때, 외계인의 논리는 <em>다른</em> 논리가 아니라 <em>틀린</em> 논리임이, 즉 애초에 논리가 아님이 드러난다.</p>

<p>(여기서 혹자는 <em>우리의</em> 논리가 틀린 것일수도 있지 않냐고 물을지 모른다. 그러나 이 경우 외계인 사고실험 자체가, 나아가 우리의 모든 이성이 넌센스의 구렁으로 빠져버린다. 논리에 대한 회의주의는 그러한 회의주의를 품게 만든 논증 또한 비논리적인 것으로 만들어 버림으로써 철학적 탐구의 가능성을 완전히 함몰시킨다. 우리는 우리의 논리를 옳은 것으로 <em>간주할 수밖에</em> 없다. 이것은 후술할 프레게의 내적 긴장의 원인이 된다.)</p>

<p>둘째 갈림길은 심리학주의자가 프레게의 질문마저 무의미한 것으로 치부하는 경우이다. 이 경우 심리학주의자는 어느 누구의 논리 법칙도 절대적으로 올바른 것은 아니라고 주장할 것이다. 외계인의 논리 법칙은 외계인에게 올바르고, 인간의 논리 법칙은 인간에게 올바르며, 그 이상 주장할 것은 없다. 그러나 프레게는 이러한 심리학주의자의 태도가 심리학주의자가 견지하고자 하는 입장 — 즉, 우리와 다른 논리 법칙으로 사고하는 외계인의 존재 가능성 — 을 불가해한 입장으로 만들어버림을 지적한다.</p>

<p><strong>프레게의 지적에서 핵심적인 것은, “A와 B는 논리적으로 다르다”라는 명제가 유의미하기 위해서는 A와 B의 동일성을 판별할 수 있는 논리가 전제되어야 한다는 것이다.</strong> (이해의 편의를 위해 논리학이 아닌 위상수학으로 예를 들어 보자. 우리가 구와 도넛<a href="#sub3" id="sup3"><sup>3</sup></a>이 <em>위상수학적으로 다르다고</em> 말할 수 있는 이유는, 구와 도넛에 대해 공통적으로 유효한 위상수학적 개념 — 이를테면 구멍의 개수<a href="#sub4" id="sup4"><sup>4</sup></a> — 이 존재하여, 구와 토러스가 그 개념에 대해 차이를 보이기 때문이다.)</p>

<p>마찬가지로 우리와 <em>논리적으로 다른</em> 외계인이 존재할 수 있다는 심리학주의자의 주장은 그 자체로 우리의 논리학과 외계인의 논리학의 <em>다름을 성립시키는</em> 배경 논리를 전제하며, 이 경우 우리는 다시 첫째 갈림길로 돌아가게 된다. 한편 심리학주의자가 주장하는 바가 우리와 <em>그저 다른 발화를 하는</em> 외계인의 존재라면, 여기서의 차이는 두 소의 울음소리가 다른 것, 그 이상도 이하도 아니다. 우리와 다른 논리로 사고하는 외계인이 존재한다는 심리학주의의 주장은, 실상 그 외계인은 애초에 <em>사고를 하지 않는다는 것</em> 을 드러낼 뿐이다. (소와 인간은 둘 다 소리를 내지만 오직 후자만이 사고를 한다. 빙고 머신과 계산기는 둘 다 숫자를 출력하지만 오직 후자만이 계산을 한다.)</p>

<h2 id="4-프레게-논리철학의-내적-긴장">4. 프레게 논리철학의 내적 긴장</h2>

<p>지금까지의 논증을 보았을 때 프레게가 내리는 결론은 “논리적 외계인은 존재할 수 없다”인 듯하다. 정말로 이것이 논증의 결론이라면, 우리의 사고는 다음의 과정을 따랐을 것이다.</p>

<ol>
  <li>우리는 논리적 외계인이라는 존재를 상정했다.</li>
  <li>해당 존재가 가질 특징에 대해 고려했다.</li>
  <li>이 특징들이 논리의 특성과 양립할 수 없음을 깨달았다.</li>
  <li>따라서 우리는 논리적 외계인의 가능성을 기각한다.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>그러나 — 적어도 프레게 본인이 제시하는 “판단의 성립 요건”에 따르면 — 여기서 우리가 겪는 것은 생각의 환영이 아닌가?</strong> 프레게의 논증을 면밀하게 들여다 보면, 그가 말하고자 하는 바는 “논리적 외계인은 이러이러한 이유로 존재할 수 없다”가 아니라 “논리적 외계인의 상정 자체가 불가해하다”는 것임을 알 수 있다. 논리적 외계인의 상정은 우리의 사고를 논리의 범위 밖으로 위치시켜버림으로써, 우리의 사고를 사고가 아닌 것으로 만들어버린다. 비유하자면 그것은 트로이 목마인 것이다.</p>

<p>여기서 궁극적으로 드러나는 사실은, 논리적 외계인에 대한 사고실험 자체가 일종의 가짜 생각<sub>Scheingedanke</sub>이라는 것이다. “논리적 외계인은 가능하다”는 심리학주의의 주장은 의미를 결여한 문장이다. 그것은 “참 또는 거짓의 여부를 따질 수 있는 명제일 것”이라는 판단의 성립 요건을 만족하지 않는다. 그리고 이것이 함의하는 바는, “논리적 외계인이 불가능하다”는 <em>우리의 주장</em> 또한 의미를 결여한다는 것이다.<a href="#sub5" id="sup5"><sup>5</sup></a></p>

<p>그러나 어떤 의미에서 “논리적 외계인이 불가능하다”는 문장에는 무언가 참인 진술이 있는 듯하다. 그것은 논리의 본성에 관한 어떤 진리를 드러내고 있지 않은가? 단지 우리 언어의 논리적 구조가 그 진리의 발화를 불가능하게 만드는 것이다. 전통적으로 《논고》는 이러한 맥락에서 해석되었다. 특히 해커<sub>Hacker</sub>, 기치<sub>Geach</sub> 등의 학자는 《논고》가 반구문론적 명제<sub>countersyntactic proposition</sub>를 통해 “엄밀한 의미에서는 말해질 수 없는” 진리를 “드러내 보이는” 저술이라고 해석해 왔다. 여기서 <strong>반구문론적 명제</strong>란, 언어의 자연적 구문론은 따르되 — 이를테면 주어는 서술어를 선행해야 한다 — 어느 시점에서 논리적 구문론을 위배하는 명제이다 — 이를테면 서로 다른 위계에 있는 유형론적 대상들을 같은 술어에 양화시킨다. 예를 들어 대상<sub>object</sub>과 개념<sub>concept</sub>의 구분은 엄격한 논리적 언어에서 표현될 수 있는 것이 아니다. 둘은 유형론적으로 다르기 때문이다. 대상과 개념의 구분은 ‘개념’을 대상화함으로써, 러셀의 역설과 같은 유형의 문제를 발생시킨다. 그럼에도 이 구분은 논리의 중요한 특성을 담지하는 것으로 보인다. 전통적 해석에 따르면 《논고》 또한 이러한 반구문론적 명제들 — 엄밀히 말해 무의미하지만 그럼에도 유의미한 진리를 담지하는 명제들 — 로 구성되어 있으며, “사다리를 걷어차야 한다”는 《논고》의 최종적인 메시지는 그 명제들의 반구문론적 특징을 폭로하는 대목이다.</p>

<p><strong>그러나 논문의 저자는 이러한 전통적 해석을 강하게 비판한다.</strong> 전통적 해석은 데카르트의 ‘이해’와 ‘파악’의 구분과 같은, 말장난에 불과한 허황된 구분들 — “엄밀히 말해 생각”과 “생각”, “그저 무의미”와 “깊은 무의미”, “사실”과 “<em>사실</em>” — 을 통해 《논고》의 내적 긴장을 해소하는 시늉을 했을 뿐, 실질적으로 그 긴장을 해소하는 데는 완전히 실패했다. 전통적 해석은 이들 구분에 완전히 의존하고 있으면서도, 어떻게 논리적 규칙을 위배하는 문장이 “무의미”하지만 “그저 무의미”하지 않을 수 있는지, 어떻게 “생각은 결코 비논리적일 수 없다(§3.03)”는 《논고》의 구절을 인정하면서도 비논리적인 “생각”이 가능한지를 명료하게 해명하지 못한다. 따라서 논문의 저자는 전통적 해석과 단절된 새 해석을 제시한다. 그것은 소위 “새로운 비트겐슈타인”으로 일컬어지는 해석의 일환이다.</p>

<p><em>2편에서 계속</em></p>

<hr />

<p><a href="#sup1" id="sub1">1.</a> <a href="https://namu.wiki/w/한국%20칸트%20학계%20번역어%20논쟁">이런 걸</a> 신경 쓰는 독자라면, 필자는 ‘a priori’를 ‘선험적’, ‘transzendent’를 ‘초험적’, ‘transzendental’을 ‘초월적’이라고 번역한 아카넷 칸트전집의 용어를 사용한다.</p>

<p><a href="#sup2" id="sub2">2.</a> 데카르트의 주장은 묘하게 칸트적이다. 실제로 윌슨<sub>Margaret Wilson</sub>은 논리 법칙에 대한 데카르트의 입장을 칸트의 초월철학과 현대의 자연주의의 시조로 평가한다. 그러나 이후 드러나듯이, 논리 법칙에 대한 데카르트의 입장과 칸트의 입장에는 간과할 수 없는 간극이 있다.</p>

<p><a href="#sup3" id="sub3">3.</a> 엄밀히는 토러스. 토러스는 도넛의 겉면이다.</p>

<p><a href="#sup4" id="sub4">4.</a> 엄밀히는 1차 호몰로지 군. 구의 경우 이는 $\mathbb{Z}$이고 토러스의 경우 $\mathbb{Z} \times \mathbb{Z}$이다.</p>

<p><a href="#sup5" id="sub5">5.</a> 원 논문에서는 다음과 같이 말한다.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If we take the sentences “illogical thought is impossible” or “we cannot think illogically” to indeed present us with <em>thoughts</em> (with senses which we can affirm the truth of), then we concede what a moment ago we wished to deny (namely, that the negation of these sentences preseunt us with a genuine content, one which is able to stand up to the demand for judgment). But if we conclude that these words (which we want to utter in response to the psychologicstic logician) do not express a thought with a sense, then aren’t <em>we</em>, if we judge psychologism to be false, equally victims of an illusion of judgment? This is the problem at the heart of the onion.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>즉, 논문의 저자는 다음의 문장이 실제로는 생각<sub>thought</sub>이 아님을 지적하고 있다.</p>

<ol>
  <li>비논리적인 생각은 불가능하다.</li>
</ol>

<p>이것을 논리식으로 옮기면 다음과 같다.</p>

<ol start="2">
  <li>$\not\exists x (I(x) \land T(x))$</li>
</ol>

<p>이제 이를 다음의 문장과 대조해 보자.</p>

<ol start="3">
  <li>초록색 생각은 불가능하다.</li>
  <li>$\not\exists x (G(x) \land T(x))$</li>
</ol>

<p>(1)과 (3)은 형태론적으로 같은 문장이다. 그런데 (3)은 의미가 <i>있는</i> 문장으로 보인다. 그 의미란, 이 세상에 초록색이면서 생각이기도 한 대상이 없다는 것이다. 실증주의자라면 (3)이 반증 가능성 원리 또한 통과한다고 말할지 모른다. 요컨대 세상의 모든 초록색 대상 중 생각에 해당하는 것이 발견되면 (3)은 기각된다는 것이다. 또한 (3)의 논리적 표현인 (4)는 어떠한 논리적 규칙도 위배하지 않는 것으로 보인다.</p>

<p>그러나 필자가 보기에 (1)과 (2)가 유의미하다는 생각은, 프레게의 표현을 빌리자면 “생각의 환영”에 사로잡힌 것이다. 이 입장을 논증하는 가장 효율적인 방법은 (4)에서 등장하는 무제약적 양화사 $\exists x$의 부당함을 피력하는 것이다. $x$의 범위는 어디까지인가? 내 앞의 사과가 $x$에 양화될 수 있다면, 사과의 꼭지 또한 $x$에 양화될 수 있는가? 무언가가 — 이를테면 나뭇잎 — 대상의 부분이 아니라 독립적인 대상으로 고려되어야 하는 기준은 무엇인가? 반대로, 무언가가 — 이를테면 나무 — 대상의 단순한 조합이 아니라 독립적인 대상으로 고려되어야 하는 기준은 무엇인가? 수학적 플라톤주의를 인정하여 ‘자연수 집합’ 또한 양화의 대상으로 고려해야 하는가? ‘신’ 또한 양화의 대상인가?</p>

<p>이렇듯 무제약적 양화사는 사용자로 하여금 강한 존재론적 개입을 요구한다. 이런 난처한 상황을 피하는 한 가지 방법은 무제약적 존재 양화를 사용하는 대신 $x$를 $T$의 진리집합으로 양화시키는 것이다. 요컨대 (4)를 (5)와 같이 수정하는 것이다.</p>

<ol start="5">
  <li>$\exists x \in \mathrm{Th}\; G(x)$</li>
</ol>

<p>여기서 $\mathrm{Th}$는 생각들의 집합이다. 그런데 이렇게 적고 나면, (5)는 적형식이 <strong>아니게 된다</strong>. 문제는 $G$를 정의하는 데 있다. 우리가 무제약적 양화를 피하고자 한다면, $G$의 정의역을 정의하는 데 있어서도 무제약적 양화를 피해야 한다. 즉 a는 가능하지만 b는 불가능하다.</p>

<p>    a) G: 물리적 대상 → {T, F} (O)</p>

<p>    b) G: 모든 대상 → {T, F} (X)</p>

<p>따라서 (5)는 적형식이 아니다. (5)는 정의역에 속하지 않는 대상을 술어에 적용하고 있으므로 논리적 규칙을 위배한 것이다. 다시 말해, (5)는 의미를 결여한 문장이다.</p>

<p>이는 다음의 수학적 예시를 통해 이해할 수 있다. 독자 분은 $0 &lt; i$가 올바르지 않은 부등식임을 배웠을 것이다. 왜냐하면 해당 맥락에서 $&lt;$는 실수 위에서만 정의되기 관계이기 때문이다. 그리고 $&lt;$가 실수 위에서만 정의 가능한 이유는 실수, 허수, 그리고 $&lt;$가 요구하는 논리적 규칙들과 연관한다. $&lt;$의 규칙에 따르면, 양변에 0보다 큰 수를 곱하면 부등호의 방향이 유지되고, 0보다 작은 수를 곱하면 부등호의 방향이 뒤집힌다. 그런데 만약 $0 &lt; i$라면 $0 = 0 \cdot i &lt; i \cdot i = -1$이 되어 모순이고, $i &lt; 0$이라면 $-1 = i \cdot i &gt; 0 \cdot i = 0$이 되어 모순이다. 따라서 $0 &lt; i$는 의미를 결여한 부등식이다. 이는 $0 &lt; i$가 <strong>거짓</strong>임을 의미하지 않는다. $0 &lt; i$가 거짓이라면 $0 &gt; i$가 참이어야 하기 때문이다.</p>

<p>참고: <a href="https://forum.owlofsogang.com/t/topic/6465">https://forum.owlofsogang.com/t/topic/6465</a></p>]]></content><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><category term="철학" /><category term="논리학" /><category term="언어철학" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[이 글은 James Conant, The Search for Logically Alien Thought: Descartes, Kant, Frege, and the Tractatus (1991)를 정리한 것이다. 괄호 안의 내용은 필자가 보충한 것이다 (다시 말해 뇌피셜이다).]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Are Logically Alien Beings Possible? Descartes, Kant, Frege, and the Tractus</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/wittgenstein-conant/en" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are Logically Alien Beings Possible? Descartes, Kant, Frege, and the Tractus" /><published>2025-06-02T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-06-02T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/wittgenstein-conant/wittgenstein-conant-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/wittgenstein-conant/en"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>This post was machine translated and has not yet been proofread. It may contain minor errors or unnatural expressions. Proofreading will be done in the near future.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>This article is a summary of <a href="/public/Search for Logically Alien Thought.pdf">James Conant, <em>The Search for Logically Alien Thought: Descartes, Kant, Frege, and the</em> Tractatus (1991)</a>. THe post includes the author’s supplementary remarks.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2>

<p>One of the principal debates in the history of Western philosophy concerns the necessity of logical laws. Are logical laws <em>necessarily</em> necessary, or are they <em>contingently</em> necessary? That is, is a world with logical laws different from ours, or aliens who think according to different logical laws, possible?</p>

<p>The responses of philosophers to this question may be summarised as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Aquinas argued that logical laws are necessarily necessary, on the grounds that even God operates according to logical laws.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>However, Descartes contended that if God is truly omnipotent, He must be able to alter logical laws as well, and accordingly maintained that logical laws are contingently necessary.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Kant overcame Descartes’s position by presenting logical laws as transcendental<a href="#sub1" id="sup1"><sup>1</sup></a> conditions of rational thought.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>However, Descartes’s position survived as psychologism<sub>Psychologism</sub>, which held that since logic is also part of human thought, logic should be reduced to psychology.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Frege, borrowing from Kant’s position, launched a fierce attack on psychologism, but his stance of viewing logical laws simultaneously as transcendental conditions and as ‘the most universal laws of nature’ created internal tension.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Wittgenstein argued that logical laws are senseless<sub>Sinnlos</sub>. Furthermore, he diagnosed that the cause of Frege’s internal tension was that the question “Are logical laws necessarily necessary?” lacks sense<sub>Unsinn</sub>.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Through this philosophical-historical trajectory, the author defends the interpretation of the “New Wittgenstein<sub>New Wittgenstein</sub>” school, which contends against the traditional interpretation that the <em>Tractus</em> is a work about ineffable truths, arguing instead that the <em>Tractus</em> contains <em>no</em> philosophical claims whatsoever, and that making one realise this fact is the ultimate goal of the <em>Tractus</em>.</p>

<h2 id="1-aquinas-and-descartes-is-god-subject-to-logic">1. Aquinas and Descartes: Is God Subject to Logic?</h2>

<p>For scholastic philosophers, the debate over the necessity of logical laws was a serious problem, as God’s omnipotence and the necessity of logical laws appeared incompatible. To overcome this dilemma, Aquinas presented a distinction that might be called absolute possibility<sub>possible absolutely</sub> and absolute impossibility<sub>impossible absolutely</sub>. Absolute possibility refers to states of affairs that an intellect can understand, whilst absolute impossibility refers to states of affairs that are incomprehensible. Aquinas’s claim is that God’s omnipotence means that everything absolutely possible—such as making the Earth flat—is possible for God, whilst absolutely impossible things—such as violating the law of excluded middle—are irrelevant to discussions of God’s omnipotence.</p>

<p>However, Descartes objects that Aquinas’s claim is blasphemous. When Aquinas distinguishes between absolute possibility and absolute impossibility, the “intellect” upon which he bases this distinction is implicitly presupposed to be human intellect. That is, Aquinas conflates the limitations of human intellect—<em>we</em> cannot imagine an apple that is simultaneously red and not red—with the limitations of God’s omnipotence—therefore <em>God</em> cannot create an apple that is simultaneously red and not red. Descartes criticises this as an overreach of human intellect. God can act in ways that humans cannot understand. For such a God, logical laws are contingent products that can be altered at will, according to Descartes.</p>

<p>Then why do humans perceive logical laws as necessary? Descartes’s answer is that the reason God gave to humans is designed to understand logical laws as necessary. If God created this world according to specific logical laws, a benevolent God would give humans dwelling in this world an intellect that perceives those logical laws as necessary (contrast this passage with Descartes’s famous evil demon argument). That is, according to Descartes, the apparent necessity of logical laws originates in the design of reason (given by God).<a href="#sub2" id="sup2"><sup>2</sup></a> If we merely replace theological expressions with neurophysiological ones in Descartes’s claim, we obtain the psychologist claim that the apparent necessity of logical laws originates in the workings of the brain.</p>

<p>However, Cartesianism appears to contain an internal contradiction. Descartes wishes to assert the following three propositions simultaneously:</p>

<p>① Humans cannot understand logically impossible states of affairs.</p>

<p>② God can create logically impossible states of affairs.</p>

<p>③ Humans can understand the statement in ② and furthermore judge it to be true.</p>

<p>Here ① and ③ seem to conflict. <strong>If ‘logically impossible states of affairs’ is a concept incomprehensible to humans, would not the statement that God can accomplish such things be equally incomprehensible?</strong> Just as the statement ‘a mathematical system in which the continuum hypothesis is true is possible’ is equally incomprehensible to someone who does not understand the continuum hypothesis. Feeling the need to address this problem, Descartes presented a subtle distinction between comprehension<sub>comprehend</sub> and apprehension<sub>apprehend</sub>. If comprehension is the complete grasping of something within reason, apprehension is reason’s <em>touching</em> of something.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I know that God is the creator of all things, that there are immutable truths, and that God is their creator. I say that I know this, not that I perceive or grasp it. For although our mind is finite and thus cannot perceive or grasp God, we can know that God is infinite and omnipotent. This is like how our hands can touch a mountain but we cannot embrace a mountain with our two arms.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Therefore, Descartes would modify ③ as follows:</p>

<p>③ Humans can <em>apprehend</em> the statement in ② and furthermore judge it to be true.</p>

<p>Later, we shall encounter once again in the traditional interpretation of Wittgenstein’s <em>Tractus</em> such attempts to justify through subtle distinctions of words—dare one say, wordplay—the existence of propositions that are, strictly speaking, senseless but nevertheless pass for valid truths.</p>

<h2 id="2-leibniz-and-kant-freedom-reason-logic">2. Leibniz and Kant: Freedom, Reason, Logic</h2>

<p>Leibniz opposed Descartes’s claim that God arbitrarily created logical laws. To refute Descartes, Leibniz resurrected the scholastic philosophical debate: “Is something good because God does it, or does God do it because it is good?” Leibniz argues for the latter. God acts <em>because</em> something is good. However, according to Leibniz, this does not suggest that God is bound by the concept of ‘good’. Rather, this fact shows that God <em>understands</em> that something is good. That is, the concept of ‘good’ precedes God’s will but is subsumed under God’s reason.</p>

<p><strong>Leibniz emphasises that the concept of ‘good’ that precedes God’s will, far from being contrary to God’s freedom, is a condition for God’s freedom to be established.</strong> If there were no principles preceding God’s will, God would have no grounds for performing any particular action. (If God nonetheless acted, it could only be seen as random choice. However, we do not call random behaviour a choice by free will. Just as we do not say that electrons passing through a double slit choose which slit to pass through by free will. Therefore, free will requires principles to distinguish it from randomness.)</p>

<p>Similarly, Leibniz argues that logical laws are principles subsumed under God’s reason whilst preceding God’s will, and are conditions for God’s freedom to be established. This Leibnizian philosophy is inherited by Kant. Where Descartes viewed logical laws as products of reason, Kant reverses Descartes’s claim through the so-called ‘Copernican revolution’. According to Kant, logical laws are not products of reason but constitutive conditions of reason. And in a Leibnizian sense, free reason is reason that follows logical laws. <strong>Reason that does not follow logical laws cannot, in the strict sense, be called reason.</strong> (This is like how chess that does not follow the rules of chess cannot, in the strict sense, be called chess.) Putnam writes the following about Kant’s philosophy of logic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Kant’s <em>Lectures on Logic</em> presents a position that stands in extreme opposition to what we today call ‘psychologism’—a pioneering, perhaps the first, work. […] What interests me is [Kant’s] repeated assertion that illogical thought is not, strictly speaking, thought at all.</p>

  <p>Certainly logic contains no metaphysical assumptions. That thought in the normative sense, i.e., <em>judgement that can be proven true [or false]</em>, follows logic is not something that metaphysics must <em>explain</em>. To explain something <em>presupposes</em> logic. For Kant, logic precedes all rational activity.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Kant particularly emphasises that logic must be strictly distinguished from psychology. As a science of empirical facts, psychology is a theory reached through rational judgement activity, whilst logic is a condition that must be presupposed for such rational activity to be possible. Therefore, attempts to reduce logic to psychology constitute a categorical error. Note here that the object of Kant’s discussion is not ‘human reason’ but reason in general.</p>

<p>However, Kant draws stricter boundaries of logic than Leibniz. According to Kant, logic concerns only the pure form of sentences. (Therefore, the law of excluded middle, modus ponens<sub>modus ponens</sub>, contraposition, etc., belong to the category of logic, but what we today call set theory, model theory, and modal logic do not.) <strong>What this implies is that logic states <em>nothing</em> about the world.</strong> (Unlike set theory, which includes ontological statements such as the axiom of infinity—the axiom that at least one infinite set exists—or the empty set axiom—the axiom that the empty set exists—Kantian logic makes no ontological claims.)</p>

<p>Since logic is thus divorced from worldly affairs, <strong>attempts to justify the necessity of logic or to gain metaphysical insights from logic become subjects of transcendental critique.</strong> This is as much beyond the limits of reason as questions about the immortality of eternity or the existence of God. Later we shall see Wittgenstein accepting Kant’s claim whilst transposing it to a more fundamental level. In short, where Kant diagnosed the cause of philosophical confusion about logic as reason overstepping its limits, Wittgenstein diagnoses the cause of confusion as the <em>illusion that there are limits</em> that reason inevitably encounters.</p>

<h2 id="3-frege-the-logically-alien-thought-experiment">3. Frege: The Logically Alien Thought Experiment</h2>

<p>Like Kant, Frege emphasises that logic is not a product of reason but a constitutive condition of reason—not human reason but reason in general. Frege particularly argues that for judgement to be established, it must be a proposition whose truth or falsity can be assessed. <strong>Thoughts that do not satisfy the conditions for judgement are pseudo-thoughts<sub>Scheingedanke</sub>.</strong> This is a requirement of the law of excluded middle, which Frege—and Kant as the <em>sole</em> logical law—puts forward as a logical law.</p>

<p>Based on this position, Frege strongly criticised the psychologism that was fashionable in his time. <strong>Frege criticises psychologism for confusing questions of causation with questions of justification.</strong> Psychological and physiological research on the human brain can provide explanations for why we <em>accept</em> logical laws as absolutely true. However, such explanations do not justify why logical laws <em>are absolutely true</em>. The validity of logical laws precedes psychology.</p>

<p>Frege’s argument successfully refutes what we might call <em>weak psychologism</em>—the position that recognises the absolute status of logical laws whilst attempting to reduce logic to psychology. However, it is still insufficient to refute <em>strong psychologism</em>—the position that does not recognise the absolute status of logical laws and attempts to reduce logic solely to psychology. Strong psychologists can dismiss questions about the absoluteness of logical laws as meaningless questions, like questions about the existence of God.</p>

<p>Frege’s logically alien thought experiment points out that there is a fundamental error in strong psychologism’s thinking. According to strong psychologism, aliens with different brain structures who think of logical laws contradicting ours as absolutely true are possible. Let us suppose that such an alien actually appeared before us. In this situation, Frege poses the following question: <strong>Which is correct: the alien’s logical laws or our logical laws?</strong></p>

<p>At this point, the thought experiment divides into two paths. The first path is when the psychologist acknowledges Frege’s question as meaningful. In this case, the psychologist comes to acknowledge that there exists a logical system that precedes <em>both</em> the alien’s logical laws and our logical laws, and can judge which of the two laws is correct. The question “Which is correct, the alien or us?” belongs neither to alien-psychology nor to human-psychology. It transcends psychology, and acknowledging the meaningfulness of this question itself acknowledges logic that transcends psychology. Compared to this higher logic, the alien’s logic is revealed to be not <em>different</em> logic but <em>wrong</em> logic—that is, not logic at all.</p>

<p>(Here someone might ask whether <em>our</em> logic might be wrong. However, in this case, the alien thought experiment itself, and indeed all our reason, falls into a pit of nonsense. Scepticism about logic makes the arguments that led to such scepticism illogical, thereby completely destroying the possibility of philosophical enquiry. We have <em>no choice but to regard</em> our logic as correct. This becomes the cause of Frege’s internal tension, to be discussed below.)</p>

<p>The second path is when the psychologist dismisses even Frege’s question as meaningless. In this case, the psychologist would claim that no one’s logical laws are absolutely correct. The alien’s logical laws are correct for the alien, human logical laws are correct for humans, and there is nothing more to claim. However, Frege points out that such a psychologist’s attitude makes the position the psychologist wishes to maintain—namely, the possibility of aliens who think according to logical laws different from ours—incomprehensible.</p>

<p><strong>What is crucial in Frege’s point is that for the proposition “A and B are logically different” to be meaningful, there must be presupposed a logic that can determine the identity of A and B.</strong> (For ease of understanding, let us use an example from topology rather than logic. The reason we can say that a sphere and a torus<a href="#sub3" id="sup3"><sup>3</sup></a> are <em>topologically different</em> is that there exist topological concepts—such as the number of holes<a href="#sub4" id="sup4"><sup>4</sup></a>—that are commonly valid for both spheres and tori, and spheres and tori show differences with respect to those concepts.)</p>

<p>Similarly, the psychologist’s claim that aliens who are <em>logically different</em> from us can exist presupposes by itself a background logic that <em>establishes the difference</em> between our logic and the alien’s logic, and in this case we return to the first path. On the other hand, if what the psychologist claims is the existence of aliens who merely <em>make different utterances</em> from us, the difference here is nothing more or less than the difference between the sounds of two cows. The psychologist’s claim that aliens who think according to different logic from ours exist merely reveals that such aliens do not <em>think</em> in the first place. (Cows and humans both make sounds, but only the latter thinks. Bingo machines and calculators both output numbers, but only the latter calculates.)</p>

<h2 id="4-internal-tension-in-freges-philosophy-of-logic">4. Internal Tension in Frege’s Philosophy of Logic</h2>

<p>From the arguments thus far, Frege’s conclusion appears to be “logically alien beings cannot exist”. If this were truly the conclusion of the argument, our thinking would have followed this process:</p>

<ol>
  <li>We posited the existence of logically alien beings.</li>
  <li>We considered the characteristics such beings would have.</li>
  <li>We realised that these characteristics are incompatible with the nature of logic.</li>
  <li>Therefore, we reject the possibility of logically alien beings.</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>However—at least according to the “conditions for judgement” that Frege himself presents—is what we experience here not an illusion of thought?</strong> If we examine Frege’s argument closely, we can see that what he means to say is not “logically alien beings cannot exist for such and such reasons” but “the very positing of logically alien beings is incomprehensible”. The positing of logically alien beings makes our thinking non-thinking by placing our thought outside the scope of logic. Metaphorically speaking, it is a Trojan horse.</p>

<p>What is ultimately revealed here is that the thought experiment about logically alien beings is itself a kind of pseudo-thought<sub>Scheingedanke</sub>. The psychologist’s claim that “logically alien beings are possible” is a sentence that lacks sense. It does not satisfy the condition for judgement that it should be “a proposition whose truth or falsity can be assessed”. And what this implies is that <em>our claim</em> that “logically alien beings are impossible” also lacks sense.<a href="#sub5" id="sup5"><sup>5</sup></a></p>

<p>However, in some sense, the sentence “logically alien beings are impossible” seems to contain something that is a true statement. Does it not reveal some truth about the nature of logic? It is merely that the logical structure of our language makes the utterance of that truth impossible. The <em>Tractus</em> has traditionally been interpreted in this context. Scholars such as Hacker<sub>Hacker</sub> and Geach<sub>Geach</sub> have interpreted the <em>Tractus</em> as a work that “shows” truths that “cannot be said in the strict sense” through counter-syntactic propositions<sub>countersyntactic proposition</sub>. Here, <strong>counter-syntactic propositions</strong> are propositions that follow the natural syntax of language—for instance, the subject must precede the predicate—but at some point violate logical syntax—for instance, quantifying over type-theoretic objects at different levels with the same predicate. For example, the distinction between object<sub>object</sub> and concept<sub>concept</sub> cannot be expressed in strict logical language because they are type-theoretically different. The distinction between object and concept generates problems of the same type as Russell’s paradox by objectifying ‘concept’. Nevertheless, this distinction seems to bear important characteristics of logic. According to traditional interpretation, the <em>Tractus</em> is also composed of such counter-syntactic propositions—propositions that are strictly speaking senseless but nevertheless bear meaningful truths—and the final message of the <em>Tractus</em> to “throw away the ladder” is the passage that exposes the counter-syntactic characteristics of those propositions.</p>

<p><strong>However, the author of the paper strongly criticises such traditional interpretation.</strong> Traditional interpretation has merely pretended to resolve the internal tension of the <em>Tractus</em> through spurious distinctions—”strictly speaking thought” and “thought”, “merely senseless” and “deeply senseless”, “fact” and “<em>fact</em>“—that are no more than wordplay, like Descartes’s distinction between ‘understanding’ and ‘grasping’, but has completely failed to actually resolve that tension. Traditional interpretation is completely dependent on these distinctions whilst failing to clearly explain how sentences that violate logical rules can be “senseless” but not “merely senseless”, how “thought can never be illogical (§3.03)” can be acknowledged whilst illogical “thought” remains possible. Therefore, the author presents a new interpretation that breaks with traditional interpretation. This is part of the interpretation called the “New Wittgenstein”.</p>

<p><em>Continued in Part 2</em></p>

<hr />

<p><a href="#sup1" id="sub1">1.</a> Note that in Kantian philosophy, ‘transcendent’ means “beyond the limits of experience,” while ‘transcendental’ means “related to the preconditions of rational judgment.”</p>

<p><a href="#sup2" id="sub2">2.</a> Descartes’s claim is strangely Kantian. Indeed, Margaret Wilson evaluates Descartes’s position on logical laws as the progenitor of Kant’s transcendental philosophy and modern naturalism. However, as will become apparent later, there is an unbridgeable gap between Descartes’s position on logical laws and Kant’s position.</p>

<p><a href="#sup3" id="sub3">3.</a> Strictly speaking, a torus. A torus is the surface of a doughnut.</p>

<p><a href="#sup4" id="sub4">4.</a> Strictly speaking, the first homology group. For a sphere this is $\mathbb{Z}$ and for a torus this is $\mathbb{Z} \times \mathbb{Z}$.</p>

<p><a href="#sup5" id="sub5">5.</a> The original paper states:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If we take the sentences “illogical thought is impossible” or “we cannot think illogically” to indeed present us with <em>thoughts</em> (with senses which we can affirm the truth of), then we concede what a moment ago we wished to deny (namely, that the negation of these sentences present us with a genuine content, one which is able to stand up to the demand for judgment). But if we conclude that these words (which we want to utter in response to the psychologistic logician) do not express a thought with a sense, then aren’t <em>we</em>, if we judge psychologism to be false, equally victims of an illusion of judgment? This is the problem at the heart of the onion.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That is, the author of the paper is pointing out that the following sentence is not actually a thought:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Illogical thought is impossible.</li>
</ol>

<p>Translating this into logical notation:</p>

<ol start="2">
  <li>$\not\exists x (I(x) \land T(x))$</li>
</ol>

<p>Now contrast this with the following sentence:</p>

<ol start="3">
  <li>Green thoughts are impossible.</li>
  <li>$\not\exists x (G(x) \land T(x))$</li>
</ol>

<p>(1) and (3) are morphologically identical sentences. Yet (3) appears to be a sentence with <em>meaning</em>. That meaning is that there exist no objects in this world that are both green and thoughts. An empiricist might say that (3) also passes the falsifiability principle. In short, if any green object amongst all green objects in the world is discovered to correspond to a thought, then (3) is rejected. Moreover, (4), the logical expression of (3), appears to violate no logical rules.</p>

<p>However, in my view, the idea that (1) and (2) are meaningful is, to borrow Frege’s expression, captivated by an “illusion of thought”. The most efficient way to argue this position is to emphasise the impropriety of the unrestricted quantifier $\exists x$ appearing in (4). What is the range of $x$? If the apple in front of me can be quantified by $x$, can the stem of the apple also be quantified by $x$? What is the criterion by which something—such as a leaf—should be considered an independent object rather than part of an object? Conversely, what is the criterion by which something—such as a tree—should be considered an independent object rather than a simple combination of objects? Should we acknowledge mathematical Platonism and consider ‘the set of natural numbers’ also as an object of quantification? Is ‘God’ also an object of quantification?</p>

<p>Thus unrestricted quantifiers require users to make strong ontological commitments. One way to avoid this awkward situation is to quantify $x$ to the truth set of $T$ instead of using unrestricted existential quantification. In short, modifying (4) as (5):</p>

<ol start="5">
  <li>$\exists x \in \mathrm{Th}\; G(x)$</li>
</ol>

<p>Here $\mathrm{Th}$ is the set of thoughts. But having written this, (5) becomes <strong>ill-formed</strong>. The problem lies in defining $G$. If we wish to avoid unrestricted quantification, we must also avoid unrestricted quantification in defining the domain of $G$. That is, a) is possible but b) is not:</p>

<p>    a) G: physical objects → {T, F} (O)</p>

<p>    b) G: all objects → {T, F} (X)</p>

<p>Therefore (5) is ill-formed. (5) violates logical rules by applying a predicate to an object that does not belong to its domain. In other words, (5) is a sentence that lacks sense.</p>

<p>This can be understood through the following mathematical example. You will have learnt that $0 &lt; i$ is an incorrect inequality because in that context $&lt;$ is a relation defined only over real numbers. And the reason $&lt;$ can only be defined over real numbers relates to real numbers, imaginary numbers, and the logical rules required by $&lt;$. According to the rules of $&lt;$, multiplying both sides by a number greater than 0 maintains the direction of the inequality, whilst multiplying by a number less than 0 reverses the direction of the inequality. But if $0 &lt; i$, then $0 = 0 \cdot i &lt; i \cdot i = -1$, which is contradictory, and if $i &lt; 0$, then $-1 = i \cdot i &gt; 0 \cdot i = 0$, which is contradictory. Therefore $0 &lt; i$ is an inequality that lacks sense. This does not mean that $0 &lt; i$ is <strong>false</strong>, because if $0 &lt; i$ were false, then $0 &gt; i$ would have to be true.</p>

<p>See also the discussion in: <a href="https://forum.owlofsogang.com/t/topic/6465">https://forum.owlofsogang.com/t/topic/6465</a></p>]]></content><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><category term="Philosophy" /><category term="Logic" /><category term="Philosophy of Language" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post was machine translated and has not yet been proofread. It may contain minor errors or unnatural expressions. Proofreading will be done in the near future.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Why is Continuity in Topology defined ‘Backwards’?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/notes-on-continuity/en" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why is Continuity in Topology defined ‘Backwards’?" /><published>2025-06-02T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2025-06-02T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/notes-on-continuity/notes-on-continuity-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/02/notes-on-continuity/en"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Definition.</strong> A mapping $f: X \to Y$ is said to be <strong>continuous</strong> if for any open set $V \subseteq Y$, the preimage $f^{-1}[V] \subseteq X$ is also an open set.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Students learning topology for the first time often experience confusion with this definition. Intuitively, it seems more natural to define continuity as “if $U \subseteq X$ is open, then $f[U] \subseteq V$ is also open,” but the actual definition is the inverse. The reasoning behind this intuition might roughly be as follows.</p>

<h3 id="1-epsilon-delta-definition">1. Epsilon-Delta Definition</h3>

<p>According to the epsilon-delta definition, a function $f: X \to Y$ is continuous if the following holds:</p>

\[\forall \epsilon &gt; 0 \; \exists \delta &gt; 0 : |x - y| &lt; \delta \rightarrow |f(x) - f(y)| &lt; \epsilon\]

<p>Here the antecedent contains $x, y \in X$, and the consequent contains $f(x), f(y) \in Y$. Therefore, it seems natural for the topological definition of continuity to also have $U \subseteq X$ in the antecedent and $f[U] \subseteq Y$ in the consequent.</p>

<h3 id="2-intuition-about-open-sets">2. Intuition about Open Sets</h3>

<p>When first learning topology, one often thinks of an open set as a “collection of points that are close to each other.” That is, if $U$ is an open set, then $x, y \in U$ implies that $x$ and $y$ are “close.” Thus, if continuous function are those that map “close points” to “close points,” it seems natural to require that they map open sets to open sets.</p>

<div style="margin: 2.5em 0;">
</div>

<p><strong>However, both of these reasonings are fundamentally flawed.</strong></p>

<div style="margin: 2.5em 0;">
</div>

<h3 id="3-why-the-reasoning-behind-epsilon-delta-definition-is-incorrect">3. Why the Reasoning behind “Epsilon-Delta Definition” is Incorrect</h3>

<p>Judging the antecedent and consequent based solely on $\rightarrow$ can easily lead to misunderstandings. One must also consider the quantifiers. The quantifiers of the epsilon-delta definition can be read linguistically as “for any positive $\epsilon$, there exists some positive $\delta$ such that…” In other words, “if $\epsilon$ is a positive number, then there exists some positive $\delta$ such that…”</p>

<p><em>Here we see that the “true” antecedent regards $\epsilon$\, not $\delta$.</em> And indeed, the space related to $\epsilon$ is not $X$, but $Y$. Therefore, it is only natural that $V \subseteq Y$ appears in the antecedent of the topological definition.</p>

<h3 id="4-why-the-reasoning-behind-intuition-about-open-sets-is-incorrect">4. Why the Reasoning behind “Intuition about Open Sets” is Incorrect</h3>

<p>For convenience, let us denote that $x$ and $y$ are “close” as $x \sim y$. The said reasoning is based on the following <strong>incorrect</strong> intuition.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Incorrect Intuition about Open Sets.</strong> If $x \in U$ and $y \in U$, then $x \sim y$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>This should be corrected as follows:</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Correct Intuition about Open Sets.</strong> If $x \in U$ and $x \sim y$, then $y \in U$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A little thought reveals that this is quite trivial. For example, the set of all real numbers $\mathbb{R}$ is an open set. But surely, that does not mean that two arbitrary real numbers are always “close”. Conversely, the set $\lbrace  0 \rbrace $ is not an open set, but when $x, y \in \lbrace  0 \rbrace $, we have $x = y$, so $x$ and $y$ are as “close” as possible. Thus, according to the “incorrect intuition,” $\lbrace 0 \rbrace $ should be an open set.</p>

<p>On the other hand, with the “correct intuition,” it is evident that $\mathbb{R}$ is an open set while $\lbrace  0 \rbrace $ is not. When $x \in \mathbb{R}$, the real number $y$ that is “close” to $x$ is trivially included in $\mathbb{R}$. Meanwhile, $\lbrace  0 \rbrace $ does not include the real numbers that are “not equal to, but in the neighbourhood of” $0$, so it is not an open set.</p>

<p>Furthermore, with the “correct intuition,” the reason why the topological definition of continuous functions should be “backwards” also becomes clear. Let us first note that the following intuition about continuity are indeed correct.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Correct Intuition about Continuous Functions.</strong> If $x \sim y$, then $f(x) \sim f(y)$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now let us show that this intuitive deifinition of continuity is equivalent to the topological definition of continuity.</p>

<h4 id="intuitive-definition--topological-definition">Intuitive Definition =&gt; Topological Definition</h4>

<p>Let $f$ be “intuitively continuous”. We need to show that for an open set $V$, the preimage $U = f^{-1}[V]$ is an open set. Let $x \in U$ and assume $x \sim y$. Since $f$ is continuous, we have $f(x) \sim f(y)$. Moreover, since $V$ is an open set and $f(x) \in V$, it follows that $f(y) \in V$. Therefore, $y \in U$. □</p>

<h4 id="topological-definition--intuitive-definition">Topological Definition =&gt; Intuitive Definition</h4>

<p>Let $f$ be “topologically continuous”. We need to show that if $x \sim y$, then $f(x) \sim f(y)$. Let $V$ be a set that contains only points “close” to $f(x)$. Since $V$ is an open set, if $z \in V$ and $z \sim w$, then by the definition of $V$, we have $f(x) \sim z$, <em>which implies by transitivity of $\sim$</em> that $f(x) \sim w$, hence $w \in V$. Furthermore, since $U = f^{-1}[V]$ is an open set containing $x$, it follows that $y \in U$. Therefore, $f(y) \in V$, which means $f(x) \sim f(y)$. ■</p>

<p>Of course, the above discussion uses the somewhat dubious relation $\sim$, which is not rigorously defined. This may have caused some to feel uneasy in invoking the “transitivity of $\sim$”. However, I think using $\sim$ to understand open sets and continuity serves as a helpful intuition for those studying topology for the first time. Additionally, using non-standard analysis, one can rigorously define $x \sim y$ as $|x - y| = \epsilon$ — but that is a story for another time.</p>]]></content><author><name>최정담</name><email>dimenerno@kaist.ac.kr</email></author><category term="Logic" /><category term="Topology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Definition. A mapping $f: X \to Y$ is said to be continuous if for any open set $V \subseteq Y$, the preimage $f^{-1}[V] \subseteq X$ is also an open set.]]></summary></entry></feed>